<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../constitution_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<constitution country="Armenia">
    <meta>
        <source>
            <title/>
            <container/>
            <url>https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Armenia_2015</url>
        </source>
    </meta>
    <body>
        <preamble>PREAMBLE The Armenian People, accepting as a basis the fundamental principles of
                <sovereignty> Armenian statehood</sovereignty> and <nationalism>pan-national
                aspirations</nationalism> enshrined in the Declaration on the Independence of
            Armenia, having fulfilled the sacred behest of its <nationalism>freedom-loving
                ancestors</nationalism> to restore the sovereign state, dedicated to the
                <nationalism>strengthening and prosperity of the fatherland</nationalism>, with the
            aim of ensuring the <peace>freedom, general well-being, and civic solidarity</peace> of
            the generations, and affirming its commitment to universal values, adopts the
            Constitution of the Republic of Armenia. </preamble>
        <chapter>
            <chap_title>CHAPTER 1. THE FOUNDATIONS OF CONSTITUTIONAL ORDER </chap_title>


            <section>
                <s_text>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 1.</a_header>
                        <a_text> The Republic of Armenia is a <sovereignty>sovereign</sovereignty>,
                                <gov>democratic</gov>, social, and <gov>rule-of-law state</gov>.
                        </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 2.</a_header>
                        <a_text> In the Republic of Armenia, <consent>the power belongs to the
                                people</consent>. The people shall exercise its power through
                                <elections>free elections, referenda</elections>, as well as
                                <gov>through state and local self-government bodies and
                                officials</gov> prescribed by the Constitution. Usurpation of the
                            power by any organization or individual shall be a crime. </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 3.</a_header>
                        <a_text> The Human Being, His Dignity, Fundamental Rights, and Freedoms The
                            human being shall be the supreme value in the Republic of Armenia.
                                <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">The inalienable dignity of the human
                                being shall be the integral basis of his rights and
                                freedoms</ind_rights>. The respect for and protection of the
                            fundamental rights and freedoms of the human being and the citizen shall
                            be the duties of the public power. <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">The
                                public power shall be bound by the fundamental rights and freedoms
                                of the human being and the citizen as the directly applicable
                                law.</ind_rights>
                        </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 4.</a_header>
                        <a_text> The Principle of <separation>Separation and Balance of the Powers
                            </separation>State power shall be exercised in accordance with the
                            Constitution and the laws, based on the separation and balance of the
                                <separation>legislative, executive, and judicial
                            powers</separation>. </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 5.</a_header>
                        <a_text> The Hierarchy of Legal Norms The Constitution shall have supreme
                            legal force. <gov>Laws shall conform to the constitutional laws, and
                                sub-legislative normative legal acts shall conform to the
                                constitutional laws and laws.</gov> In case there are contradictions
                            between the norms of international treaties ratified by the Republic of
                            Armenia and the norms of laws, <international>the norms of the
                                international treaties shall be applied.</international>
                        </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 6.</a_header>
                        <a_text> The Principle of Legality State and <gov>local self-government
                                bodies and officials shall have the power to perform only such acts
                                for which they are empowered by the Constitution or laws</gov>.
                            Bodies prescribed by the Constitution, based on the Constitution and
                            laws and with the purpose of ensuring their implementation, may be
                            authorized by the law to adopt sub-legislative normative legal acts.
                            Authorizing norms shall comply with the principle of legal certainty.
                            Laws and sub-legislative normative legal acts shall come into force
                            after being published in the manner stipulated by law. </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 7.</a_header>
                        <a_text> The <elections>Suffrage Principles Elections</elections> of the
                            National Assembly and community councils, as well as referenda shall be
                            carried out on the basis of <ind_rights ind_type="vote">universal,
                                equal, free, and direct suffrage, by secret vote</ind_rights>.
                        </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 8.</a_header>
                        <a_text>
                            <parties p_type="multi">Ideological Pluralism and the Multipartisan
                                System Ideological pluralism and the multipartisan system shall be
                                guaranteed in the Republic of Armenia. Parties shall be formed and
                                operate freely. Equal legal opportunities for activities of the
                                parties shall be guaranteed by law. Parties shall promote the
                                formulation and expression of the people’s political will. The
                                structure and activities of parties may not contravene the
                                democratic principles.</parties>
                        </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 9.</a_header>
                        <a_text> Guaranteeing Local Self-Government <gov>Local self-government is
                                guaranteed in the Republic of Armenia as one of the essential
                                foundations of democracy</gov>. </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 10.</a_header>
                        <a_text> Guaranteeing Property <property prop_type="other">All forms of
                                property shall be recognized and equally protected in the Republic
                                of Armenia</property>. <property prop_type="public">Subsoils and
                                water resources shall be exclusive property of the State</property>.
                        </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 11.</a_header>
                        <a_text> The Economic Order The basis of the economic order in the Republic
                            of Armenia shall be the s<gov>ocial market economy</gov>, which shall be
                            based on <property prop_type="private"> private property,</property>
                            freedom of economic activity, free economic competition, and through the
                            state policy aimed at general <peace>economic well-being</peace> and
                            social justice. </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 12.</a_header>
                        <a_text> Preservation of the Environment and Sustainable Development The
                            state shall promote the preservation, improvement, and regeneration of
                            the environment, and the reasonable utilization of natural resources,
                            governed by the principle of sustainable development and taking into
                            account <nationalism>the responsibility towards future
                                generations</nationalism>. Everyone shall take care of the
                            preservation of the environment. </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 13.</a_header>
                        <a_text> Foreign Policy <international>The foreign policy of the Republic of
                                Armenia shall be conducted on the basis of international law with
                                the aim of establishing good-neighborly and mutually-beneficial
                                relations with all states. </international></a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 14.</a_header>
                        <a_text> The Armed Forces and Defense The armed forces of the Republic of
                            Armenia shall ensure the <sovereignty>defense, security, and territorial
                                integrity of the Republic of Armenia</sovereignty>, and the
                            inviolability of its borders. The armed forces of the Republic of
                            Armenia shall maintain neutrality in political matters and shall be
                            under civilian control. <ind_rights ind_type="arms">Every citizen shall
                                be obliged to participate in the defense of the Republic of Armenia
                                in the manner stipulated by law</ind_rights>. </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 15.</a_header>
                        <a_text> Promotion of Culture, Education, and Science, Protection of the
                                <language>Armenian language</language> and <nationalism>Cultural
                                Heritage</nationalism> The state shall promote the development of
                            culture, education, and science. The Armenian language and the cultural
                            heritage shall be under the care and protection of the state. </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 16.</a_header>
                        <a_text> Protection of the Family Family, being the natural and fundamental
                            cell of society and the basis for the preservation and reproduction of
                            the population, as well as motherhood and childhood shall be under
                            special protection and aegis of the state. </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 17.</a_header>
                        <a_text> The State and Religious Organizations <religion
                                r_type="church-state">The freedom of activity of religious
                                organizations</religion> shall be guaranteed in the Republic of
                            Armenia. <religion r_type="church-state">Religious organizations shall
                                be separate from the state</religion>. </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 18.</a_header>
                        <a_text> The Armenian Apostolic Holy Church The Republic of Armenia shall
                            recognize the <religion r_type="state-religion">exceptional mission of
                                the Armenian Apostolic Holy Church, as the national
                                church</religion>, in the spiritual life of the Armenian people, in
                            the development of its <nationalism>national culture, and in the
                                preservation of its national identity. </nationalism> The
                            relationship between the Republic of Armenia and the Armenian Apostolic
                            Holy Church may be regulated by a law. </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 19.</a_header>
                        <a_text> Ties with the Armenian Diaspora The Republic of Armenia shall carry
                            out a policy aimed at <nationalism>developing comprehensive ties and
                                preserving Armenianness with the Armenian Diaspora</nationalism>,
                            and shall facilitate repatriation. Based on international law, the
                            Republic of Armenia shall contribute to p<nationalism>rotecting the
                                Armenian language and Armenian historical and cultural values in
                                other countries</nationalism>, and advancing Armenian educational
                            and cultural life in such countries. </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 20.</a_header>
                        <a_text> The State Language of the Republic of Armenia <language>The
                                Armenian language shall be the state language of the Republic of
                                Armenia</language>. </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 21.</a_header>
                        <a_text> The Symbols of the Republic of Armenia <symbols>The flag of the
                                Republic of Armenia shall be tricolor - with equal horizontal
                                stripes of red, blue, and orange.</symbols>
                            <symbols>The coat of arms of the Republic of Armenia shall depict, in
                                the center on a shield, Mount Ararat with Noah’s ark and the coats
                                of arms of the four kingdoms of historical Armenia. The shield is
                                held by an eagle and a lion, while a sword, a branch, a sheaf, a
                                chain, and a ribbon are depicted below the shield.</symbols> The
                            detailed description of the flag and the coat of arms shall be
                            stipulated by law. <symbols>The anthem of the Republic of Armenia shall
                                be stipulated by law.</symbols>
                        </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 22.</a_header>
                        <a_text> The Capital of the Republic of Armenia T<capital>he capital of the
                                Republic of Armenia is Yerevan. </capital></a_text>
                    </article>
                </s_text>
            </section>
        </chapter></body>
</constitution>
