<?xml-model href="../constitution_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<constitution country="Azerbaijan">
    <meta>
        <source>
            <title>Azerbaijan Constitution</title>
            <container/>
            <url>https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Azerbaijan_2016</url>
        </source>
    </meta>
    <body>
        <preamble> PREAMBLE <consent>The Azerbaijan people</consent>,<nationalism> continuing the traditions of many centuries of
            their Statehood, guided by the principles which are reflected in the Constitutional Act
            on the State Independence of the Republic of Azerbaijan,</nationalism> wishing <!-- heres that lack of commitment again -->
            to provide welfare for all and everyone, and to establish justice, freedom, security, and being aware of their
            responsibility before past, present, and future generations, <sovereignty>exercise their sovereign
            right by solemnly declaring the following goals: to protect the independence,
            sovereignty and the territorial integrity of the Republic of Azerbaijan;</sovereignty><gov> to guarantee
            the democratic system within the framework of the Constitution; to achieve the
            realization of a civil society; to establish a law-governed,</gov> <religion r_type="church-state">secular state</religion> which assures
            the supremacy of the law as an expression of the will of the people; to assure to all a
            decent level of life in accordance with a just economic and social order; to live under
            conditions of friendship, peace and safety with other peoples, maintaining a commitment
            to general human values and to implement a mutually beneficial cooperation for these
            purposes. For the sake of the above stated high intentions, <gov>this Constitution shall be
            adopted through a nationwide referendum.</gov></preamble>
        <chapter>
            <chap_title>FIRST PART. GENERAL PROVISIONS Chapter I. The Power of the
                People</chap_title>
            <section>
                <s_text>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 1.</a_header>
                        <a_text><consent> Source of Power The Azerbaijan people are the sole source of State
                            power in the Republic of Azerbaijan.</consent><nationalism> The Azerbaijan people include
                            citizens of the Republic of Azerbaijan that live in the territory of the
                            Republic of Azerbaijan or outside the country and that obey the
                            Azerbaijan State and its Laws.</nationalism><international> This does not exclude norms defined by
                            the international law.</international></a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 2.</a_header>
                        <a_text><sovereignty> The Sovereignty of the People The Azerbaijan people have the
                            sovereign right to freely and independently decide their fate and to
                            establish the form of its own governance.</sovereignty><sovereignty> The Azerbaijan people
                            implement their sovereign right</sovereignty><elections> by universal elections-referendum and by
                            their representatives elected on the basis of universal, direct and
                            equal elections by secret and individual ballot.</elections></a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 3.</a_header>
                        <a_text><elections> Matters to be determined by Referendum The Azerbaijan people can
                            settle every matter connected with their rights and interests by
                            referendum. The below-mentioned matters can only be determined by
                            referendum: The adoption of the Constitution of the Republic of
                            Azerbaijan and the introduction of changes to it. The change of State
                            borders of the Republic of Azerbaijan. A referendum cannot be held
                            concerning the following matters: Taxes and the state budget; Amnesty
                            and pardon; The election, appointment or confirmation of officials,
                            whose election, appointment or confirmation are within the competence of
                            the legislative organs and (or) the executive power.</elections></a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 4.</a_header>
                        <a_text> T<consent>he Right to Represent the People No one except authoritative
                            representatives elected by the people have the right to represent, speak
                            for and address on behalf of the people.</consent></a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 5.</a_header>
                        <a_text> <nationalism>The Unity of the People The Azerbaijan people are united. The unity
                            of the Azerbaijan people constitutes the foundation of the Azerbaijan
                            State. The Republic of Azerbaijan is wholly and indivisibly the Homeland
                            for all the citizens of the Republic of Azerbaijan.</nationalism></a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 6.</a_header>
                        <a_text><elections> Banning of Power Usurpation No part of the Azerbaijan people,
                            either an individual, or a social group or an organization has the right
                            to usurp the authority of the Azerbaijan people to exercise the power.
                            Power usurpation is the most serious crime directed against the
                            people.</elections></a_text>
                    </article>
                </s_text>
            </section>
        </chapter>
    </body>
</constitution>
