
<?xml-model href="../constitution_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<constitution country="Belarus">
    <meta>
        <source>
            <title>Belarus 1994 (rev. 2004)</title>
            <container>Constitute Project</container>
            <url>https://www.constituteproject.org</url>
        </source>
    </meta>
   
        <body>
            <preamble>PREAMBLE
         We, the People of the Republic of Belarus, (of Belarus), proceeding from the
        responsibility for the present and future of Belarus, <nationalism>recognising ourselves as a
        full-fledged subject of the international community</nationalism> and confirming our adherence to values
        common to all mankind, <ind_rights ind_type="citizenship">founding ourselves on our inalienable right to self-determination,
        supported by the centuries-long history of development of Belarusian statehood</ind_rights>, striving to
        assert the <ind_rights ind_type="misc">rights and freedoms of every citizen of the Republic of Belarus</ind_rights>, desiring to
        <gov>maintain civic concord, firm foundations of government by the people and a state based on
        the rule of law</gov>, adopt hereby this Constitution - the Fundamental Law of the Republic of
        Belarus.</preamble>
    <chapter>
        
          <chap_title>  SECTION 1. FUNDAMENTALS OF THE CONSTITUTIONAL SYSTEM </chap_title>
        <section>
            <s_text>
                <article><a_header>Article 1 </a_header>
                    <a_text>The Republic of Belarus is a <gov>unitary, <!--would unitary count as gov or
                        parties?-->
                    democratic, social state</gov> based on the rule of law. The Republic of Belarus
                    exercises supreme control and absolute <sovereignty>authority over the whole of its territory
                    and implements an independent domestic and foreign policy</sovereignty>. The Republic of
                    Belarus shall defend its <sovereignty>independence and territorial integrity, its
                    constitutional system, and safeguard lawfulness and law and order</sovereignty>.</a_text></article>

                <article>
                    <a_header>Article 2</a_header>
                    <a_text> The <ind_rights ind_type="misc">individual, his rights, freedoms and guarantees to secure them are
                        the supreme value and goal of the society and the State</ind_rights>. The State shall
                        assume responsibility before the citizen to <ind_rights ind_type='liberty'>create the conditions for free
                        and dignified development of his personality</ind_rights>. The citizen shall assume
                        responsibility before the State to discharge unwaveringly the duties imposed
                        upon him by the Constitution.</a_text>
                </article>
                <article>
                    <a_header>Article 3 </a_header> <!--the tagging for tgis is not
                        that good need help-->
                    <a_text> The people shall be the <nationalism>sole source of state power</nationalism> and the <sovereignty>bearer of
                        sovereignty</sovereignty> in the Republic of Belarus. The <gov>people shall exercise their
                        power directly, through representative and other bodies in the forms and
                        within the confines determined by the Constitution</gov>. Any <consent>actions aimed at
                        changing the constitutional system</consent> and <consent>seizing state power by forcible means
                        or by way of any other violation of the laws</consent> of the Republic of Belarus
                        shall be punishable by law.</a_text>
                </article>
                <article>
                    <a_header>Article 4</a_header>
                    <a_text> <gov>Democracy</gov> in the Republic of Belarus shall be exercised on the basis of
                       <parties p_type="multi"> diversity of political institutions, ideologies and
                           opinions</parties>. The <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">ideology
                        of political parties, religious or other public associations, social groups
                        may not be made mandatory for citizens</ind_rights>.</a_text>
                </article>
                <article>
                    <a_header>Article 5</a_header>
                    <a_text> Political parties and other public associations acting within the
                        framework of the Constitution and laws of the Republic of Belarus shall
                        contribute to ascertaining and <gov>expressing the political will of the citizens</gov>
                        and <elections>shall participate in elections</elections>. Political parties and other public
                        associations <consent>shall have the right to use state mass media </consent>under the
                        procedure determined by the legislation. The foundation and activities of
                        political parties and other public associations, that aim to change the
                        constitutional system by force or <consent>conduct propaganda of war, social, ethnic,
                        religious and racial hatred, shall be prohibited</consent>.</a_text>
                </article>
                <article>
                    <a_header>Article 6</a_header>
                    <a_text>State power in the Republic of Belarus shall be exercised on the
                        principle of <separation>its separation into legislative, executive, and judicial
                        powers</separation>. State bodies within the confines of their powers, shall be
                        <separation>independent: they shall interact among themselves, check and balance one
                        another</separation>.</a_text>
                </article>
                <article>
                    <a_header>Article 7</a_header> <!--unsure of this one too -->
                    <a_text>The Republic of Belarus shall be bound by the principle of supremacy of
                        law. The State and all the bodies and officials thereof shall operate within
                        the confines of the Constitution and acts of legislation adopted in
                        accordance therewith. <gov>Legal acts or specific provisions thereof which have
                        been recognised under the procedure specified by law as contradicting the
                        provisions of the Constitution shall have no legal force</gov>. Normative acts of
                        state bodies shall be published or promulgated by other means specified by
                        law.</a_text>
                </article>
                <article>
                    <a_header>Article 8 </a_header>
                    <a_text>The Republic of Belarus shall recognize the supremacy of the generally
                        recognised principles of <international>international law and shall ensure the compliance
                        of laws </international>therewith. The Republic of Belarus in conformity with the rules of
                        international law m<international>ay on a voluntary basis enter interstate formations and
                        withdraw</international> from them. <sovereignty>Conclusion of treaties that are contrary to the
                        Constitution shall not be permitted</sovereignty>.</a_text>
                </article>
                <article>
                    <a_header>Article 9 </a_header>
                    <a_text> The territory of the Republic of Belarus shall be the natural condition
                        of the existence and spatial limit of the <ind_rights ind_type="citizenship">people's self-determination</ind_rights>, and
                        the basis for its prosperity and the <sovereignty>sovereignty</sovereignty> of the Republic of Belarus.
                        The territory of Belarus shall be integral and inalienable. The territory
                        shall be divided into regions (oblasts), districts, cities and other
                        administrative and territorial units. The <consent>administrative and territorial
                        division of the State is determined by the legislation</consent>.</a_text>
                </article>
                <article>
                    <a_header>Article 10 </a_header>
                    <a_text> A citizen of the Republic of Belarus shall be<ind_rights ind_type="legal"> guaranteed protection and
                        patronage of the State both in the territory of Belarus</ind_rights> and
                        <international>beyond</international>. <ind_rights ind_type="citizenship">No one
                        may be deprived of citizenship of the Republic of Belarus or the right to
                        change his citizenship</ind_rights>. A <ind_rights ind_type="citizenship">citizen of the Republic of Belarus may not be
                        extradited to a foreign state</ind_rights>, unless otherwise provided by treaties to
                        which the Republic of Belarus is a party. <nationalism>Acquisition and loss of the
                        citizenship shall be carried out in accordance with the law</nationalism>.</a_text>
                </article>
                <article>
                    <a_header>Article 11</a_header>
                    <a_text>Foreign nationals and stateless persons in the territory of Belarus
                       <ind_rights ind_type="racial-equality"> shall enjoy the rights and freedoms and execute duties on equal terms with
                        the citizens</ind_rights> of the Republic of Belarus, unless otherwise specified by the
                        Constitution, laws and treaties.</a_text>
                </article>
                <article>
                    <a_header>Article 12</a_header>
                    <a_text>The Republic of Belarus may <ind_rights ind_type="racial-equality">grant the right of asylum to persons
                        persecuted in other states for political or religious beliefs or their
                        ethnic affiliation</ind_rights>.</a_text>
                </article>
                <article>
                    <a_header>Article 13</a_header>
                    <a_text> Property may be <property prop_type="public">state-owned </property>or
                        <property prop_type="private">private</property>. The State shall
                        <ind_rights ind_type="misc">grant equal
                        rights to all to conduct economic and other activities</ind_rights>, except for those
                        prohibited by law, and guarantee equal protection and equal conditions for
                        the development of all forms of ownership. The State shall<separation> promote the
                        development of co-operation</separation>. The State shall guarantee to all equal
                        opportunities for <ind_rights ind_type="misc">free utilisation of abilities and property for
                        entrepreneurial and other types of economic activities which are not
                        prohibited by the law</ind_rights>. The State shall <consent>regulate economic activities in the
                        interests of the individual and society, and shall ensure the direction and
                        co-ordination of state and private economic activity for social purposes</consent>.
                        The <property prop_type="public">mineral wealth, waters and forests are the exclusive property of the
                        State</property>. The <property prop_type="public">land for agricultural use is the property of the State</property>. Law may
                       <property prop_type="public"> determine facilities that are in the ownership of the State only, or
                        establish a special procedure for their transfer to private ownership, or
                        grant the State an exclusive right to conduct certain types of activity</property>. The
                        State shall guarantee the <ind_rights ind_type="misc">working people the right to participate in
                        management of enterprises, organizations and establishments to enhance their
                        efficiency and improve social and economic living standards</ind_rights>.</a_text>
                </article>
                <article>
                    <a_header>Article 14</a_header>
                    <a_text>The State shall regulate relations among <ind_rights ind_type="legal">social, ethnic and other
                        communities on the basis of the principles of equality before the law and
                        respect of their rights and interests</ind_rights>. Relations in the<separation> social and labour
                        sphere between the bodies of state administration, associations of employers
                        and trade unions shall be exercised on the principles of social partnership
                        and interaction of parties</separation>.</a_text>
                </article>
                <article>
                    <a_header>Article 15</a_header>
                    <a_text>The State shall bear responsibility for preserving the <ind_rights ind_type="legal">historic,
                        cultural and spiritual heritage, and for free development of the cultures of
                        all ethnic communities</ind_rights> residing in the Republic of Belarus.</a_text>
                </article>
                <article>
                    <a_header>Article 16</a_header>
                    <a_text><religion r_type="neutral">Religions and faiths shall be equal before the law. Relations between
                        the State and religious organizations shall be regulated by law with regard
                        to their influence</religion> on formation of spiritual, cultural and state traditions
                        of the Belarusian people. The activities of religious organisations, their
                        bodies and representatives, that are directed against the <sovereignty>sovereignty of the
                        Republic of Belarus, its constitutional system and civic concord</sovereignty>, or involve
                       <ind_rights ind_type="misc"> violation of civil rights and freedoms of its citizens </ind_rights>as well as impede the
                        execution of state, public and family duties by its citizens or are
                        detrimental to their health and morality shall be prohibited.</a_text>
                </article>
                <article>
                    <a_header> Article 17 </a_header>
                    <a_text> The <language>Belarusian and Russian languages</language> shall be the official languages of
                        the Republic of Belarus</a_text>
                </article>
                <article>
                    <a_header>Article 18 </a_header>
                    <a_text> In its foreign policy the Republic of Belarus shall proceed from the
                        principles of<international> equality of states, non-use of force or the threat of force,
                        inviolability of frontiers, peaceful settlement of disputes,
                        non-interference in internal affairs and other generally recognised
                        principles and norms of the international law</international>. The Republic of Belarus aims
                        at making its <international>territory a nuclear-free zone, and the state neutral</international>.</a_text>
                </article>
                <article>
                    <a_header>Article 19 </a_header>
                    <a_text>The symbols of the Republic of Belarus as a sovereign state shall be its
                        <symbols>national flag, national emblem and national anthem</symbols>.</a_text>
                </article>
                <article>
                    <a_header>Article 20 </a_header>
                    <a_text>The capital of the Republic of Belarus is the city of <capital>Minsk</capital>. The status
                        of the city of Minsk shall be determined by the law.</a_text>
                </article>
            </s_text>
        </section></chapter>
        </body>    
</constitution>
