<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<constitutions>
    <constitution country="Armenia">
        <meta>
            <source>
                <title/>
                <container/>
                <url>https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Armenia_2015</url>
            </source>
        </meta>
        <body>
            <preamble>PREAMBLE The Armenian People, accepting as a basis the fundamental principles of
                <sovereignty> Armenian statehood</sovereignty> and <nationalism>pan-national
                    aspirations</nationalism> enshrined in the Declaration on the Independence of
                Armenia, having fulfilled the sacred behest of its <nationalism>freedom-loving
                    ancestors</nationalism> to restore the <sovereignty>sovereign state</sovereignty>, dedicated to the
                <nationalism>strengthening and prosperity of the fatherland</nationalism>, with the
                aim of <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">ensuring the freedom</ind_rights>, <peace>general well-being, and civic solidarity</peace> of
                the generations, and affirming its commitment to universal values, adopts the
                Constitution of the Republic of Armenia. </preamble>
            <chapter>
                <chap_title>CHAPTER 1. THE FOUNDATIONS OF CONSTITUTIONAL ORDER </chap_title>
                
                
                <section>
                    <s_text>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 1.</a_header>
                            <a_text> The Republic of Armenia is a <sovereignty>sovereign</sovereignty>,
                                <gov>democratic</gov>, social, and <gov>rule-of-law state</gov>.
                            </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 2.</a_header>
                            <a_text> In the Republic of Armenia, <consent>the power belongs to the
                                people. The people shall exercise its power</consent> through
                                <elections>free elections, referenda</elections>, as well as
                                <levels l_type="neutral">through state and local self-government bodies and
                                    officials</levels> prescribed by the Constitution. <treason>Usurpation of the
                                        power by any organization or individual shall be a crime</treason>. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 3. The Human Being, His Dignity, Fundamental Rights, and Freedoms</a_header>
                            <a_text>  The human being shall be the supreme value in the Republic of Armenia.
                                <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">The inalienable dignity of the human
                                    being shall be the integral basis of his rights and
                                    freedoms</ind_rights>. The respect for and protection of the
                                <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">fundamental rights and freedoms of the human being and the citizen</ind_rights> shall
                                be the duties of the public power. <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">The
                                    public power shall be bound by the fundamental rights and freedoms
                                    of the human being and the citizen as the directly applicable
                                    law.</ind_rights>
                            </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 4. The Principle of Separation and Balance of the Powers</a_header>
                            <a_text> 
                                State power shall be exercised in accordance with the
                                Constitution and the laws, based on the <separation>separation and balance of the
                                    legislative, executive, and judicial
                                    powers</separation>. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 5. The Hierarchy of Legal Norms</a_header>
                            <a_text> The Constitution shall have supreme
                                legal force. <gov>Laws shall conform to the constitutional laws, and
                                    sub-legislative normative legal acts shall conform to the
                                    constitutional laws and laws.</gov> In case there are contradictions
                                between the norms of international treaties ratified by the Republic of
                                Armenia and the norms of laws, <international>the norms of the
                                    international treaties shall be applied.</international>
                            </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 6. The Principle of Legality</a_header>
                            <a_text> <levels l_type="unitary">State and local self-government
                                bodies and officials shall have the power to perform only such acts
                                for which they are empowered by the Constitution or laws</levels>.
                                Bodies prescribed by the Constitution, based on the Constitution and
                                laws and with the purpose of ensuring their implementation, may be
                                authorized by the law to adopt sub-legislative normative legal acts.
                                Authorizing norms shall comply with the principle of legal certainty.
                                Laws and sub-legislative normative legal acts shall come into force
                                after being published in the manner stipulated by law. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 7. The Suffrage Principles </a_header>
                            <a_text> <elections>Elections of the
                                National Assembly and community councils, as well as referenda</elections> shall be
                                carried out on the basis of <ind_rights ind_type="vote">universal,
                                    equal, free, and direct suffrage, by secret vote</ind_rights>.
                            </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 8. >Ideological Pluralism and the Multipartisan System</a_header>
                            <a_text>
                                <parties p_type="multi">
                                    Ideological pluralism and the multipartisan system shall be
                                    guaranteed in the Republic of Armenia. Parties shall be formed and
                                    operate freely.</parties> Equal legal opportunities for activities of the
                                parties shall be guaranteed by law. <consent>Parties shall promote the
                                    formulation and expression of the people’s political will</consent>. <treason>The
                                        structure and activities of parties may not contravene the
                                        democratic principles</treason>.
                            </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 9. Guaranteeing Local Self-Government</a_header>
                            <a_text>  <levels l_type="neutral">Local self-government is
                                guaranteed in the Republic of Armenia as one of the essential
                                foundations of democracy</levels>. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 10. Guaranteeing Property </a_header>
                            <a_text> <property prop_type="other">All forms of
                                property shall be recognized and equally protected in the Republic
                                of Armenia</property>. <property prop_type="public">Subsoils and
                                    water resources shall be exclusive property of the State</property>.
                            </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 11.  The Economic Order</a_header>
                            <a_text> The basis of the economic order in the Republic
                                of Armenia shall be the <economic e_type="mixed">social market economy</economic>, which shall be
                                based on <property prop_type="private"> private property,</property>
                                freedom of economic activity, free economic competition, and through the
                                state policy aimed at general <peace>economic well-being</peace> and
                                social justice. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 12.  Preservation of the Environment and Sustainable Development </a_header>
                            <a_text> The
                                state shall promote the preservation, improvement, and regeneration of
                                the environment, and the reasonable utilization of natural resources,
                                governed by the principle of sustainable development and taking into
                                account <nationalism>the responsibility towards future
                                    generations</nationalism>. Everyone shall take care of the
                                preservation of the environment. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 13. Foreign Policy </a_header>
                            <a_text> <international>The foreign policy of the Republic of
                                Armenia shall be conducted on the basis of international law with
                                the aim of establishing good-neighborly and mutually-beneficial
                                relations with all states. </international></a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 14.The Armed Forces and Defense</a_header>
                            <a_text>  The armed forces of the Republic of
                                Armenia shall ensure the <sovereignty>defense, security, and territorial
                                    integrity of the Republic of Armenia</sovereignty>, and the
                                inviolability of its borders. The armed forces of the Republic of
                                Armenia shall maintain neutrality in political matters and shall be
                                under civilian control. Every citizen shall
                                be obliged to participate in the defense of the Republic of Armenia
                                in the manner stipulated by law. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 15.  Promotion of Culture, Education, and Science, Protection of the
                                Armenian language and Cultural
                                Heritage</a_header>
                            <a_text>The state shall promote the development of
                                <nationalism>culture</nationalism>, education, and science. <language lang_type="native">The Armenian language</language> and the <nationalism>cultural
                                    heritage</nationalism> shall be under the care and protection of the state. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 16.Protection of the Family</a_header>
                            <a_text>  Family, being the natural and fundamental
                                cell of society and the basis for the preservation and reproduction of
                                the population, as well as motherhood and childhood shall be under
                                special protection and aegis of the state. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 17.The State and Religious Organizations</a_header>
                            <a_text>  <religion
                                r_type="secular">The freedom of activity of religious
                                organizations</religion> shall be guaranteed in the Republic of
                                Armenia. <religion r_type="secular">Religious organizations shall
                                    be separate from the state</religion>. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 18. The Armenian Apostolic Holy Church </a_header>
                            <a_text>The Republic of Armenia shall
                                recognize the <religion r_type="state-religion">exceptional mission of
                                    the Armenian Apostolic Holy Church, as the national
                                    church</religion>, in the spiritual life of the Armenian people, in
                                the development of its <nationalism>national culture, and in the
                                    preservation of its national identity. </nationalism> The
                                relationship between the Republic of Armenia and the Armenian Apostolic
                                Holy Church may be regulated by a law. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 19.Ties with the Armenian Diaspora </a_header>
                            <a_text> The Republic of Armenia shall carry
                                out a policy aimed at <nationalism>developing comprehensive ties and
                                    preserving Armenianness with the Armenian Diaspora</nationalism>,
                                and shall facilitate repatriation. Based on international law, the
                                Republic of Armenia shall contribute to <language lang_type="native">protecting the
                                    Armenian language </language><nationalism>and Armenian historical and cultural values in
                                        other countries</nationalism>, and advancing Armenian educational
                                and cultural life in such countries. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 20.The State Language of the Republic of Armenia </a_header>
                            <a_text> <language lang_type="native">The
                                Armenian language shall be the state language</language> of the Republic of
                                Armenia. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 21.The Symbols of the Republic of Armenia </a_header>
                            <a_text> <symbols>The flag of the
                                Republic of Armenia shall be tricolor - with equal horizontal
                                stripes of red, blue, and orange.</symbols>
                                <symbols>The coat of arms of the Republic of Armenia shall depict, in
                                    the center on a shield, Mount Ararat with Noah’s ark and the coats
                                    of arms of the four kingdoms of historical Armenia. The shield is
                                    held by an eagle and a lion, while a sword, a branch, a sheaf, a
                                    chain, and a ribbon are depicted below the shield.</symbols> The
                                detailed description of the flag and the coat of arms shall be
                                stipulated by law. <symbols>The anthem of the Republic of Armenia shall
                                    be stipulated by law.</symbols>
                            </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 22.The Capital of the Republic of Armenia </a_header>
                            <a_text> <capital>The capital of the
                                Republic of Armenia is Yerevan. </capital></a_text>
                        </article>
                    </s_text>
                </section>
            </chapter></body>
    </constitution>
    <constitution country="Azerbaijan">
        <meta>
            <source>
                <title>Azerbaijan Constitution</title>
                <container/>
                <url>https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Azerbaijan_2016</url>
            </source>
        </meta>
        <body>
            <preamble> PREAMBLE The Azerbaijan people,<nationalism> continuing the traditions of many centuries of
                their Statehood</nationalism>, guided by the principles which are reflected in the Constitutional Act
                on the State Independence of the Republic of Azerbaijan, wishing
                to provide <peace>welfare for all and everyone</peace>, and to <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">establish justice, freedom, security,</ind_rights> and being aware of <nationalism>their
                    responsibility before past, present, and future generations</nationalism>, <sovereignty>exercise their sovereign
                        right by solemnly declaring the following goals: to protect the independence,
                        sovereignty and the territorial integrity of the Republic of Azerbaijan;</sovereignty><gov> to guarantee
                            the democratic system within the framework of the Constitution; to achieve the
                            realization of a civil society; to establish a law-governed,</gov> <religion r_type="secular">secular state</religion> which assures
                the supremacy of the law as an <consent>expression of the will of the people</consent>; <peace>to assure to all a
                    decent level of life</peace> in accordance with a just economic and social order; <peace>to live under
                        conditions of friendship, peace and safety with other peoples</peace>, maintaining a commitment
                to general human values and to implement a mutually beneficial cooperation for these
                purposes. For the sake of the above stated high intentions, <elections>this Constitution shall be
                    adopted through a nationwide referendum.</elections></preamble><!-- Election -->
            <chapter>
                <chap_title>FIRST PART. GENERAL PROVISIONS Chapter I. The Power of the
                    People</chap_title>
                <section>
                    <s_text>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 1. Source of Power</a_header>
                            <a_text> <consent>The Azerbaijan people are the sole source of State
                                power in the Republic of Azerbaijan</consent>.<nationalism> The Azerbaijan people include
                                    citizens of the Republic of Azerbaijan that live in the territory of the
                                    Republic of Azerbaijan or outside the country and that obey the
                                    Azerbaijan State and its Laws.</nationalism><international> This does not exclude norms defined by
                                        the international law.</international></a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 2. The Sovereignty of the People</a_header>
                            <a_text><sovereignty> The Azerbaijan people have the
                                sovereign right to freely and independently decide their fate and to
                                establish the form of its own governance.</sovereignty><sovereignty> The Azerbaijan people
                                    implement their sovereign right</sovereignty><elections> by universal elections-referendum and by
                                        their representatives elected on the basis of universal, direct and
                                        equal elections by secret and individual ballot.</elections></a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 3. Matters to be determined by Referendum </a_header>
                            <a_text><elections>The Azerbaijan people can
                                settle every matter connected with their rights and interests by
                                referendum</elections>. <elections>The below-mentioned matters can only be determined by
                                    referendum: The adoption of the Constitution of the Republic of
                                    Azerbaijan and the introduction of changes to it. The change of State
                                    borders of the Republic of Azerbaijan</elections>. <elections>A referendum cannot be held
                                        concerning the following matters: Taxes and the state budget; Amnesty
                                        and pardon; The election, appointment or confirmation of officials,
                                        whose election, appointment or confirmation are within the competence of
                                        the legislative organs and (or) the executive power.</elections></a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 4. The Right to Represent the People</a_header>
                            <a_text> <consent> No one except authoritative
                                representatives elected by the people have the right to represent, speak
                                for and address on behalf of the people.</consent></a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 5. The Unity of the People</a_header>
                            <a_text> <nationalism> The Azerbaijan people are united. The unity
                                of the Azerbaijan people constitutes the foundation of the Azerbaijan
                                State. The Republic of Azerbaijan is wholly and indivisibly the Homeland
                                for all the citizens of the Republic of Azerbaijan.</nationalism></a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 6. Banning of Power Usurpation</a_header>
                            <a_text><treason> No part of the Azerbaijan people,
                                either an individual, or a social group or an organization has the right
                                to usurp the authority of the Azerbaijan people to exercise the power.
                                Power usurpation is the most serious crime directed against the
                                people.</treason></a_text>
                        </article>
                    </s_text>
                </section>
            </chapter>
        </body>
    </constitution>
    <constitution country="Estonia">
        <meta>
            <source>
                <title/>
                <container/>
                <url>https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Estonia_2015</url>
            </source>
        </meta>
        <body><preamble>PREAMBLE With unwavering faith and a steadfast will to strengthen and develop
            the state, which embodies the <sovereignty>inextinguishable right of the people of
                Estonia to national self-determination</sovereignty> and which was proclaimed on 24
            February 1918, which is founded on <gov>liberty, justice and the rule of law</gov>,
            which is created to <peace>protect the peace and defend the people against aggression
                from the outside</peace>, and which forms a pledge to present and future generations
            for their social progress and welfare, which must guarantee the <peace>preservation of
                the Estonian people</peace>, <language lang_type="native">the Estonian
                    language</language> and the <nationalism>Estonian culture through the
                        ages</nationalism>, the people of Estonia, on the basis of Article 1 of the
            Constitution which <elections>entered into force in 1938, and in the
                referendum</elections> held on 28 June 1992, have adopted the following
            Constitution. </preamble>
            <chapter>
                <chap_title>CHAPTER I. GENERAL PROVISIONS</chap_title>
                <section>
                    <s_text>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 1 </a_header>
                            <a_text>Estonia is an <sovereignty>independent and sovereign
                            </sovereignty><gov>democratic republic</gov> wherein the
                                <consent>supreme power of state is vested in the people</consent>.
                                <sovereignty>The independence and sovereignty of Estonia are
                                    timeless and inalienable</sovereignty>. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 2</a_header>
                            <a_text> The land, territorial waters and airspace of the Estonian state are
                                an inseparable and indivisible whole. Estonia is politically a <levels
                                    l_type="unitary">unitary state</levels> wherein <gov>administrative
                                        division shall be provided by law</gov>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 3</a_header>
                            <a_text> The state authority shall be exercised solely pursuant to the
                                Constitution and laws which are in conformity therewith.
                                <international>Generally recognized principles and rules of
                                    international law are an inseparable part of the Estonian legal
                                    system</international>. Laws shall be published in the prescribed
                                manner. Only published laws have obligatory force. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 4 </a_header>
                            <a_text>The <gov>activities of the Riigikogu (Parliament of Estonia), the
                                President of the Republic, the Government of the Republic, and the
                                courts</gov> shall be organized on the <separation>principle of
                                    separation and balance of powers</separation>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 5 </a_header>
                            <a_text><property prop_type="public">The natural wealth and resources of
                                Estonia are national riches which shall be used
                                economically</property>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 6</a_header>
                            <a_text> The official <language lang_type="native">language of Estonia is
                                Estonian </language>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 7</a_header>
                            <a_text>The <symbols>national colors of Estonia are blue, black and
                                white</symbols>. <symbols>The design of the national flag and the
                                    national coat of arms shall be provided by law.</symbols></a_text>
                        </article>
                    </s_text>
                </section>
            </chapter></body>
    </constitution>
    <constitution country="Georgia">
        <meta>
            <source>
                <title>Georgia 1995 (rev. 2018)</title>
                <container>Constitute Project</container>
                <url>https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Georgia_2018</url>
            </source>
        </meta>
        
        <body>
            <preamble>PREAMBLE We, the citizens of Georgia - whose firm will it is to establish a
                <gov>democratic social order</gov>, economic freedom, and a legal and a social
                state; to secure <international>universally recognised human rights and
                    freedoms</international>; and to enhance <sovereignty>state
                        independence</sovereignty> and <peace>peaceful relations with other peoples</peace>
                - drawing on the <nationalism>centuries-old traditions of the statehood of the Georgian
                    nation and the historical and legal legacy of the Constitution of Georgia of
                    1921</nationalism>, proclaim this Constitution before<religion r_type="neutral"> God
                    </religion>and the nation. </preamble>
            <chapter>
                
                <chap_title>CHAPTER ONE. GENERAL PROVISIONS</chap_title>
                <section>
                    <s_text>
                        <!--regex: (Article [1-9]+).*?\n to find a_heading-->
                        <article>
                            <a_header> Article 1. State sovereignty </a_header>
                            <!--would nationalism also count as history-->
                            <a_text> Georgia is an <sovereignty>independent, unified and indivisible
                                state</sovereignty> as confirmed by the <nationalism>Referendum of
                                    31 March 1991 held in the entire territory of the country, including
                                    the Autonomous Soviet Socialist Republic of Abkhazia and the former
                                    Autonomous Region of South Ossetia, and by the Act of Restoration of
                                    State Independence of Georgia of 9 April 1991</nationalism>. The
                                territory of the state of Georgia was determined on 21 December 1991.
                                The territorial integrity of Georgia and the inviolability of the state
                                border is confirmed by the Constitution and laws of Georgia, and
                                <international>recognised by the world community of nations and by
                                    international organisations</international>. The <treason>alienation
                                        of the territory of the state of Georgia shall be
                                        prohibited</treason>. The <international>state border may be changed
                                            only by a bilateral agreement with a neighbouring
                                            state</international>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        
                        <article>
                            <a_header> Article 2. State symbols </a_header>
                            <a_text>'Georgia' is the name of the state of Georgia.
                                <capital>Tbilisi</capital> is the capital of Georgia. <language
                                    lang_type="native">The official language of Georgia shall be
                                    Georgian, and, in the Autonomous Republic of Abkhazia, also
                                    Abkhazian. The official language is protected by the organic
                                    law</language>. The <symbols>state flag, the coat of arms, and the
                                        anthem of Georgia are established by the organic law</symbols>,
                                which shall be revised in accordance with the procedure established for
                                revising the Constitution.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        
                        <article>
                            <a_header> Article 3. Democracy </a_header>
                            <a_text> Georgia is a <gov>democratic republic</gov>. <consent>People are
                                the source of state authority</consent>. People exercise power
                                through their <parties p_type="multi">representatives, as well as
                                    through referendums</parties> and other forms of <gov>direct
                                        democracy</gov>. No one shall have the right to seize power. The
                                current term of a body elected in general<elections> elections shall not
                                    be extended or reduced by the Constitution or law</elections>.
                                <parties p_type="multi">Political parties</parties> shall
                                participate in the formation and exercise of the political will of the
                                people. The activities of political parties shall be based on the
                                principles of freedom, equality, transparency, and <parties
                                    p_type="multi">intra-party democracy</parties>. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        
                        <article>
                            <a_header> Article 4. Legal state </a_header>
                            <a_text> Georgia is a <sovereignty>legal state</sovereignty>. The State
                                acknowledges and protects <international>universally recognised human
                                    rights and freedoms as eternal and supreme human values. While
                                    exercising authority, the people and the State shall be bound by
                                    these rights and freedoms as directly applicable
                                    law</international>. The Constitution<international> shall not deny
                                        other universally recognised human rights and freedoms that are not
                                        explicitly referred to herein</international>, but that inherently
                                derive from the principles of the Constitution. <separation>State
                                    authority shall be exercised based on the principle of the
                                    separation of powers</separation>. <consent>State authority shall be
                                        exercised within the ambit of the Constitution and law</consent>.
                                The Constitution of Georgia shall be the supreme law of the State.
                                General rules for the adoption and issuance of legislative and other
                                normative acts, and their hierarchy, shall be determined by the organic
                                law.<international> The legislation of Georgia shall comply with the
                                    universally recognised principles and norms of international
                                    law</international>. <international>An international treaty of
                                        Georgia shall take precedence over domestic normative
                                    </international>acts <sovereignty>unless it comes into conflict with the
                                        Constitution or the Constitutional Agreement of
                                        Georgia</sovereignty>. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header> Article 5. Social state </a_header>
                            <a_text> Georgia is a <gov>social state</gov>. <ind_rights ind_type="misc"
                                >The State shall take care of strengthening the principles of social
                                justice, social equality and social solidarity within
                                society</ind_rights>. The <ind_rights ind_type="misc">State shall
                                    take care of the equitable socio-economic and demographic
                                    development in the entire territory of the country</ind_rights>.
                                Special conditions for the development of high mountain regions shall be
                                determined by law.<ind_rights ind_type="misc"> The State shall take care
                                    of human health care and social protection, ensuring the subsistence
                                    minimum and decent housing, and protecting the welfare of the
                                    family</ind_rights>. <ind_rights ind_type="misc">The State shall
                                        promote the employment of citizens. Conditions for providing the
                                        subsistence minimum shall be determined by law</ind_rights>.
                                <ind_rights ind_type="misc">The State shall take care of
                                    environmental protection and the rational use of natural
                                    resources</ind_rights>. <nationalism>The State shall take care of
                                        the protection of national values, identity and cultural
                                        heritage</nationalism>, and of the development of <ind_rights
                                            ind_type="misc">education, science and culture</ind_rights>. The
                                State shall take care of the <ind_rights ind_type="misc">development of
                                    sports, establishing a healthy lifestyle, and engaging children and
                                    youth in physical education and sports</ind_rights>. The State shall
                                take care of<ind_rights ind_type="citizenship"> maintaining and
                                    developing connections with the homeland for Georgian compatriots
                                    residing abroad</ind_rights>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        
                        <article>
                            <a_header> Article 6. Economic freedom </a_header>
                            <a_text><property prop_type="private"> Economic freedom is recognised and
                                guaranteed</property>. The State shall take care of developing a
                                <economic e_type="free">free and open economy</economic>, and
                                <property prop_type="private">free enterprise and
                                    competition</property>. <property prop_type="private">Abolishing the
                                        universal right to private property shall be prohibited</property>.
                            </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header> Article 7. Basis of territorial arrangement </a_header>
                            <a_text> The following shall fall within <consent>the exclusive competence
                                of the supreme state authorities of Georgia</consent>: a.
                                <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">legislation on human
                                    rights</ind_rights>, <ind_rights ind_type="citizenship">Georgian
                                        citizenship</ind_rights>, <ind_rights ind_type="citizenship"
                                            >migration>, entry into and exit from the country</ind_rights>, and
                                the <international>temporary or permanent stay of aliens and stateless
                                    persons</international> in Georgia; b.<property prop_type="other">
                                        criminal, penitentiary, civil, intellectual property,
                                        administrative, labour and procedural legislation; legislation
                                        pertaining to land, minerals, and other natural resources;
                                        pharmaceutical legislation; legislation on obtaining the status of
                                        educational institution, and on accreditation, and academic degrees;
                                        and legislation on the National Academy of Sciences</property>; c.
                                <international>foreign policy and international relations; foreign
                                    trade, customs and tariff regimes</international>; d. state defence,
                                military industry and arms trade; <peace>issues relating to war and
                                    truce</peace>; determining and introducing the legal regime of a
                                state of emergency and martial law; the armed forces; courts and
                                prosecution; state security; criminal police and
                                investigation;<sovereignty> the status, regime and protection of the
                                    state border; and a cordon sanitaire on the border; </sovereignty>
                                e.<currency> state finances and state loans; the printing and
                                    emission of money; and legislation on banking, credit, insurance,
                                    tax and trade of national significance</currency>; f. <property
                                        prop_type="public">railways and motor roads of national
                                        significance; the integrated energy system and regime;
                                        communications</property>; <property prop_type="public">the status
                                            and protection of territorial waters, airspace, the continental
                                            shelf and the exclusive economic zone</property>; <property
                                                prop_type="public">aviation; the merchant fleet; ensigns; harbours
                                                of national significance; fishing in oceans and high seas;
                                                meteorology; environmental monitoring systems; standards and models;
                                                geodesy and cartography; determining the precise time; and state
                                                statistics</property>. g. The <levels l_type="federalist">powers of
                                                    the Autonomous Republic of Abkhazia and the Autonomous Republic of
                                                    Ajara, and procedures for exercising such powers shall be determined
                                                    by the constitutional laws</levels> of Georgia that are an integral
                                part of the Constitution of Georgia. h. The <separation>state
                                    territorial arrangement of Georgia shall be revised by a
                                    constitutional law of Georgia on the basis of the principle of the
                                    separation of powers</separation> after the complete restoration of
                                the jurisdiction of Georgia over the entire territory of the country. i.
                                <levels l_type="neutral">The citizens of Georgia shall regulate
                                    affairs of local importance through local self-government in
                                    accordance with the legislation of Georgia</levels>. <levels
                                        l_type="federalist">The separation of the powers of state authority
                                        and self-governing units is based on the principle of
                                        subsidiarity</levels>. <levels l_type="federalist">The State ensures
                                            that the financial resources of self-governing units correspond with
                                            their powers as determined by the organic law</levels>. j.<levels
                                                l_type="unitary"> An exclusive economic zone shall be established in
                                                Anaklia on the basis of the organic law, where a special legal
                                                regime shall apply. Other exclusive economic zones with special
                                                legal regimes may also be established on the basis of the organic
                                                law.</levels></a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header> Article 8. Relationship between the State and the Apostolic
                                Autocephalous Orthodox Church of Georgia </a_header>
                            <a_text>Along with <ind_rights ind_type="racial-equality">freedom of belief
                                and religion</ind_rights>, the State shall recognise the outstanding
                                role of the <nationalism>Apostolic Autocephalous Orthodox Church of
                                    Georgia in the history of Georgia</nationalism>, and <religion
                                        r_type="secular">its independence from the State</religion>. The
                                <religion r_type="state-religion">relationship between the state of
                                    Georgia and the Apostolic Autocephalous Orthodox Church of Georgia
                                    shall be determined by a constitutional agreement</religion>, which
                                shall be <international>in full compliance with the universally
                                    recognised principles and norms of international law in the area of
                                    human rights and freedoms</international>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        
                    </s_text>
                </section>
            </chapter>
        </body>
    </constitution>
    <constitution country="Kyrgyzstan">
        <meta>
            
            <source>
                <title/>
                <container/>
                <url>https://constitutionnet.org/sites/default/files/Kyrgyzstan%20Constitution.pdf</url>
            </source>
        </meta>
        <body><preamble>We, the people of Kyrgyzstan, striving to secure the national revival of the
            Kyrgyz, the <sovereignty>protection and development of interests of all nationalities
                who together with the Kyrgyz form the people of Kyrgyzstan</sovereignty>; guided by
            the <nationalism>ancestors’ precepts to live</nationalism> in <peace>unity, peace and
                concord</peace>; confirming our adherence to <ind_rights ind_type="legal">human
                    rights</ind_rights> and <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">freedoms</ind_rights> and the
            idea of national statehood; full of determination to develop the economy, political and
            legal institutions in order to <peace>secure a worthy living standard for all</peace>;
            proclaiming our adherence to common human moral principles and moral values of
            <nationalism>national traditions</nationalism>; wishing to establish ourselves among
            the peoples of the world as a <gov>free and democratic civil society</gov>, through our
            <gov>authorized representatives</gov> adopt this Constitution. </preamble>
            <chapter>
                <chap_title>First Chapter THE KYRGYZ REPUBLIC </chap_title>
                <section>
                    <s_header>First Section GENERAL PRINCIPLES</s_header>
                    <s_text>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 1</a_header>
                            <a_text>1. The Kyrgyz Republic (Kyrgyzstan) is a
                                <sovereignty>sovereign</sovereignty>, <levels l_type="unitary"
                                    >unitary</levels>, <gov>democratic republic created on the basis of
                                        a law-governed</gov>
                                <religion r_type="secular">secular state</religion>. 2.
                                <sovereignty>Sovereignty of the Kyrgyz Republic is not limited and
                                    extends throughout its entire territory</sovereignty>. 3.
                                <consent>The people of the Kyrgyz Republic are the bearers of
                                    sovereignty and are the only source of the state power in the Kyrgyz
                                    Republic</consent>. 4. The people of the Kyrgyz Republic
                                <gov>exercise their power directly and through the system of state
                                    organs and organs of local self-government</gov> on the basis of
                                this Constitution and the laws of the Kyrgyz Republic. <gov>Only the
                                    Jogorku Kenesh and the President of the Kyrgyz Republic have the
                                    right to represent the people</gov> of Kyrgyzstan <elections>by whom
                                        they were elected</elections>. 5. Changes and amendments to the
                                Constitution of the Kyrgyz Republic, laws of the Kyrgyz Republic and
                                other important issues of state life <elections>may be put to a
                                    referendum</elections> (nationwide vote). The procedure for holding
                                a referendum is established by a constitutional law. 6. <elections>The
                                    citizens of the Kyrgyz Republic elect the President of the Kyrgyz
                                    Republic, Deputies of the Jogorku Kenesh of the Kyrgyz Republic and
                                    their representatives to organs of local
                                    self-government</elections>. 7. <elections>Elections are free
                                    </elections>and are <ind_rights ind_type="vote">held on the basis of
                                        universal equal and direct suffrage by secret ballot</ind_rights>.
                                Citizens of the Kyrgyz Republic who have <ind_rights ind_type="vote"
                                    >attained the age of 18 have the right to vote</ind_rights>.
                            </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 2</a_header>
                            <a_text>1. The <consent>state and its organs serve the whole society and not
                                a particular group</consent>. 2. <treason>No group of people, no
                                    organization or any individual person has the right to assume power
                                    in the state. The usurpation of state power is a particularly severe
                                    crime</treason>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 3</a_header>
                            <a_text>1. The territory of the Kyrgyz Republic within its present
                                <sovereignty>boundaries is inviolable and indivisible</sovereignty>.
                                2. The territory of the Kyrgyz Republic is divided into <levels
                                    l_type="neutral">administrative territorial units established by law
                                    for the purposes of the organization of state government and local
                                    selfgovernment</levels>. 3. The cities of <symbols>Bishkek and Osh
                                        are cities of national significance</symbols>, and their status is
                                determined by law. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 4 </a_header>
                            <a_text>1. <property prop_type="private">Private</property>, <property
                                prop_type="public">state</property>, <property prop_type="other"
                                    >municipal and other forms of ownership are recognized and
                                    protected</property> in the Kyrgyz Republic. The Kyrgyz Republic
                                guarantees the diversity of property forms and their equal protection by
                                law. 2. <property prop_type="public">Land, its resources, air space,
                                    waters, forests, plant and animal life, and other natural resources
                                    are the property of the Kyrgyz Republic</property>, are used as the
                                basis of life and activity of the people of Kyrgyzstan and are under
                                special protection of the state. 3. <property prop_type="private">Land
                                    may also be in private</property>, <property prop_type="other"
                                        >municipal and other forms of ownership</property>. The limits of
                                and procedures for exercising of the landowners’ rights and the
                                guarantees of their protection are determined by law. 4. <property
                                    prop_type="private">The Kyrgyz Republic protects the right of its
                                    citizens and juridical persons to own property as well as their
                                    [citizens’] property and its own [the Republic’s] property located
                                    on the territory of other states </property>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 5 </a_header>
                            <a_text>1.<language lang_type="native"> The state language of the Kyrgyz
                                Republic is the Kyrgyz language</language>. 2. In the Kyrgyz
                                Republic, <language lang_type="russian">the Russian language is used as
                                    an official language</language>. 3. The Kyrgyz Republic
                                <nationalism>guarantees to representatives of all the nationalities
                                    that constitute the people of Kyrgyzstan</nationalism>
                                <language lang_type="native">the right of preservation of their native
                                    language</language>, creation of conditions for learning and
                                development [of the language]. 4. <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">It is
                                    not permitted to infringe on citizens’ rights and freedoms because
                                    of their ignorance of the state or official languag</ind_rights>.
                            </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 6 </a_header>
                            <a_text>1. The state symbols of the Kyrgyz Republic are the <symbols>state
                                flag, emblem and anthem</symbols>. Their description and the
                                procedure for their official use are determined by law. 2. <capital>The
                                    capital of the Kyrgyz Republic is the city of Bishkek</capital>. 3.
                                <currency>The monetary unit of the Kyrgyz Republic is a
                                    som</currency>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                    </s_text>
                </section>
                <section>
                    <s_header> Second Section THE STRUCTURE AND FUNCTIONING OF THE STATE</s_header>
                    <s_text>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 7</a_header>
                            <a_text> 1. The state power in the Kyrgyz Republic is based on the following
                                principles: • <consent>Supremacy of the power of the people</consent>,
                                represented and protected by <elections>the nationally elected head of
                                    the state— the President of the Kyrgyz Republic</elections>; •
                                <separation>Division of state power into the legislative, executive
                                    and judicial branches, their concerted functioning and
                                    interaction</separation>; • Responsibility of <levels
                                        l_type="unitary">the state organs before the nation and the
                                        implementation of their powers in the interest of the
                                        nation</levels>; • Delimitation of functions of state power and
                                local self-government. 2.Within the limits of powers established by this
                                Constitution, <levels l_type="unitary">the state power in the Kyrgyz
                                    Republic is represented and executed by</levels>: • President of the
                                Kyrgyz Republic; • Jogorku Kenesh of the Kyrgyz Republic; • Government
                                of the Kyrgyz Republic and organs of executive power subordinate to it;
                                • Constitutional Court of the Kyrgyz Republic, Supreme Court of the
                                Kyrgyz Republic, local courts and judges of the Kyrgyz
                                Republic.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header> Article 8</a_header>
                            <a_text>1. <parties p_type="multi">Political parties</parties>, <ind_rights
                                ind_type="assembly">trade unions and other public
                                associations</ind_rights> may be organized in the Kyrgyz Republic on
                                the basis of free will and common interests. <ind_rights
                                    ind_type="assembly">The state guarantees the observance of rights
                                    and lawful interests of public associations</ind_rights>. 2.
                                Political parties may participate in state affairs only in the following
                                forms: • Nomination of their candidates for the election to the Jogorku
                                Kenesh of the Kyrgyz Republic, state posts and organs of local
                                self-government; • Formation of factions in representative organs. 3.
                                <religion r_type="secular">Religion and all cults are separate from
                                    the state</religion>. 4. In the Kyrgyz Republic the following is not
                                permitted: •<parties p_type="multi"> Merging of state and party
                                    institutions</parties>, as well as the subordination of state
                                activity to party programs and decisions; • Formation and activity of
                                party organizations in state establishments and organizations. State
                                officials have the right to carry out their party activities outside
                                their work activity; • Membership in parties and activity in support of
                                any political party by the military personnel, employees of the organs
                                of internal affairs, national security, justice, Procuratura and courts;
                                • <religion r_type="secular">Organization of political parties on
                                    religious and ethnic grounds. Religious organizations must not
                                    pursue political aims and tasks</religion>; • Interference by
                                members of religious organizations and cults with the activity of state
                                organs; • Activity of foreign political parties, public associations,
                                religious and other organizations detrimental to the constitutional
                                system, state and national security.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header> Article 9</a_header>
                            <a_text> 1. The Kyrgyz Republic <international>does not have goals of
                                expansion, aggression and territorial claims to be resolved by means
                                of military force</international>. It rejects the militarization of
                                national life, subordination of the government or its activity for the
                                purposes of war. The Armed Forces of Kyrgyzstan <sovereignty>are
                                    organized in accordance with the principles of self-defense and
                                    defensive sufficiency</sovereignty>. 2. <sovereignty>The right to
                                        conduct war is not recognized except in cases of aggression against
                                        Kyrgyzstan and other states bound by obligations of collective
                                        defense</sovereignty>. Permission for each case of a unit of the
                                Armed Forces crossing over the borders of the territory of the Kyrgyz
                                Republic is a <gov>matter of decision of the Jogorku Kenesh of the
                                    Kyrgyz Republic</gov> adopted by a majority no less than two thirds
                                of the total number of Deputies. 3. <gov>The use of Armed Forces for the
                                    resolution of internal political issues is prohibited</gov>.
                                Military personnel may be called upon to liquidate the consequences of
                                natural disasters and in other similar cases directly provided by law.
                                4. The Kyrgyz Republic observes <international>generally recognized
                                    principles of international law</international>, <peace>seeks
                                        universal and just peace</peace>, mutually beneficial cooperation,
                                [and] <international>resolution of global and regional problems in a
                                    peaceful way</international>. <peace>Actions capable of disturbing
                                        the peaceful coexistence of the peoples, propaganda and
                                        encouragement of inter-ethnic or religious clashes are
                                        unconstitutional</peace>. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 10</a_header>
                            <a_text> 1. <gov>A state of exception in Kyrgyzstan may be imposed only in
                                cases of natural disasters, direct threat to the constitutional
                                system, mass disorder accompanied by violence and menace to human
                                life, as well as under the circumstances and for limited periods
                                indicated in a constitutional law</gov>. 2. A state of exception
                                throughout the entire territory of the Kyrgyz Republic <gov>may be
                                    imposed only by the Jogorku Kenesh of the Kyrgyz Republic, but a
                                    state of exception may be imposed by the President of the Kyrgyz
                                    Republic in limited locations</gov> under circumstances requiring
                                immediate action with a prompt, same day notification of that [act] to
                                the Jogorku Kenesh of the Kyrgyz Republic, which must confirm the act of
                                the President within no more than three days. In the absence of such a
                                confirmation within the indicated time, the state of exception is
                                cancelled. 3. <gov>Martial law in the Kyrgyz Republic may be imposed by
                                    the Jogorku Kenesh of the Kyrgyz Republic only in case of aggression
                                    against the Kyrgyz Republic</gov>. 4. <gov>A session recess of the
                                        Jogorku Kenesh of the Kyrgyz Republic is not permitted during a
                                        state of exception and martial law</gov>. In cases when the Jogorku
                                Kenesh of the Kyrgyz Republic is not in session and a state of exception
                                has been imposed by the President, the Jogorku Kenesh of the Kyrgyz
                                Republic shall convene without a notice no later than the day following
                                the introduction of the state of exception. 5. <gov>Referenda,
                                    elections, changes in the structure, functions and powers of state
                                    organs established by the Constitution of the Kyrgyz Republic are
                                    not allowed during a state of exception and martial
                                    law</gov>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 11</a_header>
                            <a_text> 1. The state budget of the Kyrgyz Republic consists of the national
                                budget and local budgets, comprising all expenditures and revenues of
                                the state. The national budget is approved by the Jogorku Kenesh of the
                                Kyrgyz Republic upon presentation by the Government of the Kyrgyz
                                Republic. 2. Revenues of the national budget are generated by the total
                                taxes established by law, other obligatory payments, income from state
                                property and other receipts. 3. <gov>A single system of taxation
                                    functions on the territory of the Kyrgyz Republic</gov>. <gov>The
                                        right to impose taxes belongs to the Jogorku Kenesh of the Kyrgyz
                                        Republic</gov>. Laws establishing new taxes and worsening the
                                standing of the tax payers are not retroactive. 4. In exceptional cases
                                [and] for the protection the economic interests of the Kyrgyz Republic,
                                the Government of the Kyrgyz Republic has the right to adopt temporary
                                measures in the sphere of taxation by changing individual tax rates and
                                other obligatory budget payments with prompt notification of the Jogorku
                                Kenesh of the Kyrgyz Republic. 5. The report on the execution of the
                                national budget is approved by the Jogorku Kenesh of the Kyrgyz
                                Republic.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 12</a_header>
                            <a_text> 1. <gov>The Constitution has the supreme juridical force and direct
                                effect in the Kyrgyz Republic</gov>. 2. Laws and other normative
                                legal acts are adopted on the basis of the Constitution. 3.
                                <international>International treaties and agreements that have,
                                    according to a procedure established by law, come into force [and]
                                    to which the Kyrgyz Republic is a party as well as generally
                                    accepted principles and norms of international law are a component
                                    of the legislation of the Kyrgyz Republic</international>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                    </s_text>
                </section>
            </chapter>
        </body>
    </constitution>
    <constitution country="Lithuania">
        <meta>
            <source>
                <title/>
                <container/>
                <url>https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Lithuania_2006</url>
            </source>
        </meta>
        <body><preamble>PREAMBLE THE LITHUANIAN NATION – having created the State of Lithuania
            <nationalism>many centuries ago</nationalism>, – having based its <gov>legal
                foundations on the Lithuanian Statutes and the Constitutions of the Republic of
                Lithuania</gov>, – having for centuries staunchly defended its <sovereignty>freedom
                    and independence</sovereignty>, – having preserved its spirit, <language
                        lang_type="native">native language</language>, writing, and
            <nationalism>customs</nationalism>, – embodying the <ind_rights ind_type="liberty"
                >innate right of the human being</ind_rights> and the <sovereignty>Nation to live
                    and create freely</sovereignty> in the <nationalism>land of their fathers and
                        forefathers</nationalism>—in the <sovereignty>independent State of
                            Lithuania</sovereignty>, – fostering <!--        "national concord" = "a national state of agreement"-->
            <consent>national concord</consent> in the land of Lithuania, – striving for an open,
            just, and <peace>harmonious</peace>
            <gov>civil society</gov> and State under the <gov>rule of law</gov>, <consent>by the
                will of the citizens</consent> of the reborn State of Lithuania, adopts and
            proclaims this</preamble>
            <chapter>
                <chap_title>CHAPTER I. THE STATE OF LITHUANIA </chap_title>
                <section>
                    <s_text>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 1 </a_header>
                            <a_text>The State of Lithuania shall be an
                                <sovereignty>independent</sovereignty>
                                <gov>democratic republic</gov>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 2 </a_header>
                            <a_text>The State of Lithuania shall be created by the Nation.
                                <sovereignty>Sovereignty shall belong to the
                                    Nation</sovereignty>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 3 </a_header>
                            <a_text><sovereignty>No one may restrict or limit the
                                sovereignty</sovereignty> of the Nation or make claims to the
                                sovereign powers belonging to the entire Nation. <sovereignty>The Nation
                                    and each citizen shall have the right to resist anyone who
                                    encroaches on the independence</sovereignty>, territorial integrity,
                                and constitutional order of the State of Lithuania by force.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 4 </a_header>
                            <a_text>The Nation shall execute its supreme sovereign power either
                                <gov>directly</gov> or through its <gov>democratically</gov>
                                <elections>elected representatives</elections>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 5 </a_header>
                            <a_text>In Lithuania, <separation>State power shall be executed by the
                                Seimas, the President of the Republic and the Government, and the
                                Judiciary</separation>. The scope of power shall be limited by the
                                Constitution.<consent>State institutions shall serve the
                                    people</consent>. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 6 </a_header>
                            <a_text>The Constitution shall be an integral and directly applicable act.
                                Everyone may defend <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">his rights by
                                    invoking the Constitution</ind_rights>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 7 </a_header>
                            <a_text>Any law or other act, which is contrary to the Constitution, shall
                                be invalid. Only laws which are published shall be valid. <ind_rights
                                    ind_type="legal">Ignorance of the law shall not exempt one from
                                    liability</ind_rights>. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 8 </a_header>
                            <a_text><treason>Seizure of State power or of its institution by force shall
                                be considered anti-constitutional actions</treason>, which are
                                unlawful and invalid. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 9 </a_header>
                            <a_text>The most significant issues concerning the life of the State and the
                                Nation shall be decided by <elections>referendum</elections>. In the
                                cases established by law, the Seimas shall announce a referendum.
                                <elections>A referendum shall also be announced if not less than
                                    300,000 citizens with the electoral right so request</elections>.
                                The procedure for the announcement and execution of a referendum shall
                                be established by law. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 10 </a_header>
                            <a_text><levels l_type="unitary">The territory of the State of Lithuania
                                shall be integral and shall not be divided into any State-like
                                formations</levels>. The State boundaries may be altered only by an
                                <gov>international treaty of the Republic of Lithuania after it has
                                    been ratified by 4/5 [four-fifths] of all the Members of the
                                    Seimas</gov>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 11 </a_header>
                            <a_text><gov>The administrative units of the territory of the State of
                                Lithuania</gov> and their boundaries shall be established by law.
                            </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <!--               ie, anyone born in lithuania has the right to be a citizen-->
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 12 </a_header>
                            <a_text><ind_rights ind_type="citizenship">Citizenship of the Republic of
                                Lithuania shall be acquired by birth</ind_rights> and other grounds
                                established by law. With the exception of individual cases provided for
                                by law, <ind_rights ind_type="citizenship">no one may be a citizen of
                                    both the Republic of Lithuania and another state</ind_rights> at the
                                same time. The procedure for the acquisition and loss of citizenship
                                shall be established by law. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 13 </a_header>
                            <a_text><ind_rights ind_type="citizenship">The State of Lithuania shall
                                protect its citizens abroad</ind_rights>. It shall be <ind_rights
                                    ind_type="citizenship">prohibited to extradite a
                                    citizen</ind_rights> of the Republic of Lithuania to another state
                                <international>unless an international treaty of the Republic of
                                    Lithuania establishes otherwise</international>. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 14 </a_header>
                            <a_text><language lang_type="native">Lithuanian shall be the State language
                            </language>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 15 </a_header>
                            <a_text><symbols>The colours of the State flag shall be yellow, green, and
                                red</symbols>. <symbols>The Coat-of-Arms of the State shall be a
                                    white Vytis on a red field</symbols>. The State Coat-of-Arms, flag
                                and their use shall be established by laws. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 16 </a_header>
                            <a_text><symbols>The anthem of the State shall be “Tautiška giesme” by
                                Vincas Kudirka</symbols>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 17 </a_header>
                            <a_text><capital>The capital of the State of Lithuania shall be the city of
                                Vilnius</capital>, <nationalism>the long-standing historical capital
                                    of Lithuania</nationalism>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                    </s_text>
                </section>
            </chapter>
        </body>
    </constitution>
    <constitution country="Turkmenistan">
        <meta>
            <source>
                <title/>
                <container/>
                <url>https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Turkmenistan_2008</url>
            </source>
            
        </meta>
        <body><preamble>PREAMBLE We, the people of Turkmenistan, based on our <sovereignty>inalienable
            right to determine our destiny;</sovereignty><nationalism> Proceeding from the
                responsibility for present and future of the Motherland;</nationalism>
            <nationalism>Expressing loyalty to the covenant of ancestors</nationalism> to
            <peace>live in unity, peace and harmony;</peace> With the aim of protecting the
            national values and interests, <sovereignty>strengthening the independence, sovereignty,
            </sovereignty>the status of permanent neutrality of Turkmenistan; <ind_rights
                ind_type="liberty">Guaranteeing the rights and freedoms of each person and
                citizen</ind_rights>, and seeking to <peace>ensure civil peace and national accord
                    in the society,</peace> to substantiate the <gov>foundations of democracy and
                        democratic, legal,</gov>
            <religion r_type="secular">secular state</religion>, we adopt the present
            Constitution - the Basic Law of Turkmenistan. </preamble><chapter>
                <chap_title>SECTION I. FUNDAMENTALS OF THE CONSTITUTIONAL SYSTEM OF
                    TURKMENISTAN</chap_title>
                <section>
                    <s_text>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 1 </a_header>
                            <a_text><gov>Turkmenistan is a democratic, legal</gov> and <religion
                                r_type="secular">secular state</religion> in which the government
                                takes <gov>the form of presidential republic</gov>. Turkmenistan
                                exercises the <sovereignty>complete power and complete authority on its
                                    territory, and independently conducts the internal and foreign
                                    policy</sovereignty>. The state sovereignty and territory of
                                Turkmenistan are homogeneous and indivisible. The State
                                <sovereignty>protects the independence, territorial integrity of
                                    Turkmenistan</sovereignty>, and constitutional system, and provides
                                law and order. Turkmenistan, by law, <international>has the status of
                                    permanent neutrality</international>. <international>The United
                                        Nations General Assembly resolution "Permanent Neutrality of
                                        Turkmenistan"</international> dated 12 December 1995: "1. Recognizes
                                and supports the declared status of permanent neutrality of
                                Turkmenistan; 2. Calls upon the member states of the United Nations to
                                respect and support this status of Turkmenistan and also <sovereignty>to
                                    respect its independence, sovereignty and territorial
                                    integrity</sovereignty>." The permanent neutrality of Turkmenistan,
                                recognized by the world community, <international>is the basis of its
                                    domestic and foreign policy</international>. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 2 </a_header>
                            <a_text>The people are the <consent>bearer of and the sole source of the
                                state power in Turkmenistan</consent>. The people of Turkmenistan
                                <elections>exercise their power directly or through representative
                                    bodies</elections>. <treason>No part (group) of the people,
                                        organization or individuals, have the right to abrogate the state
                                        power</treason>. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 3 </a_header>
                            <a_text>In Turkmenistan, the people are the highest value of the society and
                                the state. <gov>The state is responsible for every citizen</gov> and
                                creates conditions for <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">free development
                                    of the individual, protects the life, honour, dignity and freedom,
                                    personal integrity, natural and inalienable rights of the
                                    citizen</ind_rights>. Every citizen is responsible before the State
                                for the responsibilities entrusted to him by the Constitution and laws.
                            </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 4 </a_header>
                            <a_text>State power is based on the principle of <separation>separation of
                                powers between the legislative, executive and judicial branches,
                                which operate independently, balancing each other</separation>.
                            </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 5 </a_header>
                            <a_text>The state and all of its organs and officials are linked by law and
                                constitutional order. The Constitution of Turkmenistan is the Basic Law
                                of the State. Rules and regulations laid down in it are unswervingly
                                applicable. The laws and other legal acts that contradict the
                                Constitution are null and void. The normative-legal acts of the
                                government and administration, and the local self-government, are
                                published for general information or made available through other means,
                                except when they contain state or other secrets protected by law. The
                                normative-legal Acts affecting the rights and freedom of the individual
                                and citizen, if not brought to the general information of the public,
                                are invalid from the time of their adoption. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 6 </a_header>
                            <a_text>Turkmenistan, being a full subject of the global community, has the
                                <international>foreign policy of permanent neutrality,
                                    non-interference in the internal affairs of other countries,
                                    refrains from the use of force and participation in military blocs
                                    and alliances, promotes peaceful, friendly and mutually beneficial
                                    relations with countries in the region and states of the whole
                                    world</international>. Turkmenistan recognizes the priority of the
                                <international>universally accepted norms of international
                                    law</international>. <international>If an international treaty
                                        (contract) of Turkmenistan establishes rules other than those
                                        stipulated by the laws of Turkmenistan, the rules of international
                                        treaty will apply</international>. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 7 </a_header>
                            <a_text><sovereignty>Turkmenistan has its own citizenship.</sovereignty> The
                                citizenship is acquired, retained and lost in accordance with the law. <!--                            I know this whole paragraph could be tagged together, but i opted to split it up    -->
                                <!--                            I think each seperate tag is a seperate idea on it's own-->
                                <ind_rights ind_type="citizenship">Citizenship of another state is not
                                    recognized for the citizens of Turkmenistan</ind_rights>.
                                <ind_rights ind_type="citizenship">No one can be deprived of
                                    citizenship or the right to change citizenship</ind_rights>. A
                                citizen of Turkmenistan <ind_rights ind_type="citizenship">cannot be
                                    extradited to another state or expelled from the limits of
                                    Turkmenistan, or restricted in the right to return to the
                                    homeland</ind_rights>. <ind_rights ind_type="citizenship">The
                                        citizens of Turkmenistan are guaranteed the protection and patronage
                                        of the state in the territory of Turkmenistan and beyond its
                                        borders</ind_rights>. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 8 </a_header>
                            <a_text>Foreign nationals and stateless persons enjoy the rights and
                                freedoms, and bear the responsibilities, of citizens of Turkmenistan in
                                accordance with law <international>and international treaties of
                                    Turkmenistan</international>. Turkmenistan, <international>in
                                        accordance with universally recognized norms of international right
                                        and in the order established by the law, gives refuge to foreign
                                        citizens and stateless persons</international>. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 9 </a_header>
                            <a_text><property prop_type="private">The property is inviolable</property>.
                                <property prop_type="private">Turkmenistan approves the right to
                                    private ownership of the means of production, land and other
                                    material and intellectual values</property>. <property
                                        prop_type="public">They can also belong to the associations of
                                        citizens and the state</property>. The law establishes <property
                                            prop_type="public">objects that are exclusive property of the
                                            state</property>. <property prop_type="private">The state guarantees
                                                equal protection and creation of equal conditions for development of
                                                all forms of ownership</property>. <property prop_type="private"
                                                    >Confiscation of property is prohibited</property>, except for the
                                property acquired by means prohibited by law. Forced confiscation of
                                property is permissible only in cases stipulated by law. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 10 </a_header>
                            <a_text>The economy of Turkmenistan is based on the principles of <economic
                                e_type="free">market relations</economic>. The state encourages and
                                supports entrepreneurship, promotes development of small and medium
                                enterprises. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 11 </a_header>
                            <a_text>The state is responsible for <nationalism>safeguarding the national
                                historical and cultural heritage</nationalism>, natural environment,
                                ensuring <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">equality between
                                    social</ind_rights> and <ind_rights ind_type="racial-equality"
                                        >ethnic communities</ind_rights>. The state encourages scientific
                                and artistic creativity and distribution of its positive results,
                                <international>promotes development of international
                                    relations</international> in the fields of science, culture,
                                education and training, sports and tourism. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 12 </a_header>
                            <a_text>The state guarantees <religion r_type="secular">freedom of religion
                                and worship</religion>, and equality before the law. <religion
                                    r_type="secular">Religious organizations are separate from the
                                    state</religion>, cannot interfere in the state affairs and carry
                                out state functions. <religion r_type="secular">The public education
                                    system is separate from religious organizations and is
                                    secular</religion>. Each person independently determines his
                                attitude toward religion, has the right to, individually or jointly with
                                others, profess any religion or none, to express and disseminate beliefs
                                related to attitude toward religion, to participate in religious
                                observances, rituals, and ceremonies. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 13 </a_header>
                            <a_text>In order to <sovereignty>protect the state sovereignty and security,
                                Turkmenistan has its own armed forces</sovereignty>. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 14 </a_header>
                            <a_text><language lang_type="native">Turkmen is the state [official]
                                language of Turkmenistan</language>. <language lang_type="native"
                                    >The use of their native language is guaranteed to all citizens of
                                    Turkmenistan</language>. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 15 </a_header>
                            <a_text><symbols>The State Flag, the State Emblem, and the National Anthem
                                are the Symbols of Turkmenistan</symbols>. The flag, national emblem
                                and national anthem are established and protected by law. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 16 </a_header>
                            <a_text><levels l_type="neutral">The administrative-territorial structure of
                                Turkmenistan consists of</levels>: Velayats (provinces), cities with
                                right of Velayat, Etraps (districts), cities with right of district,
                                cities (towns) in district, settlements, Gengeshlyk. The territory of
                                one or more villages forms a Gengeshlyk. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 17 </a_header>
                            <a_text><capital>Ashgabat is the capital of Turkmenistan</capital>.
                            </a_text>
                        </article>
                    </s_text>
                </section>
            </chapter></body>
    </constitution>
    <constitution country="Tajikistan">
        
        <meta>
            <source>
                <title> Tajikistan 1994 (rev. 2016)</title>
                <container>Constitute Project</container>
                <url>https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Tajikistan_2016</url>
            </source>
        </meta>
        <body>
            <preamble>PREAMBLE WE, THE PEOPLE OF TAJIKISTAN, As <international>an inseparable part of
                the world community</international>, Realizing our debt and our responsibility to
                the past, present and future generations, Understanding the<sovereignty> necessity of
                    ensuring the sovereignty</sovereignty> and development of our State, Recognizing as
                unshakable the freedom and rights of man, Respecting the <ind_rights
                    ind_type="racial-equality">equality of rights and friendship of all nations and
                    nationalities</ind_rights>, Seeking to build a just society, ADOPT AND PROCLAIM THIS
                CONSTITUTION</preamble>
            <chapter>
                <chap_title>CHAPTER 1. FOUNDATIONS OF THE CONSTITUTIONAL SYSTEM</chap_title>
                
                <section>
                    <s_text>
                        
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 1 </a_header>
                            <a_text>The Republic of Tajikistan is a
                                <sovereignty>sovereign</sovereignty>, <gov>democratic</gov>,
                                law-governed, <separation>secular</separation>, and
                                <sovereignty>unitary</sovereignty> State. The form of the governance
                                of the Republic of Tajikistan is <gov>Presidential</gov>. Tajikistan is
                                a social State the policy of which is aimed at providing conditions that
                                <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">ensure dignified life and free human
                                    development</ind_rights>. "Republic of Tajikistan" and "Tajikistan"
                                are equivalent terms.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 2 </a_header>
                            <a_text> The <language lang_type="native">State language of Tajikistan is the Tajik
                                language</language>. <language lang_type="russian">Russian is the language of
                                    communication between the nationalities</language>. All <ind_rights
                                        ind_type="racial-equality">nations and nationalities living on the
                                        territory of the Republic have the right to freely use their native
                                        language</ind_rights>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 3 </a_header>
                            <a_text>The State symbols of the Republic of Tajikistan are the
                                <symbols>flag, the emblem, and the national anthem</symbols>.
                            </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 4 </a_header>
                            <a_text>The capital of Tajikistan is the city of
                                <capital>Dushanbe</capital>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 5</a_header>
                            <a_text>Human, its <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">rights and freedoms are the
                                highest value</ind_rights>. The <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">life,
                                    honor, dignity and other natural rights of man are
                                    inviolable</ind_rights>. The <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">rights and
                                        freedoms of man and citizen are recognized, observed, and protected
                                        by the State</ind_rights>. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 6 </a_header>
                            <a_text>In Tajikistan, the <sovereignty>people are the bearer of
                                sovereignty</sovereignty>
                                and the <consent>sole source of the State power, which they
                                    exercise directly as well as through their
                                    representatives</consent>. The ultimate <elections>direct expression
                                        of the power of the people is a national referendum
                                        and elections</elections>. The <ind_rights
                                            ind_type="racial-equality">citizens of Tajikistan, regardless of
                                            their nationalities, constitute the people of
                                            Tajikistan</ind_rights>.<treason> No single social organization,
                                                political party, group of people or individual has the right to
                                                usurp State power. The usurpation of power or infringement on its
                                                authorities is prohibited</treason>. The <gov>right to represent the
                                                    entire people of Tajikistan belongs only to the President and the
                                                    Majlisi Milli and the Majlisi Namoyandagon of the Majlisi Oli</gov>
                                of the Republic of Tajikistan at their joint session. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 7 </a_header>
                            <a_text> The territory of Tajikistan is <sovereignty>indivisible and
                                inviolable</sovereignty>. Tajikistan consists of the
                                Gorno-Badakhshan Autonomous Oblast, oblasts (areas), cities, rayons
                                (regions), settlements, and villages. The State secures the
                                <sovereignty> sovereignty, independence and territorial
                                    integrity</sovereignty> of the Republic. Propaganda and actions
                                aimed to divide the unity of the State are prohibited. <levels l_type="federalist">The procedure for
                                    creating and changing administrative-territorial units is regulated by a
                                    constitutional law</levels>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 8 </a_header>
                            <a_text>In Tajikistan, public life shall be developed on the basis of
                                <parties p_type="multi">political and ideological
                                    pluralism</parties>. No single ideology of a party, social
                                association, religious organization, movement, or group may be
                                recognized as the State [ideology]. <ind_rights ind_type="assembly"
                                    >Social associations</ind_rights> and <parties p_type="multi"
                                        >political parties</parties> are created and function within the
                                framework of the Constitution and laws. <religion r_type="secular">Religious unions are
                                    separate from the State and may not interfere with State
                                    affairs.</religion> Creation and functioning of social
                                associations and political parties<ind_rights ind_type="racial-equality"
                                    > propagating racism, nationalism, social and religious
                                    enmity</ind_rights>, or<treason> encouraging forcible overthrow of the
                                        constitutional system and organization of armed groups are prohibited</treason>.
                                The <international>activity of political parties of other countries,
                                    establishing national and religious parties, including funding of
                                    political parties by foreign countries and organizations, foreign
                                    legal entities and citizens shall be
                                    prohibited</international>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 9 </a_header>
                            <a_text>The State power is based on the principle of its
                                <separation>division into legislative, executive, and
                                    judicial</separation>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 10 </a_header>
                            <a_text>The Constitution of Tajikistan has the supreme juridical force [and]
                                its norms have direct effect. <consent>Laws and other legal acts
                                    contradicting the Constitution have no juridical force</consent>.
                                The State and all its organs, officials, citizens and their associations
                                are obligated to observe and implement the Constitution and laws of the
                                Republic. <international>International legal acts recognized by
                                    Tajikistan are a constituent part</international> of the legal
                                system of the Republic. In case of <international>disparity between the laws
                                    of the Republic and the recognized international legal acts, the
                                    norms of the international acts apply</international>. <international>Laws
                                        and international legal acts recognized by Tajikistan enter force
                                        after their official publication</international>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 11</a_header>
                            <a_text>Tajikistan, <peace>conducting peaceful policy, respects the
                                sovereignty and independence of other States</peace> [and]
                                determines its<international> foreign policy on the basis of
                                    international norms</international>. <peace>War propaganda is
                                        prohibited</peace>. Tajikistan, guided by the supreme interests of
                                the people, <international>may join commonwealths and other
                                    international organizations as well as withdraw from them [and]
                                    establish relations with foreign countries</international>. The
                                State <international>cooperates with compatriots [living]
                                    abroad</international>. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 12</a_header>
                            <a_text> Foundations of the economy of Tajikistan are composed of various
                                forms of property. <property prop_type="private">The State guarantees the freedom of economic and
                                    entrepreneurial activity, equality of rights, and legal protection of
                                    all forms of property including private
                                    property</property>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 13 </a_header>
                            <a_text><property prop_type="public">The land, its resources, water,
                                airspace, fauna and flora, and other natural resources are
                                exclusively the property of the State</property>, and the State
                                guarantees their effective use in the interests of the people.</a_text>
                        </article>
                    </s_text>
                </section>
            </chapter>
        </body>
    </constitution>
    <constitution country="Kazakhstan">
        <meta>
            <source>
                <title>Kazakhstan Constitution</title>
                <container/>
                <url>https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Kazakhstan_2017</url>
            </source>
        </meta>
        
        <body>
            <preamble>PREAMBLE<consent> We, the people of Kazakhstan,</consent><nationalism>united by common historic fate, creating
                state on the indigenous Kazakh land</nationalism>, <peace>considering ourselves peace-loving</peace> and civil
                society, dedicated to the ideals of freedom, equality and concord, wishing to take
                worthy place in the world community, realizing <nationalism>our high responsibility before the
                    present and future generations</nationalism>, proceeding from <sovereignty>our sovereign right</sovereignty>, accept this
                Constitution.</preamble>
            <!-- Every preamble I've covered doesn't dedicate itself to rights, but rather often nonspecific (and noncommittal) "ideals" or "values." This is probably something to add. Will have to bring this up. -->
            <chapter>
                <chap_title>SECTION I. GENERAL PROVISIONS</chap_title>
                <section>
                    <s_text>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 1</a_header>
                            <!--Maybe a relgious tag so that religion in some constitutions can be compared against secularism in others-->
                            <a_text>The Republic of Kazakhstan proclaims itself <gov>democratic</gov>,
                                <religion r_type="secular">secular</religion>, legal and social
                                state whose highest values are an <ind_rights ind_type="liberty"
                                    >individual, his life, rights and freedoms.</ind_rights> The
                                fundamental principles of the activity of the Republic are <peace>public
                                    concord and political stability</peace>; economic development for the benefit of
                                all the nation; <nationalism>Kazakhstan patriotism</nationalism> and <gov>resolution of the
                                    most important issues of the affairs of state by democratic methods</gov>
                                <elections>including voting at an all-nation referendum or in the
                                    Parliament.</elections></a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 2</a_header>
                            <a_text>
                                The Republic of Kazakhstan is <levels l_type="unitary">unitary state</levels> with <gov>presidential form
                                    of government</gov>. <sovereignty>The sovereignty of the Republic extends to its
                                        entire territory. The state ensures the integrity, inviolability and
                                        inalienability of its territory.</sovereignty> The administrative-territorial
                                division of the Republic, the status of its capital shall determine
                                by law. <capital>Capital of Kazakhstan is the city of Astana</capital>. A
                                special legal regime in the financial sphere may be established within <!-- I'll find out what the hell this means-->
                                the city of Astana in accordance with the constitutional law.
                                <sovereignty>The names “Republic of Kazakhstan” and “Kazakhstan” <!-- Also ok not using sovereignty to tag names as I once suggested now that I see it again. Lmk.-->
                                    have the same meaning</sovereignty>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 3</a_header>
                            <a_text><consent>The people shall be the only source of state
                                power.</consent>
                                <elections>The people shall exercise power directly through an
                                    all-nation referendum and free elections</elections> as well as <consent>delegate the
                                        execution of their power to state institutions</consent>. <treason>Nobody
                                            shall have the right to appropriate power in the Republic of Kazakhstan.
                                            Appropriation of power shall be persecuted by law</treason>. <consent>The right to
                                                act on behalf of the people and the state</consent><gov> shall belong to the
                                                    President as well as to Parliament of the Republic</gov> within the limits
                                of the constitutional powers.
                                The government and other state bodies shall act on behalf of
                                the state only within the limits of their delegated authorities. The
                                state power in the Republic of Kazakhstan is unified and executed on
                                the basis of the Constitution and laws in accordance with the
                                principle of <separation>its division into the legislative, executive and
                                    judicial branches and system of checks and balances that governs
                                    their interaction</separation>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 4</a_header>
                            <a_text>The provisions of the Constitution, the laws corresponding to it,
                                other regulatory legal acts,<international> international treaty and other commitments</international>
                                of the Republic as well as regulatory resolutions of Constitutional
                                Council and the Supreme Court of the Republic shall be the functioning
                                law in the Republic of Kazakhstan. The Constitution shall have the
                                highest juridical force and direct effect on the entire territory of the
                                Republic.<international> International treaties ratified by the Republic shall have
                                    priority over its laws. The procedure and conditions of the application
                                    in the territory of the Republic of Kazakhstan of international treaties
                                    to which Kazakhstan is a party are determined by the legislation of the <!-- Multiple ideas, multiple tags?-->
                                    Republic. All laws, international treaties of which the Republic is
                                    party shall be published</international>. Official publication of regulatory legal acts
                                dealing with the <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">rights, freedoms and responsibilities of citizens shall
                                    be necessary condition for their application</ind_rights>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 5</a_header>
                            <a_text> The Republic of Kazakhstan shall recognize ideological and
                                political<!-- Interesting that they don't mention freedom of politcs and idealogy, just "diversity"-->
                                diversity. <parties p_type="0">The formation of political party
                                    organizations in state bodies shall not be permitted. Public
                                    associations shall be equal before the law.</parties> Illegal
                                interference of the state in the affairs of public associations and of
                                public associations in the affairs of the state, imposing the functions
                                of state institutions on public associations shall not be permitted.
                                <parties p_type="0">Formation and functioning of public associations
                                    pursuing the goals or actions directed toward violent change of the
                                    constitutional system, violation of the integrity of the Republic,
                                    undermining the security of the state, inciting social, racial,
                                    national, religious, class and tribal enmity, as well as formation
                                    of unauthorized paramilitary units shall be prohibited.</parties>
                                <international>Activities of political parties and trade unions of other states,
                                    religious parties as well as financing political parties and trade
                                    unions by foreign legal entities and citizens, foreign states and
                                    international organizations shall not be permitted in the
                                    Republic.</international> <international>Activities of <!--Treason?--> foreign</international><religion r_type="state-religion"> religious associations on the territory of
                                        the Republic as well as appointment of heads of religious
                                        associations in the Republic by foreign
                                        religious<!-- Feels like should be tagged concerning religion, but also the-->
                                        centers shall be carried out in coordination with the respective
                                        state institutions of the Republic.</religion></a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>>Article 6</a_header>
                            <a_text><property prop_type="public">The Republic of Kazakhstan shall
                                recognize and by the same token protect state</property><property prop_type="private"> and private property</property>.
                                <property prop_type="other">Property shall impose obligations, and its use must simultaneously
                                    benefit the society. Subjects and objects of ownership, the scope
                                    and limits of the rights of proprietors, and guarantees of their
                                    protection shall be determined by law.</property><property prop_type="public"> The land and underground
                                        resources, waters, flora and fauna, other natural resources shall be
                                        owned by the state.</property> <property prop_type="private">The land may also be privately owned on terms,
                                            conditions and within the limits established by
                                            legislation.</property></a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 7</a_header>
                            <a_text><language lang_type="native">The state language of the Republic of Kazakhstan shall be
                                the Kazak language </language>. <language lang_type="russian">In state institutions and local
                                    self-administrative bodies the Russian language shall be officially
                                    used on equal grounds along with the Kazak language</language>. <language lang_type="native">The state shall
                                        promote conditions for the study and development of the languages of
                                        the people of Kazakhstan</language>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 8</a_header>
                            <a_text><international>The Republic of Kazakhstan shall respect principles
                                and norms of international law, pursue the policy of cooperation and
                                good-neighborly relations between states, their equality and
                                non-interference in each other’s domestic affairs, peaceful
                                settlement of international disputes and renounce the first use of
                                the military force</international>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 9</a_header>
                            <a_text><symbols>The Republic of Kazakhstan shall have its state symbols -
                                the flag, emblem and anthem</symbols>. Their description and order of official
                                use shall be established by the constitutional law.
                            </a_text>
                        </article>
                    </s_text>
                </section>
            </chapter>
        </body>
    </constitution>
    <constitution country="Latvia">
        <meta>
            <source>
                <title>Latvia Constitution</title>
                <container/>
                <url>https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Latvia_2016</url>
            </source>
        </meta>
        <body><preamble>PREAMBLE The people of Latvia, in freely elected Constitutional Assembly, have
            adopted the following State Constitution: The State of Latvia, proclaimed on 18 November
            1918, has been <nationalism>established by uniting historical Latvian lands and on the basis of the
                unwavering will of the Latvian nation</nationalism> to have <sovereignty>its own State and its inalienable right of
                    self-determination in order to guarantee the existence and development of the Latvian
                    nation</sovereignty>, <language lang_type="native">its language</language> and <nationalism>culture</nationalism> throughout the centuries, to ensure <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">freedom</ind_rights> and <peace>promote
                        welfare of the people of Latvia</peace> and each individual. The people of Latvia won their 
            State in the War of Liberation. <gov>They consolidated the system of government and adopted
                the Constitution in a freely elected Constitutional Assembly</gov>. <international>The people of Latvia did
                    not recognise the occupation regimes</international>, resisted them and <sovereignty>regained their freedom by
                        restoring national independence on 4 May 1990 on the basis of continuity of the State</sovereignty>.
            <nationalism>They honour their freedom fighters</nationalism>, <international>commemorate victims of foreign powers, condemn the
                Communist and Nazi totalitarian regimes and their crimes</international>. Latvia as <gov>democratic, socially
                    responsible and national state is based on the rule of law</gov> and on <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">respect for human
                        dignity and freedom</ind_rights>; it recognises and protects <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">fundamental human rights</ind_rights> and <ind_rights ind_type="racial-equality">respects
                            ethnic minorities</ind_rights>. The people of Latvia protect <sovereignty>their sovereignty, national
                                independence, territory, territorial integrity</sovereignty> and <gov>democratic system of government of
                                    the State of Latvia.</gov> Since ancient times, <nationalism>the identity of Latvia in the European
                                        cultural space has been shaped by Latvian and Liv traditions, Latvian folk wisdom,</nationalism> <language lang_type="native">the
                                            Latvian language</language>, universal human and <religion r_type="neutral">Christian values</religion>. <nationalism>Loyalty to Latvia</nationalism>,<language lang_type="native"> the Latvian
                                                language as the only official language</language>, <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">freedom, equality, solidarity, justice</ind_rights>, honesty,
            work ethic and family are the foundations of a cohesive society. Each individual takes
            care of oneself, one’s relatives and the common good of society by acting responsibly
            toward other people, <nationalism>future generations</nationalism>, the environment and nature. <international>While acknowledging
                its equal status in the international community, Latvia protects its national interests
                and promotes sustainable and democratic development of a united Europe and the world</international>.
            <religion r_type="neutral">God, bless Latvia!</religion></preamble>
            <chapter>
                <chap_title>CHAPTER I. GENERAL PROVISIONS</chap_title>
                <section>
                    <s_text>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 1</a_header>
                            <a_text><gov> Latvia is an independent democratic republic</gov>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 2</a_header>
                            <a_text> <sovereignty>The sovereign power of the State of Latvia</sovereignty><consent> is vested in the people
                                of Latvia</consent>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 3</a_header>
                            <a_text> The territory of the State of Latvia, <international>within the borders
                                established by international agreements,</international><sovereignty> consists of Vidzeme, Latgale,
                                    Kurzeme and Zemgale</sovereignty>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 4</a_header>
                            <a_text><language lang_type="native"> The Latvian language is the official language in the Republic of 
                                Latvia.</language><symbols> The national flag of Latvia shall be red with a band of
                                    white</symbols>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                    </s_text>
                </section>
            </chapter></body>
    </constitution>
    <constitution country="Russia">
        <meta>
            <source>
                <title>Russia Constitution</title>
                <container/>
                <url>https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Russia_2014</url>
            </source>
        </meta>
        <body><preamble>PREAMBLE We, the multinational people of the Russian Federation, united by a
            common fate on our land, <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">establishing human rights and freedoms</ind_rights>,<peace> civil peace and accord</peace>,
            <nationalism>preserving the historically established State unity</nationalism>,<sovereignty> proceeding from universally
                acknowledged principles of equality and self-determination of peoples</sovereignty>,<nationalism> revering the
                    memory of ancestors who have passed on to us their love for the Fatherland and faith in
                    good and justice</nationalism>,<sovereignty> reviving the sovereign statehood of Russia</sovereignty> and <gov>asserting the firmness
                        of its democratic basis</gov>, striving to ensure the<peace> well-being and prosperity</peace> of Russia,
            <nationalism>proceeding from the responsibility for our Fatherland before present and future
                generations</nationalism>,<international> recognizing ourselves to be a part of the world community</international>, do hereby adopt
            THE CONSTITUTION OF THE RUSSIAN FEDERATION.</preamble>
            <chapter>
                <chap_title>SECTION ONE CHAPTER 1. THE BASIS OF THE CONSTITUTIONAL SYSTEM</chap_title>
                <section>
                    <s_text>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 1</a_header>
                            <a_text><gov>The Russian Federation - Russia is a democratic federative
                                law-governed state with a republican form of government</gov>.<sovereignty> The names
                                    Russian Federation and Russia are equivalent</sovereignty>.</a_text> <!-- Same thing with names -->
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 2</a_header>
                            <a_text>Man, his rights and freedoms shall be the supreme value. The
                                recognition, observance and <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">protection of human and civil rights and
                                    freedoms shall be an obligation of the State</ind_rights>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 3</a_header>
                            <a_text><sovereignty>The bearer of sovereignty</sovereignty> and <consent>the sole source of power in the
                                Russian Federation shall be its multinational people</consent>. The people shall
                                exercise its power directly, as well as <levels l_type="neutral">through State government bodies
                                    and local self-government bodies</levels>. <elections>The supreme direct expression of the
                                        power of the people shall be referendum and free elections</elections>. <treason>Nobody may
                                            usurp power in the Russian Federation. The seizure of power or
                                            usurpation of State authority shall be prosecuted</treason> under federal
                                law.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 4</a_header>
                            <a_text><sovereignty>The sovereignty of the Russian Federation shall extend to the
                                entirety of its territory</sovereignty>.<gov> The Constitution of the Russian Federation
                                    and federal laws shall have supremacy on the entire territory of the
                                    Russian Federation</gov>.<sovereignty> The Russian Federation shall ensure the integrity
                                        and inviolability of its territory</sovereignty>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 5</a_header>
                            <a_text><gov>The Russian Federation shall consist of republics, krays, oblasts,
                                cities of federal significance, an autonomous oblast and autonomous
                                okrugs, which shall have equal rights as constituent entities of the
                                Russian Federation. A republic (state) shall have its own constitution
                                and legislation. A kray, oblast, city of federal significance,
                                autonomous oblast and autonomous okrug shall have its own charter and
                                legislation. The federal structure of the Russian Federation shall be
                                based on its State integrity, the unity of the system of State power</gov>,
                                <separation>the division of matters of authority and powers between State government
                                    bodies of the Russian Federation and State government bodies of
                                    constituent entities of the Russian Federation,</separation> <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">the equality</ind_rights> and
                                <sovereignty>self-determination of peoples in the Russian Federation</sovereignty>. All constituent
                                entities of the Russian Federation shall be equal with one another in
                                relations with federal State government bodies.</a_text>
                            <!-- Maybe also an attribute for general equality -->
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 6</a_header>
                            <a_text><ind_rights ind_type="citizenship"> Citizenship of the Russian Federation shall be acquired and
                                terminated in accordance with federal law, and shall be one and equal,
                                irrespective of the grounds on which it is acquired. Every citizen of
                                the Russian Federation</ind_rights> shall enjoy all <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">rights and freedoms</ind_rights> on its
                                territory and shall bear equal responsibilities as envisaged in the
                                Constitution of the Russian Federation. <ind_rights ind_type="citizenship">A citizen of the Russian
                                    Federation may not be deprived of his (her) citizenship or of the right
                                    to change it</ind_rights>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 7</a_header>
                            <a_text> The Russian Federation shall be a social state whose policy is
                                aimed at creating conditions ensuring a worthy life and a free
                                development of Man.<ind_rights ind_type="misc"> In the Russian Federation the labour and health of
                                    people shall be protected, a guaranteed minimum wage shall be
                                    established, State support shall be provided for the family, maternity,
                                    fatherhood and childhood, to the disabled and to elderly citizens, the
                                    system of social services shall be developed and State pensions,
                                    allowances and other social security guarantees shall be
                                    established</ind_rights>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 8</a_header>
                            <a_text> <property prop_type="private">In the Russian Federation the integrity of economic space, free
                                flow of goods, services and financial resources, support of competition,
                                and the freedom of economic activity shall be guaranteed</property>. <property prop_type="public"> In the Russian
                                    Federation private, State, municipal and other forms of property shall
                                    be recognized and shall be protected on an equal basis</property>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 9</a_header>
                            <a_text> Land and other natural resources shall be utilized and protected in
                                the Russian Federation as the basis of the life and activity of the
                                peoples living on the territories concerned. <property prop_type="private">Land and other natural
                                    resources may be subject to private</property>,<property prop_type="public"> State, municipal</property><property prop_type="other"> and other forms of
                                        ownership.</property></a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 10</a_header>
                            <a_text><separation> State power in the Russian Federation shall be exercised on the
                                basis of its division into legislative, executive and judicial
                                authority. Bodies of legislative, executive and judicial authority shall
                                be independent</separation>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 11</a_header>
                            <a_text> State power in the Russian Federation shall be exercised by the
                                President of the Russian Federation, the Federal Assembly (the Council
                                of Federation and the State Duma), the Government of the Russian
                                Federation, and the courts of the Russian Federation. State power in
                                constituent entities of the Russian Federation shall be exercised by
                                bodies of State government formed by those constituent entities. <levels l_type="unitary">The <!-- I think this is implied unitarianism-->
                                    division of authorities and powers among State government bodies of the
                                    Russian Federation and State government bodies of constituent entities
                                    of the Russian Federation shall be established</levels> by this Constitution, the
                                Federation Treaty and other treaties on the division of authorities and
                                powers.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 12</a_header>
                            <a_text> <levels l_type="neutral">Local self-government shall be recognized and guaranteed in the
                                Russian Federation</levels>. Local self-government shall be independent within
                                the limits of its competence. Bodies of local self-government shall not
                                form part of the system of State government bodies.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 13</a_header>
                            <a_text> Ideological diversity shall be recognized in the Russian
                                Federation. <parties p_type="multi">No ideology shall be proclaimed as State ideology or as
                                    obligatory. Political diversity and the multi-party system shall be
                                    recognized in the Russian Federation. Public associations shall be equal
                                    before the law</parties>. The establishment and activities of public associations
                                whose goals and activities are aimed at the forcible changing of the
                                basis of the constitutional order and at violating the integrity of the
                                Russian Federation, at undermining its security, at creating armed
                                units, and at instigating social, racial, national and religious strife
                                shall be prohibited.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 14</a_header>
                            <a_text> <religion r_type="secular">The Russian Federation shall be a secular state. No religion may be
                                established as the State religion or as obligatory. Religious
                                associations shall be separate from the State and shall be equal before
                                the law</religion>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 15</a_header>
                            <a_text> <gov>The Constitution of the Russian Federation shall have supreme legal
                                force, direct effect and shall be applicable on the entire territory of
                                the Russian Federation. Laws and other legal acts, which are adopted in
                                the Russian Federation, must not contradict the Constitution of the
                                Russian Federation. State government bodies, local self-government
                                bodies, officials, citizens and their associations shall be obliged to
                                observe the Constitution of the Russian Federation and laws. Laws must
                                be officially published. Unpublished laws shall not have force.</gov><ind_rights ind_type="liberty"> Any
                                    normative legal acts concerning human and civil rights, freedoms and
                                    obligations shall not have force unless they have been officially
                                    published for the information of the general public.</ind_rights>
                                <international>Universally recognized principles and norms of international law as well as
                                    international agreements of the Russian Federation should be an integral
                                    part of its legal system</international>. <international>If an international agreement of the Russian
                                        Federation establishes rules, which differ from those stipulated by law,
                                        then the rules of the international agreement shall be applied</international>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 16</a_header>
                            <a_text> The provisions of this Chapter of the Constitution shall constitute
                                the fundamental principles of the constitutional order of the Russian
                                Federation and may not be changed except in accordance with the
                                procedure established by this Constitution. No other provisions of this
                                Constitution may conflict with the fundamental principles of the
                                constitutional order of the Russian Federation.</a_text>
                        </article>
                    </s_text>
                </section>
            </chapter>
        </body>
    </constitution>
    <constitution country="Uzbekistan">
        <meta>
            <source>
                <title>Uzbekistan Constitution</title>
                <container/>
                <url>https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Uzbekistan_2011</url>
            </source>
        </meta>
        <body><preamble>PREAMBLE The people of Uzbekistan, solemnly declaring their
            adherence to <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">human rights</ind_rights> and
            <sovereignty>principles of state sovereignty</sovereignty>, <nationalism>being aware
                of their ultimate responsibility to the present and the future generations, relying
                on historical experience in the development of the Uzbek statehood</nationalism>,
            affirming their commitment to the ideals of <gov>democracy</gov> and social justice,
            <international>recognizing priority of the generally accepted norms of the
                international law</international>, aspiring to a worthy life for the citizens of the
            Republic, <gov>setting forth the task of creating a humane and democratic law-governed
                state</gov>,
            <peace>aiming to ensure civil peace and national accord</peace>,
            <gov>adopt in the person of their plenipotentiary representatives the present
                Constitution of the Republic of Uzbekistan</gov>.</preamble>
            <chapter>
                <chap_title>PART ONE. FUNDAMENTAL PRINCIPLES Chapter I. STATE SOVEREIGNTY</chap_title>
                <section>
                    <s_text>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 1</a_header>
                            <a_text> Uzbekistan is a <sovereignty>sovereign</sovereignty>
                                <gov>democratic republic</gov>.<sovereignty> Both names of the state
                                    “the Republic of Uzbekistan” and “Uzbekistan” shall be
                                    equivalent</sovereignty>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 2</a_header>
                            <a_text><consent> The state shall express the will of the people and serve
                                their interests. State bodies and officials shall be accountable to
                                the society and citizens</consent>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 3</a_header>
                            <a_text>
                                <gov>The Republic of Uzbekistan shall determine its national-state and
                                    administrative-territorial structure, its structure of state
                                    authority and administration</gov>, and shall pursue its home
                                <international>and foreign policies</international>.<sovereignty> The
                                    state boundary and the territory of Uzbekistan shall be inviolable
                                    and indivisible</sovereignty>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 4</a_header>
                            <a_text>
                                <language lang_type="native">The state language of the Republic of Uzbekistan shall be
                                    Uzbek.</language>
                                <ind_rights ind_type="racial-equality">The Republic of Uzbekistan shall
                                    ensure a respectful attitude toward the languages, customs and
                                    traditions of all nationalities and ethnic groups living on its
                                    territory, and the creation of the conditions for their
                                    development</ind_rights>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 5</a_header>
                            <a_text> <symbols>The Republic of Uzbekistan shall have its state symbols:
                                the flag, the emblem, and the anthem</symbols> sanctioned by the
                                law.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 6</a_header>
                            <a_text><capital> The capital of the Republic of Uzbekistan shall be the
                                city of Tashkent</capital>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                    </s_text>
                </section>
            </chapter>
        </body> 
    </constitution>
    <constitution country="Belarus">
        <meta>
            <source>
                <title>Belarus 1994 (rev. 2004)</title>
                <container>Constitute Project</container>
                <url>https://www.constituteproject.org</url>
            </source>
        </meta>
        
        <body>
            <preamble>PREAMBLE We, the People of the Republic of Belarus, (of Belarus), proceeding from the
                responsibility for the <nationalism>present and future of Belarus, recognising ourselves as a
                    full-fledged subject of the international community and confirming our adherence to values
                    common to all mankind, founding ourselves on our inalienable right to self-determination,
                    supported by the centuries-long history of development of Belarusian statehood </nationalism>,
                striving to <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">assert the rights and freedoms of every citizen of the
                    Republic of Belarus </ind_rights>, desiring to <peace>maintain civic concord, firm foundations
                        of government by the people and a state based on the rule of law</peace>, adopt hereby this
                Constitution - the Fundamental Law of the Republic of Belarus.</preamble>
            <chapter>
                
                <chap_title> SECTION 1. FUNDAMENTALS OF THE CONSTITUTIONAL SYSTEM </chap_title>
                <section>
                    <s_text>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 1 </a_header>
                            <a_text>The Republic of Belarus is a <levels l_type="unitary">unitary</levels>,
                                <gov>democratic, social state based on the rule of law</gov>. The Republic of
                                Belarus exercises supreme control and absolute <sovereignty>authority over the
                                    whole of its territory and implements an independent domestic and foreign
                                    policy</sovereignty>. The Republic of Belarus shall defend its
                                <sovereignty>independence and territorial integrity</sovereignty>, its
                                constitutional system, and <peace>safeguard lawfulness and law and
                                    order</peace>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 2</a_header>
                            <a_text> The <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">individual, his rights, freedoms and
                                guarantees to secure them are the supreme value and goal of the society and
                                the State</ind_rights>. The State shall assume responsibility before the
                                citizen to <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">create the conditions for free and
                                    dignified development of his personality</ind_rights>. The citizen shall
                                assume responsibility before the State to discharge unwaveringly the duties
                                imposed upon him by the Constitution.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 3 </a_header>
                            <!--the tagging for tgis is not
                        that good need help-->
                            <a_text>
                                <consent>The people shall be the sole source of state power</consent> and
                                the <sovereignty>bearer of sovereignty</sovereignty> in the Republic of Belarus.
                                The <gov>people shall exercise their power directly, through representative and
                                    other bodies in the forms and within the confines determined by the
                                    Constitution</gov>. <treason>Any actions aimed at changing the constitutional
                                        system and seizing state power by forcible means or by way
                                        of any other violation of the laws of the Republic of Belarus shall
                                        be punishable by law</treason>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 4</a_header>
                            <a_text>
                                <gov>Democracy</gov> in the Republic of Belarus shall be exercised on the basis of
                                <parties p_type="multi"> diversity of political institutions, ideologies and
                                    opinions</parties>. The <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">ideology of political
                                        parties, religious or other public associations, social groups may not be made
                                        mandatory for citizens</ind_rights>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 5</a_header>
                            <a_text> Political parties and other public associations acting within the framework
                                of the Constitution and laws of the Republic of Belarus shall contribute to
                                ascertaining and <gov>expressing the political will of the citizens</gov> and
                                <elections>shall participate in elections</elections>. <ind_rights ind_type="misc">Political parties and
                                    other public associations shall have the right to use state mass media
                                    under the procedure determined by the legislation</ind_rights>. <treason>The foundation and
                                        activities of political parties and other public associations, that aim to change
                                        the constitutional system by force or conduct propaganda of war, social,
                                        ethnic, religious and racial hatred, shall be prohibited</treason>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 6</a_header>
                            <a_text>State power in the Republic of Belarus shall be exercised on the principle of
                                <separation>its separation into legislative, executive, and judicial
                                    powers</separation>. State bodies within the confines of their powers, shall
                                be <separation>independent: they shall interact among themselves, check and
                                    balance one another</separation>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 7</a_header>
                            <!--unsure of this one too -->
                            <a_text>The Republic of Belarus shall be bound by the principle of supremacy of law.
                                <consent> The State and all the bodies and officials thereof shall operate within the
                                    confines of the Constitution and acts of legislation adopted in accordance
                                    therewith</consent>. <consent>Legal acts or specific provisions thereof which have been
                                        recognised under the procedure specified by law as contradicting the
                                        provisions of the Constitution shall have no legal force</consent>.<consent> Normative acts
                                            of state bodies shall be published or promulgated by other means specified by
                                            law</consent>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 8 </a_header>
                            <a_text>The Republic of Belarus shall recognize the supremacy of the generally
                                recognised principles of <international>international law and shall ensure the
                                    compliance of laws </international>therewith. <international>The Republic of
                                        Belarus in conformity with the rules of international law may on a voluntary
                                        basis enter interstate formations and withdraw from them</international>.
                                <sovereignty>Conclusion of treaties that are contrary to the Constitution
                                    shall not be permitted</sovereignty>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 9 </a_header>
                            <a_text> <sovereignty>The territory of the Republic of Belarus shall be the natural condition of
                                the existence and spatial limit of the people's
                                self-determination</sovereignty>, and the basis for its prosperity and the
                                <sovereignty>sovereignty</sovereignty> of the Republic of Belarus. The
                                territory of Belarus shall be integral and inalienable. The territory shall be
                                divided into regions (oblasts), districts, cities and other administrative and
                                territorial units. The <levels l_type="federalist">administrative and territorial division of the
                                    State is determined by the legislation</levels>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 10 </a_header>
                            <a_text> A citizen of the Republic of Belarus shall be <ind_rights
                                ind_type="citizenship"> guaranteed protection and patronage of the State both
                                in the territory of Belarus and beyond</ind_rights>. <ind_rights
                                    ind_type="citizenship">No one may be deprived of citizenship of the Republic
                                    of Belarus or the right to change his citizenship</ind_rights>. A <ind_rights
                                        ind_type="citizenship">citizen of the Republic of Belarus may not be
                                        extradited to a foreign state</ind_rights>, unless otherwise provided by
                                treaties to which the Republic of Belarus is a party.Acquisition and loss of the
                                citizenship shall be carried out in accordance with the law.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 11</a_header>
                            <a_text>
                                <international> Foreign nationals and stateless persons in the territory of
                                    Belarus shall enjoy the rights and freedoms and execute duties on equal terms
                                    with the citizens of the Republic of Belarus, unless otherwise specified by
                                    the Constitution, laws and treaties</international>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 12</a_header>
                            <a_text>The Republic of Belarus may <international>grant the right of asylum to
                                persons persecuted in other states for political or religious beliefs or their
                                ethnic affiliation</international>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 13</a_header>
                            <a_text> Property may be <property prop_type="public">state-owned </property>or
                                <property prop_type="private">private</property>. The State shall <ind_rights
                                    ind_type="misc">grant equal rights to all to conduct economic and other
                                    activities</ind_rights>, except for those prohibited by law, and guarantee
                                equal protection and equal conditions for the development of all forms of
                                ownership. The State shall<separation> promote the development of
                                    co-operation</separation>. The State shall guarantee to all equal
                                opportunities for <ind_rights ind_type="misc">free utilisation of abilities and
                                    property for entrepreneurial and other types of economic activities which are
                                    not prohibited by the law</ind_rights>. The State shall <consent>regulate
                                        economic activities in the interests of the individual and society, and shall
                                        ensure the direction and co-ordination of state and private economic activity
                                        for social purposes</consent>. The <property prop_type="public">mineral
                                            wealth, waters and forests are the exclusive property of the State</property>.
                                The <property prop_type="public">land for agricultural use is the property of the
                                    State</property>. Law may <property prop_type="public"> determine facilities
                                        that are in the ownership of the State only, or establish a special procedure
                                        for their transfer to private ownership, or grant the State an exclusive right
                                        to conduct certain types of activity</property>. The State shall guarantee the
                                <ind_rights ind_type="misc">working people the right to participate in
                                    management of enterprises, organizations and establishments to enhance their
                                    efficiency and improve social and economic living
                                    standards</ind_rights>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 14</a_header>
                            <a_text>The State shall regulate relations among <ind_rights ind_type="liberty"
                                >social, ethnic and other communities on the basis of the principles of
                                equality before the law and respect of their rights and
                                interests</ind_rights>. Relations in the<separation> social and labour sphere
                                    between the bodies of state administration, associations of employers and
                                    trade unions shall be exercised on the principles of social partnership and
                                    interaction of parties</separation>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 15</a_header>
                            <a_text>The State shall bear responsibility for preserving the <ind_rights
                                ind_type="racial-equality">historic, cultural and spiritual heritage, and for
                                free development of the cultures of all ethnic communities</ind_rights>
                                residing in the Republic of Belarus.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 16</a_header>
                            <a_text><religion r_type="neutral">Religions and faiths shall be equal before the law.
                                Relations between the State and religious organizations shall be regulated by
                                law with regard to their influence</religion> on formation of<nationalism>
                                    spiritual, cultural and state traditions of the Belarusian
                                    people</nationalism>. The activities of religious organisations, their bodies
                                and representatives, that are directed against the <sovereignty>sovereignty of the
                                    Republic of Belarus, its constitutional system and civic
                                    concord</sovereignty>, or involve <ind_rights ind_type="misc"> violation of civil
                                        rights and freedoms of its citizens </ind_rights>as well as impede the
                                execution of state, public and family duties by its citizens or are detrimental to
                                their health and morality shall be prohibited.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header> Article 17 </a_header>
                            <a_text> The <language lang_type="native">Belarusian</language> and <language
                                lang_type="russian">Russian languages</language> shall be the official
                                languages of the Republic of Belarus</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 18 </a_header>
                            <a_text> In its foreign policy the Republic of Belarus shall proceed from the
                                principles of<international> equality of states, non-use of force or the threat of
                                    force, inviolability of frontiers, peaceful settlement of disputes,
                                    non-interference in internal affairs and other generally recognised principles
                                    and norms of the international law</international>. The Republic of Belarus
                                aims at making its <international>territory a nuclear-free zone, and the state
                                    neutral</international>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 19 </a_header>
                            <a_text>The symbols of the Republic of Belarus as a sovereign state shall be its
                                <symbols>national flag, national emblem and national
                                    anthem</symbols>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 20 </a_header>
                            <a_text>The capital of the Republic of Belarus is the city of
                                <capital>Minsk</capital>. The status of the city of Minsk shall be determined by
                                the law.</a_text>
                        </article>
                    </s_text>
                </section>
            </chapter>
        </body>
    </constitution>
    <constitution country="Moldova">
        
        <meta>
            <source>
                <title>Moldova (Republic of) 1994 (rev. 2016)</title>
                <container>Constitute Project</container>
                <url>https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Moldova_2016</url>
            </source>
        </meta>
        <body>
            <preamble> PREAMBLE WE, the plenipotentiary representatives of the people of the Republic of
                Moldova, members of the Parliament, STARTING from the age-old aspirations of our people
                to live in a <sovereignty>sovereign country</sovereignty>, expressed by the
                <sovereignty>proclamation of independenc</sovereignty>e of the Republic of Moldova,
                TAKING DUE ACCOUNT to the <nationalism>continuity of the Moldavian people statehood
                    within the historical and ethnic framework of its growing as a nation</nationalism>,
                STRIVING to satisfy the <peace>interests of citizens of a different ethnic origin, which
                    together with the Moldavians, constitute the Republic of Moldova people</peace>,
                CONSIDERING the rule of <ind_rights ind_type="misc">law, civic peace, democracy, human
                    dignity, fundamental human rights and freedoms, the free development of human
                    personality, justice </ind_rights>and <parties p_type="multi">political pluralism as
                        supreme values</parties>, BEING AWARE of our responsibility and obligations towards
                the previous, present and future generations, REASSERTING our devotion to overall human
                values and <peace> desire to live in peace and harmony with all world-wide
                    peoples</peace>, in compliance with the <international>unanimously acknowledged
                        principles and norms of the international law</international>We herewith adopt the
                Constitution of the Republic of Moldova, and declare it as the SUPREME LAW OF OUR
                SOCIETY AND STATE. </preamble>
            <chapter>
                <chap_title> TITLE I. GENERAL PRINCIPLES </chap_title>
                <!--Regex: `(Article [1-9]+)..*\n` to find all article headings -->
                <section>
                    <s_text>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 1. State of the Republic of Moldova </a_header>
                            <a_text> The Republic of Moldova is a <sovereignty>sovereign, independent,
                                unitary and indivisible state</sovereignty>. The <gov>form of
                                    government of the State is the republic</gov>. The Republic of
                                Moldova is <gov>a democratic and governed by the rule of law
                                    State</gov>, in which <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">human dignity,
                                        his/her rights and freedoms, the free development of human
                                        personality</ind_rights>, justice and <parties p_type="multi"
                                            >political pluralism</parties> represent supreme values and shall be
                                guaranteed.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 2. Sovereignty and State power (
                                <!--not so sure if this may include nationalism-->
                            </a_header>
                            <a_text>
                                <sovereignty> National sovereignty resides with the people of the
                                    Republic of Moldova</sovereignty>, who shall directly and through
                                its <consent> representative bodies exercise it in the manners provided
                                    for by the Constitution</consent>. <treason>Neither an individual
                                        person or a group of people, nor a social group, a political party
                                        or any other public organization may exercise the State power on
                                        their own behalf</treason>. <treason>The usurpation of the State
                                            power shall constitute the gravest crime against the
                                            people.</treason>
                            </a_text>
                        </article>
                        
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 3. Territory</a_header>
                            <a_text>
                                <sovereignty>The territory of the Republic of Moldova is
                                    inalienable</sovereignty>. The borders of the country shall be
                                sanctioned by an organic law <international>under the observance of
                                    unanimously recognized principles and norms of the international
                                    law</international>. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 4. Human rights and freedoms </a_header>
                            <a_text> Constitutional provisions on <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">human
                                rights and freedoms</ind_rights> shall be interpreted and enforced
                                in <international>accordance with the Universal Declaration of Human
                                    Rights, other conventions and treaties to which the Republic of
                                    Moldova is a party</international>. Wherever disagreements appear
                                between the conventions and treaties on fundamental human rights to
                                which the Republic of Moldova is a party and its domestic laws,
                                <international>priority shall be given to international
                                    regulations</international>. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 5. Democracy and political pluralism </a_header>
                            <a_text> Democracy in the Republic of Moldova shall be exercised under the
                                conditions of <separation>political pluralism, which is incompatible
                                    with the dictatorship or totalitarianism</separation>. <treason>No
                                        ideology may be instituted as official ideology of the
                                        State</treason>. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 6. Separation and cooperation of powers </a_header>
                            <a_text> In the Republic of Moldova the legislature, the
                                <separation>executive and the judiciary shall be
                                    separate</separation> and cooperate in the exercise of the assigned
                                prerogatives pursuant to the provisions of the Constitution. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 7. Constitution - the Supreme Law</a_header>
                            <a_text> The Constitution of the Republic of Moldova shall be the Supreme
                                Law of the State.<consent> No law or any other legal act, which
                                    contravenes the provisions of the Constitution, shall have legal
                                    force</consent>. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 8. Observance of the international law and international
                                treaties</a_header>
                            <a_text> The Republic of Moldova <international>pledges to observe the
                                Charter of the United Nations Organization and the treaties to which
                                it is a party, to institute relationships with other states on the
                                basis of unanimously recognized principles and norms of the
                                international law.</international> The coming into force of an
                                international treaty containing provisions contrary to the Constitution
                                shall be preceded by a revision of the latter. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 9. Fundamental principles regarding property</a_header>
                            <a_text> Property shall be <property prop_type="public">public</property>
                                and <property prop_type="private">private</property>. It shall be
                                constituted of material and intellectual goods. No property may be used
                                to the <ind_rights ind_type="misc">prejudice of human
                                    rights</ind_rights>, <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">liberties and
                                        dignity</ind_rights>. The market, <economic e_type="free">free
                                            economic initiative
                                            <!--seperation of gov and economy, highlight democracy-->and fair
                                            competition shall represent the main elements of the
                                            economy.</economic>
                            </a_text>
                        </article>
                        
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 10. Unity of the people and the right to national
                                identity</a_header>
                            <a_text>
                                <sovereignty>The State foundation is laid on the unity of the Republic
                                    of Moldova people. The Republic of Moldova is the common and
                                    indivisible motherland of all its citizens. </sovereignty>
                                <ind_rights ind_type="racial-equality">The State shall recognize and
                                    guarantee the right of all citizens to the preservation, development
                                    and expression of their ethnic, cultural, linguistic and religious
                                    identity.</ind_rights>
                            </a_text>
                        </article>
                        
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 11. Republic of Moldova - a neutral State</a_header>
                            <a_text>
                                <international>The Republic of Moldova proclaims its permanent
                                    neutrality</international>.<!--unsure if the first part counts as nationalism-->
                                The Republic of Moldova <sovereignty>shall not allow the dispersal of
                                    foreign military troops on its territory</sovereignty>. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 12. Symbols of the State</a_header>
                            <a_text>
                                <symbols>The Republic of Moldova has a flag, coat of arms and anthem.
                                    The State flag of the Republic of Moldova shall be a tricolour. The
                                    colours are arranged vertically in the following order from the
                                    flagpole: blue, yellow, and red. The coat of arms is printed on the
                                    central yellow stripe of the tricolour. The State coat of arms shall
                                    consist of a shield divided horizontally into two parts: the upper
                                    part being of a red chromatics and the lower part - blue chromatics
                                    with a superimposed auroch's head showing between its horns an
                                    eight-pointed star. On its right the auroch's head is flanked by a
                                    five-petalled rose, and on its left by a slightly rotated crescent.
                                    All heraldic elements present on the shield are of golden (yellow)
                                    colour. The shield is laid on the breast of a natural eagle holding
                                    in its beak a golden cross, in its right claw a green olive-tree
                                    branch and in its left claw a golden sceptre. The State anthem of
                                    the Republic of Moldova shall be established by organic law. The
                                    flag, coat of arms and anthem shall be considered the State symbols
                                    of the Republic of Moldova and shall be protected by law as
                                    such.</symbols>
                            </a_text>
                        </article>
                        
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 13. State language, use of other languages</a_header>
                            <a_text> <language lang_type="native">The State language in the Republic of Moldova is the Moldavian
                                language, and its writing is based on the Latin alphabet</language>.
                                <language lang_type="russian">The State shall acknowledge and protect the right to
                                    the preservation, development and use of the Russian language and
                                    other languages spoken within the territory of the
                                    State.</language> The State shall <international>facilitate the
                                        study of languagesof widespread international usage</international>.
                                The manner of functioning of languages within the territory of the
                                Republic of Moldova shall be established by organic law. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 14. Capital</a_header>
                            <a_text> The capital of the Republic of Moldova is the city of
                                <capital>Chisinau</capital>. </a_text>
                        </article>
                    </s_text>
                </section>
            </chapter>
        </body>
    </constitution>
    <constitution country="Ukraine">
        <meta>
            <source>
                <title>Ukraine 1996 (rev. 2016)</title>
                <container>Constitute Project</container>
                <url>https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Ukraine_2016</url>
            </source>
        </meta>
        
        <body>
            <preamble>PREAMBLE The Verkhovna Rada of Ukraine, on behalf of the Ukrainian people -
                <ind_rights ind_type="racial-equality">citizens of Ukraine of all
                    nationalities</ind_rights>, expressing the <nationalism>sovereign will of the
                        people, based on the centuries-old history of Ukrainian state-building
                        and on the right to self-determination realised by the Ukrainian nation, all the
                        Ukrainian people</nationalism>, <ind_rights ind_type="misc">providing for the guarantee of human
                            rights and freedoms and of the worthy conditions of human life</ind_rights>,
                <peace>caring for the strengthening of civil harmony on Ukrainian soil</peace>,
                striving to develop and strengthen a <gov> democratic, social, law-based state</gov>,
                aware of our responsibility before <religion r_type="neutral">God</religion>, our own
                conscience, past, present and future generations, guided by the Act of Declaration of
                the Independence of Ukraine of 24 August 1991, approved by the national vote of 1
                December 1991, adopts this Constitution — the Fundamental Law of Ukraine.</preamble>
            <chapter>
                <chap_title>CHAPTER I. GENERAL PRINCIPLES </chap_title>
                <section>
                    <s_text>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 1</a_header>
                            
                            <a_text>Ukraine is a <sovereignty>sovereign and independent</sovereignty>
                                and, <gov>democratic, social, law-based state</gov>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 2</a_header>
                            
                            <a_text>The<sovereignty> sovereignty of Ukraine extends throughout its
                                entire territory. Ukraine is a unitary state. The territory of
                                Ukraine within its present border is indivisible and
                                inviolable</sovereignty>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 3</a_header>
                            
                            <a_text>The <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">human being, his or her life and
                                health, honour and dignity</ind_rights>, inviolability and security
                                are recognised in Ukraine as the highest social value. <ind_rights
                                    ind_type="liberty">Human rights and freedoms and their guarantees
                                    determine the essence and orientation of the activity of the
                                    State</ind_rights>,. The State is answerable to the individual for
                                its activity. To affirm and ensure <ind_rights ind_type="misc">human
                                    rights and freedoms is the main duty</ind_rights> of the
                                State.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 4</a_header>
                            
                            <a_text>There is <ind_rights ind_type="citizenship">single citizenship in
                                Ukraine. The grounds for the acquisition and termination of
                                Ukrainian citizenship are determined by law</ind_rights>. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 5</a_header>
                            
                            <a_text>Ukraine is a <gov>republic</gov>. The people are the bearers of
                                sovereignty and the only source of power in Ukraine. The people<parties
                                    p_type="multi"> exercise power directly and through bodies of state
                                    power and bodies of local self-government</parties>. The right to
                                determine and change the constitutional order in Ukraine belongs
                                exclusively to the people and <consent>shall not be usurped by the
                                    State, its bodies or officials. No one shall usurp state
                                    power</consent>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 6</a_header>
                            
                            <a_text><separation>State power in Ukraine is exercised on the principles of its
                                division into legislative, executive and judicial power.</separation>
                                <consent>Bodies of legislative, executive and judicial power exercise
                                    their authority within the limits established by this
                                    Constitution and in accordance with the laws of Ukraine</consent>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 7</a_header>
                            
                            <a_text>In Ukraine, <levels l_type="neutral">local self-government is recognised and
                                guaranteed</levels>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 8</a_header>
                            
                            <a_text>In Ukraine, the principle of the rule of law is recognised and
                                effective. <consent>The Constitution of Ukraine has the highest legal
                                    force</consent>. <consent>Laws and other normative legal acts are adopted on
                                        the basis of the Constitution of Ukraine and shall conform to it</consent>. The
                                norms of the Constitution of Ukraine are norms of direct effect. Appeals
                                to the court in defence of the <ind_rights ind_type="misc"
                                    >constitutional rights and freedoms of the individual and
                                    citizen</ind_rights> directly on the grounds of the Constitution of
                                Ukraine are guaranteed.</a_text>
                            <!--not
                            sure about the tag ind_rights-->
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 9</a_header>
                            
                            <a_text><international>>International treaties that are in force, agreed to
                                be binding by the Verkhovna Rada of Ukraine, are part of the
                                national legislation</international> of Ukraine. The conclusion
                                of<international> international treaties that contravene the
                                    Constitution of Ukraine is possible</international> only after
                                introducing relevant amendments to the Constitution of Ukraine.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 10</a_header>
                            
                            <a_text><language lang_type="native">The state language of Ukraine is the Ukrainian
                                language. The State ensures the comprehensive development
                                and functioning of the Ukrainian language in all spheres of social life
                                throughout the entire territory of Ukraine</language>. In Ukraine,
                                <language lang_type="russian">the
                                    free development, use and protection of Russian</language>,
                                and<ind_rights ind_type="racial-equality"> other languages
                                    of national minorities of Ukraine, is guaranteed</ind_rights>.
                                <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">The
                                    State promotes the learning of languages of international
                                    communication.The use of languages in Ukraine is
                                    guaranteed by the Constitution of Ukraine and is
                                    determined by law</ind_rights>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 11</a_header>
                            
                            <a_text><nationalism>The State promotes the consolidation and development of the
                                Ukrainian nation, of its historical consciousness,
                                traditions and culture</nationalism>, and also the development of
                                the <ind_rights ind_type="racial-equality">ethnic, cultural, linguistic
                                    and religious identity of all indigenous peoples and national
                                    minorities</ind_rights> of Ukraine. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 12</a_header>
                            
                            <a_text>Ukraine provides for the satisfaction of <ind_rights ind_type="citizenship"
                                >national and cultural, and linguistic needs of
                                Ukrainians residing beyond the borders of the State</ind_rights>.
                            </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 13</a_header>
                            <a_text>
                                <property prop_type="private">The land, its mineral wealth, atmosphere,
                                    water and other natural resources within the territory of Ukraine,
                                    the natural resources of its continental shelf, and the exclusive
                                    (maritime) economic zone, are objects of the right of property of
                                    the Ukrainian people</property>. Ownership rights on behalf of the
                                Ukrainian people are <levels l_type="neutral">exercised by bodies of state power and
                                    bodies of local self-government within the limits
                                    determined by this Constitution</levels>. <property prop_type="private"> Every
                                        citizen has the right to utilise the natural objects of the people's
                                        right of property </property>in accordance with the law. Property
                                entails responsibility. Property shall not be used to the detriment of
                                the person and society. The State ensures the protection of the rights
                                of <property prop_type="private">all subjects of the right of property
                                    and economic management, and the social orientation of the
                                    economy</property>. All <ind_rights ind_type="legal">subjects of the
                                        right of property are equal before the law</ind_rights>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 14</a_header>
                            
                            <a_text><property prop_type="public">Land is the fundamental national wealth that is under special state
                                protection</property>. The <property prop_type="private">right of property to land is guaranteed. This right is
                                    acquired and realised by citizens</property>,<property prop_type="public"> legal persons and the State,
                                        exclusively in accordance with the law</property>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 15</a_header>
                            
                            <a_text>Social life in Ukraine is based on the principles of <ind_rights
                                ind_type="liberty">political, economic and ideological
                                diversity</ind_rights>. No <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">ideology
                                    shall be recognised by the State as mandatory</ind_rights>.
                                Censorship is prohibited. The <ind_rights ind_type="protest">State
                                    guarantees freedom of political activity not prohibited by the
                                    Constitution</ind_rights> and the
                                <!--unsure of which attribute to use for freedom of pol activoty--> laws
                                of Ukraine.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 16</a_header>
                            
                            <a_text>To ensure ecological safety and to maintain the ecological balance
                                on the territory of Ukraine, to overcome the consequences of the
                                Chornobyl catastrophe - a catastrophe of global
                                scale, and to <nationalism>preserve the gene pool of the
                                    Ukrainian people, is the duty of the State</nationalism>. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 17</a_header>
                            
                            <a_text><sovereignty>To protect the sovereignty and territorial
                                indivisibility of Ukraine</sovereignty>, and to <nationalism>ensure its economic
                                    and informational security are the most important functions
                                    of the State and a matter of concern for all the Ukrainian
                                    people</nationalism>. <sovereignty>The defence of Ukraine and the protection of
                                        its sovereignty, territorial indivisibility and inviolability, are
                                        entrusted to the Armed Forces of Ukraine</sovereignty>. <consent>Ensuring state
                                            security and protecting the state border of Ukraine
                                            are entrusted to the respective military formations and law enforcement
                                            bodies of the State, whose organisation and operational procedure are
                                            determined by law</consent>. The <ind_rights ind_type="misc">Armed Forces of
                                                Ukraine and other military formations shall not be used by anyone to
                                                restrict the rights and freedoms of citizens</ind_rights> or<treason> with
                                                    the intent to overthrow the constitutional order, subvert the bodies of
                                                    power or obstruct their activity</treason>. The State ensures the<ind_rights
                                                        ind_type="legal"> social protection of citizens of Ukraine who serve
                                                        in the Armed Forces of Ukraine and in other military formations as
                                                        well as of members of their families</ind_rights>. <treason>The 
                                                            creation and operation of any armed formations
                                                            not envisaged by law are prohibited on the territory of
                                                            Ukraine</treason>. The <international>location of foreign military bases shall not
                                                                be permitted on the territory of Ukraine</international>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 18</a_header>
                            
                            <a_text>The <international>foreign political activity of
                                Ukraine is aimed at ensuring its national interests and
                                security</international> by <peace>maintaining peaceful and mutually
                                    beneficial co-operation with members of the international
                                    community</peace>, according to generally acknowledged
                                <international>principles and norms of international
                                    law</international>. </a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 19</a_header>
                            
                            <a_text>The legal order in Ukraine is based on the principles according to
                                which <ind_rights ind_type="legal"> no one shall be forced to do what is
                                    not envisaged by legislation</ind_rights>. <levels l_type="neutral">Bodies of state power and
                                        bodies of local self-government and their officials</levels> are obliged to act
                                only on the grounds,<consent> within the limits of authority,
                                    and in the manner envisaged by the Constitution and the laws of
                                    Ukraine</consent>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                        <article>
                            <a_header>Article 20</a_header>
                            
                            <a_text>The <symbols>state symbols of Ukraine are the State Flag of Ukraine,
                                the State Coat of Arms of Ukraine and the State Anthem of Ukraine.
                                The State Flag of Ukraine is a banner of two equally-sized
                                horizontal bands of blue and yellow. The Great State Coat of Arms of
                                Ukraine shall be established with the consideration of the Small
                                State Coat of Arms of Ukraine and the Coat of Arms of the
                                Zaporozhian Host</symbols>, by the law adopted by no less than
                                two-thirds of the constitutional composition of the Verkhovna Rada of
                                Ukraine. The main element of the Great State Coat of Arms of Ukraine is
                                the <symbols>Emblem of the Royal State of Volodymyr the Great (the Small
                                    State Coat of Arms of Ukraine). The State Anthem of Ukraine is the
                                    national anthem set to the music of M. Verbytskyi, with words that
                                    are confirmed by the law adopted by no less than two-thirds of the
                                    constitutional composition of the Verkhovna Rada of
                                    Ukraine</symbols>. The description of the state symbols of Ukraine
                                and the procedure for their use shall be established by the law adopted
                                by no less than two-thirds of the constitutional composition of the
                                Verkhovna Rada of Ukraine. The capital of Ukraine is the City of
                                <capital>Kyiv</capital>.</a_text>
                        </article>
                    </s_text>
                </section>
            </chapter>
        </body>
    </constitution>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
</constitutions>
