<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<constitutions>
    <constitution place="armenia">
        <url>https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Armenia_2015</url> PREAMBLE The Armenian
        People, accepting as a basis the fundamental principles of Armenian statehood and
        pan-national aspirations enshrined in the Declaration on the Independence of Armenia, having
        fulfilled the sacred behest of its freedom-loving ancestors to restore the sovereign state,
        dedicated to the strengthening and prosperity of the fatherland, with the aim of ensuring
        the freedom, general well-being, and civic solidarity of the generations, and affirming its
        commitment to universal values, adopts the Constitution of the Republic of Armenia. CHAPTER
        1. THE FOUNDATIONS OF CONSTITUTIONAL ORDER Article 1 The Republic of Armenia is a sovereign,
        democratic, social, and rule-of-law state. Article 2 In the Republic of Armenia, the power
        belongs to the people. The people shall exercise its power through free elections,
        referenda, as well as through state and local self-government bodies and officials
        prescribed by the Constitution. Usurpation of the power by any organization or individual
        shall be a crime. Article 3. The Human Being, His Dignity, Fundamental Rights, and Freedoms
        The human being shall be the supreme value in the Republic of Armenia. The inalienable
        dignity of the human being shall be the integral basis of his rights and freedoms. The
        respect for and protection of the fundamental rights and freedoms of the human being and the
        citizen shall be the duties of the public power. The public power shall be bound by the
        fundamental rights and freedoms of the human being and the citizen as the directly
        applicable law. Article 4. The Principle of Separation and Balance of the Powers State power
        shall be exercised in accordance with the Constitution and the laws, based on the separation
        and balance of the legislative, executive, and judicial powers. Article 5. The Hierarchy of
        Legal Norms The Constitution shall have supreme legal force. Laws shall conform to the
        constitutional laws, and sub-legislative normative legal acts shall conform to the
        constitutional laws and laws. In case there are contradictions between the norms of
        international treaties ratified by the Republic of Armenia and the norms of laws, the norms
        of the international treaties shall be applied. Article 6. The Principle of Legality State
        and local self-government bodies and officials shall have the power to perform only such
        acts for which they are empowered by the Constitution or laws. Bodies prescribed by the
        Constitution, based on the Constitution and laws and with the purpose of ensuring their
        implementation, may be authorized by the law to adopt sub-legislative normative legal acts.
        Authorizing norms shall comply with the principle of legal certainty. Laws and
        sub-legislative normative legal acts shall come into force after being published in the
        manner stipulated by law. Article 7. The Suffrage Principles Elections of the National
        Assembly and community councils, as well as referenda shall be carried out on the basis of
        universal, equal, free, and direct suffrage, by secret vote. Article 8. Ideological
        Pluralism and the Multipartisan System Ideological pluralism and the multipartisan system
        shall be guaranteed in the Republic of Armenia. Parties shall be formed and operate freely.
        Equal legal opportunities for activities of the parties shall be guaranteed by law. Parties
        shall promote the formulation and expression of the people’s political will. The structure
        and activities of parties may not contravene the democratic principles. Article 9.
        Guaranteeing Local Self-Government Local self-government is guaranteed in the Republic of
        Armenia as one of the essential foundations of democracy. Article 10. Guaranteeing Property
        All forms of property shall be recognized and equally protected in the Republic of Armenia.
        Subsoils and water resources shall be exclusive property of the State. Article 11. The
        Economic Order The basis of the economic order in the Republic of Armenia shall be the
        social market economy, which shall be based on private property, freedom of economic
        activity, free economic competition, and through the state policy aimed at general economic
        well-being and social justice. Article 12. Preservation of the Environment and Sustainable
        Development The state shall promote the preservation, improvement, and regeneration of the
        environment, and the reasonable utilization of natural resources, governed by the principle
        of sustainable development and taking into account the responsibility towards future
        generations. Everyone shall take care of the preservation of the environment. Article 13.
        Foreign Policy The foreign policy of the Republic of Armenia shall be conducted on the basis
        of international law with the aim of establishing good-neighborly and mutually-beneficial
        relations with all states. Article 14. The Armed Forces and Defense The armed forces of the
        Republic of Armenia shall ensure the defense, security, and territorial integrity of the
        Republic of Armenia, and the inviolability of its borders. The armed forces of the Republic
        of Armenia shall maintain neutrality in political matters and shall be under civilian
        control. Every citizen shall be obliged to participate in the defense of the Republic of
        Armenia in the manner stipulated by law. Article 15. Promotion of Culture, Education, and
        Science, Protection of the Armenian language and Cultural Heritage The state shall promote
        the development of culture, education, and science. The Armenian language and the cultural
        heritage shall be under the care and protection of the state. Article 16. Protection of the
        Family Family, being the natural and fundamental cell of society and the basis for the
        preservation and reproduction of the population, as well as motherhood and childhood shall
        be under special protection and aegis of the state. Article 17. The State and Religious
        Organizations The freedom of activity of religious organizations shall be guaranteed in the
        Republic of Armenia. Religious organizations shall be separate from the state. Article 18.
        The Armenian Apostolic Holy Church The Republic of Armenia shall recognize the exceptional
        mission of the Armenian Apostolic Holy Church, as the national church, in the spiritual life
        of the Armenian people, in the development of its national culture, and in the preservation
        of its national identity. The relationship between the Republic of Armenia and the Armenian
        Apostolic Holy Church may be regulated by a law. Article 19. Ties with the Armenian Diaspora
        The Republic of Armenia shall carry out a policy aimed at developing comprehensive ties and
        preserving Armenianness with the Armenian Diaspora, and shall facilitate repatriation. Based
        on international law, the Republic of Armenia shall contribute to protecting the Armenian
        language and Armenian historical and cultural values in other countries, and advancing
        Armenian educational and cultural life in such countries. Article 20. The State Language of
        the Republic of Armenia The Armenian language shall be the state language of the Republic of
        Armenia. Article 21. The Symbols of the Republic of Armenia The flag of the Republic of
        Armenia shall be tricolor - with equal horizontal stripes of red, blue, and orange. The coat
        of arms of the Republic of Armenia shall depict, in the center on a shield, Mount Ararat
        with Noah’s ark and the coats of arms of the four kingdoms of historical Armenia. The shield
        is held by an eagle and a lion, while a sword, a branch, a sheaf, a chain, and a ribbon are
        depicted below the shield. The detailed description of the flag and the coat of arms shall
        be stipulated by law. The anthem of the Republic of Armenia shall be stipulated by law.
        Article 22. The Capital of the Republic of Armenia The capital of the Republic of Armenia is
        Yerevan.</constitution>
    <constitution place="estonia">
        <url>https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Estonia_2015</url>
        PREAMBLE With unwavering faith and a steadfast will to strengthen and develop the state,
        which embodies the inextinguishable right of the people of Estonia to national
        self-determination and which was proclaimed on 24 February 1918, which is founded on
        liberty, justice and the rule of law, which is created to protect the peace and defend the
        people against aggression from the outside, and which forms a pledge to present and future
        generations for their social progress and welfare, which must guarantee the preservation of
        the Estonian people, the Estonian language and the Estonian culture through the ages, the
        people of Estonia, on the basis of Article 1 of the Constitution which entered into force in
        1938, and in the referendum held on 28 June 1992, have adopted the following Constitution.
        CHAPTER I. GENERAL PROVISIONS Article 1 Estonia is an independent and sovereign democratic
        republic wherein the supreme power of state is vested in the people. The independence and
        sovereignty of Estonia are timeless and inalienable. Article 2 The land, territorial waters
        and airspace of the Estonian state are an inseparable and indivisible whole. Estonia is
        politically a unitary state wherein administrative division shall be provided by law.
        Article 3 The state authority shall be exercised solely pursuant to the Constitution and
        laws which are in conformity therewith. Generally recognized principles and rules of
        international law are an inseparable part of the Estonian legal system. Laws shall be
        published in the prescribed manner. Only published laws have obligatory force. Article 4 The
        activities of the Riigikogu (Parliament of Estonia), the President of the Republic, the
        Government of the Republic, and the courts shall be organized on the principle of separation
        and balance of powers. Article 5 The natural wealth and resources of Estonia are national
        riches which shall be used economically. Article 6 The official language of Estonia is
        Estonian. Article 7 The national colors of Estonia are blue, black and white. The design of
        the national flag and the national coat of arms shall be provided by law. </constitution>
    <constitution place="Kyrgyzstan">
        <url>https://constitutionnet.org/sites/default/files/Kyrgyzstan%20Constitution.pdf</url> We,
        the people of Kyrgyzstan, striving to secure the national revival of the Kyrgyz, the
        protection and development of interests of all nationalities who together with the Kyrgyz
        form the people of Kyrgyzstan; guided by the ancestors’ precepts to live in unity, peace and
        concord; confirming our adherence to human rights and freedoms and the idea of national
        statehood; full of determination to develop the economy, political and legal institutions in
        order to secure a worthy living standard for all; proclaiming our adherence to common human
        moral principles and moral values of national traditions; wishing to establish ourselves
        among the peoples of the world as a free and democratic civil society, through our
        authorized representatives adopt this Constitution. First Chapter THE KYRGYZ REPUBLIC First
        Section GENERAL PRINCIPLES Article 1 1. The Kyrgyz Republic (Kyrgyzstan) is a sovereign,
        unitary, democratic republic created on the basis of a law-governed secular state. 2.
        Sovereignty of the Kyrgyz Republic is not limited and extends throughout its entire
        territory. 3. The people of the Kyrgyz Republic are the bearers of sovereignty and are the
        only source of the state power in the Kyrgyz Republic. 4. The people of the Kyrgyz Republic
        exercise their power directly and through the system of state organs and organs of local
        self-government on the basis of this Constitution and the laws of the Kyrgyz Republic. Only
        the Jogorku Kenesh and the President of the Kyrgyz Republic have the right to represent the
        people of Kyrgyzstan by whom they were elected. 5. Changes and amendments to the
        Constitution of the Kyrgyz Republic, laws of the Kyrgyz Republic and other important issues
        of state life may be put to a referendum (nationwide vote). The procedure for holding a
        referendum is established by a constitutional law. 6. The citizens of the Kyrgyz Republic
        elect the President of the Kyrgyz Republic, Deputies of the Jogorku Kenesh of the Kyrgyz
        Republic and their representatives to organs of local self-government. 7. Elections are free
        and are held on the basis of universal equal and direct suffrage by secret ballot. Citizens
        of the Kyrgyz Republic who have attained the age of 18 have the right to vote. Article 2 1.
        The state and its organs serve the whole society and not a particular group. 2. No group of
        people, no organization or any individual person has the right to assume power in the state.
        The usurpation of state power is a particularly severe crime. Article 3 1. The territory of
        the Kyrgyz Republic within its present boundaries is inviolable and indivisible. 2. The
        territory of the Kyrgyz Republic is divided into administrative territorial units
        established by law for the purposes of the organization of state government and local
        selfgovernment. 3. The cities of Bishkek and Osh are cities of national significance, and
        their status is determined by law. Article 4 1. Private, state, municipal and other forms of
        ownership are recognized and protected in the Kyrgyz Republic. The Kyrgyz Republic
        guarantees the diversity of property forms and their equal protection by law. 2. Land, its
        resources, air space, waters, forests, plant and animal life, and other natural resources
        are the property of the Kyrgyz Republic, are used as the basis of life and activity of the
        people of Kyrgyzstan and are under special protection of the state. 3. Land may also be in
        private, municipal and other forms of ownership. The limits of and procedures for exercising
        of the landowners’ rights and the guarantees of their protection are determined by law. 4.
        The Kyrgyz Republic protects the right of its citizens and juridical persons to own property
        as well as their [citizens’] property and its own [the Republic’s] property located on the
        territory of other states. Article 5 1. The state language of the Kyrgyz Republic is the
        Kyrgyz language. 2. In the Kyrgyz Republic, the Russian language is used as an official
        language. 3. The Kyrgyz Republic guarantees to representatives of all the nationalities that
        constitute the people of Kyrgyzstan the right of preservation of their native language,
        creation of conditions for learning and development [of the language]. 4. It is not
        permitted to infringe on citizens’ rights and freedoms because of their ignorance of the
        state or official language. Article 6 1. The state symbols of the Kyrgyz Republic are the
        state flag, emblem and anthem. Their description and the procedure for their official use
        are determined by law. 2. The capital of the Kyrgyz Republic is the city of Bishkek. 3. The
        monetary unit of the Kyrgyz Republic is a som. Second Section THE STRUCTURE AND FUNCTIONING
        OF THE STATE Article 7 1. The state power in the Kyrgyz Republic is based on the following
        principles: • Supremacy of the power of the people, represented and protected by the
        nationally elected head of the state— the President of the Kyrgyz Republic; • Division of
        state power into the legislative, executive and judicial branches, their concerted
        functioning and interaction; • Responsibility of the state organs before the nation and the
        implementation of their powers in the interest of the nation; • Delimitation of functions of
        state power and local self-government. 2.Within the limits of powers established by this
        Constitution, the state power in the Kyrgyz Republic is represented and executed by: •
        President of the Kyrgyz Republic; • Jogorku Kenesh of the Kyrgyz Republic; • Government of
        the Kyrgyz Republic and organs of executive power subordinate to it; • Constitutional Court
        of the Kyrgyz Republic, Supreme Court of the Kyrgyz Republic, local courts and judges of the
        Kyrgyz Republic. Article 8 1. Political parties, trade unions and other public associations
        may be organized in the Kyrgyz Republic on the basis of free will and common interests. The
        state guarantees the observance of rights and lawful interests of public associations. 2.
        Political parties may participate in state affairs only in the following forms: • Nomination
        of their candidates for the election to the Jogorku Kenesh of the Kyrgyz Republic, state
        posts and organs of local self-government; • Formation of factions in representative organs.
        3. Religion and all cults are separate from the state. 4. In the Kyrgyz Republic the
        following is not permitted: • Merging of state and party institutions, as well as the
        subordination of state activity to party programs and decisions; • Formation and activity of
        party organizations in state establishments and organizations. State officials have the
        right to carry out their party activities outside their work activity; • Membership in
        parties and activity in support of any political party by the military personnel, employees
        of the organs of internal affairs, national security, justice, Procuratura and courts; •
        Organization of political parties on religious and ethnic grounds. Religious organizations
        must not pursue political aims and tasks; • Interference by members of religious
        organizations and cults with the activity of state organs; • Activity of foreign political
        parties, public associations, religious and other organizations detrimental to the
        constitutional system, state and national security. Article 9 1. The Kyrgyz Republic does
        not have goals of expansion, aggression and territorial claims to be resolved by means of
        military force. It rejects the militarization of national life, subordination of the
        government or its activity for the purposes of war. The Armed Forces of Kyrgyzstan are
        organized in accordance with the principles of self-defense and defensive sufficiency. 2.
        The right to conduct war is not recognized except in cases of aggression against Kyrgyzstan
        and other states bound by obligations of collective defense. Permission for each case of a
        unit of the Armed Forces crossing over the borders of the territory of the Kyrgyz Republic
        is a matter of decision of the Jogorku Kenesh of the Kyrgyz Republic adopted by a majority
        no less than two thirds of the total number of Deputies. 3. The use of Armed Forces for the
        resolution of internal political issues is prohibited. Military personnel may be called upon
        to liquidate the consequences of natural disasters and in other similar cases directly
        provided by law. 4. The Kyrgyz Republic observes generally recognized principles of
        international law, seeks universal and just peace, mutually beneficial cooperation, [and]
        resolution of global and regional problems in a peaceful way. Actions capable of disturbing
        the peaceful coexistence of the peoples, propaganda and encouragement of inter-ethnic or
        religious clashes are unconstitutional. Article 10 1. A state of exception in Kyrgyzstan may
        be imposed only in cases of natural disasters, direct threat to the constitutional system,
        mass disorder accompanied by violence and menace to human life, as well as under the
        circumstances and for limited periods indicated in a constitutional law. 2. A state of
        exception throughout the entire territory of the Kyrgyz Republic may be imposed only by the
        Jogorku Kenesh of the Kyrgyz Republic, but a state of exception may be imposed by the
        President of the Kyrgyz Republic in limited locations under circumstances requiring
        immediate action with a prompt, same day notification of that [act] to the Jogorku Kenesh of
        the Kyrgyz Republic, which must confirm the act of the President within no more than three
        days. In the absence of such a confirmation within the indicated time, the state of
        exception is cancelled. 3. Martial law in the Kyrgyz Republic may be imposed by the Jogorku
        Kenesh of the Kyrgyz Republic only in case of aggression against the Kyrgyz Republic. 4. A
        session recess of the Jogorku Kenesh of the Kyrgyz Republic is not permitted during a state
        of exception and martial law. In cases when the Jogorku Kenesh of the Kyrgyz Republic is not
        in session and a state of exception has been imposed by the President, the Jogorku Kenesh of
        the Kyrgyz Republic shall convene without a notice no later than the day following the
        introduction of the state of exception. 5. Referenda, elections, changes in the structure,
        functions and powers of state organs established by the Constitution of the Kyrgyz Republic
        are not allowed during a state of exception and martial law. Article 11 1. The state budget
        of the Kyrgyz Republic consists of the national budget and local budgets, comprising all
        expenditures and revenues of the state. The national budget is approved by the Jogorku
        Kenesh of the Kyrgyz Republic upon presentation by the Government of the Kyrgyz Republic. 2.
        Revenues of the national budget are generated by the total taxes established by law, other
        obligatory payments, income from state property and other receipts. 3. A single system of
        taxation functions on the territory of the Kyrgyz Republic. The right to impose taxes
        belongs to the Jogorku Kenesh of the Kyrgyz Republic. Laws establishing new taxes and
        worsening the standing of the tax payers are not retroactive. 4. In exceptional cases [and]
        for the protection the economic interests of the Kyrgyz Republic, the Government of the
        Kyrgyz Republic has the right to adopt temporary measures in the sphere of taxation by
        changing individual tax rates and other obligatory budget payments with prompt notification
        of the Jogorku Kenesh of the Kyrgyz Republic. 5. The report on the execution of the national
        budget is approved by the Jogorku Kenesh of the Kyrgyz Republic. Article 12 1. The
        Constitution has the supreme juridical force and direct effect in the Kyrgyz Republic. 2.
        Laws and other normative legal acts are adopted on the basis of the Constitution. 3.
        International treaties and agreements that have, according to a procedure established by
        law, come into force [and] to which the Kyrgyz Republic is a party as well as generally
        accepted principles and norms of international law are a component of the legislation of the
        Kyrgyz Republic</constitution>
    <constitution place="lithuania">
        <url>https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Lithuania_2006</url> PREAMBLE THE
        LITHUANIAN NATION – having created the State of Lithuania many centuries ago, – having based
        its legal foundations on the Lithuanian Statutes and the Constitutions of the Republic of
        Lithuania, – having for centuries staunchly defended its freedom and independence, – having
        preserved its spirit, native language, writing, and customs, – embodying the innate right of
        the human being and the Nation to live and create freely in the land of their fathers and
        forefathers—in the independent State of Lithuania, – fostering national concord in the land
        of Lithuania, – striving for an open, just, and harmonious civil society and State under the
        rule of law, by the will of the citizens of the reborn State of Lithuania, adopts and
        proclaims this CHAPTER I. THE STATE OF LITHUANIA Article 1 The State of Lithuania shall be
        an independent democratic republic. Article 2 The State of Lithuania shall be created by the
        Nation. Sovereignty shall belong to the Nation. Article 3 No one may restrict or limit the
        sovereignty of the Nation or make claims to the sovereign powers belonging to the entire
        Nation. The Nation and each citizen shall have the right to resist anyone who encroaches on
        the independence, territorial integrity, and constitutional order of the State of Lithuania
        by force. Article 4 The Nation shall execute its supreme sovereign power either directly or
        through its democratically elected representatives. Article 5 In Lithuania, State power
        shall be executed by the Seimas, the President of the Republic and the Government, and the
        Judiciary. The scope of power shall be limited by the Constitution. State institutions shall
        serve the people. Article 6 The Constitution shall be an integral and directly applicable
        act. Everyone may defend his rights by invoking the Constitution. Article 7 Any law or other
        act, which is contrary to the Constitution, shall be invalid. Only laws which are published
        shall be valid. Ignorance of the law shall not exempt one from liability. Article 8 Seizure
        of State power or of its institution by force shall be considered anti-constitutional
        actions, which are unlawful and invalid. Article 9 The most significant issues concerning
        the life of the State and the Nation shall be decided by referendum. In the cases
        established by law, the Seimas shall announce a referendum. A referendum shall also be
        announced if not less than 300,000 citizens with the electoral right so request. The
        procedure for the announcement and execution of a referendum shall be established by law.
        Article 10 The territory of the State of Lithuania shall be integral and shall not be
        divided into any State-like formations. The State boundaries may be altered only by an
        international treaty of the Republic of Lithuania after it has been ratified by 4/5
        [four-fifths] of all the Members of the Seimas. Article 11 The administrative units of the
        territory of the State of Lithuania and their boundaries shall be established by law.
        Article 12 Citizenship of the Republic of Lithuania shall be acquired by birth and other
        grounds established by law. With the exception of individual cases provided for by law, no
        one may be a citizen of both the Republic of Lithuania and another state at the same time.
        The procedure for the acquisition and loss of citizenship shall be established by law.
        Article 13 The State of Lithuania shall protect its citizens abroad. It shall be prohibited
        to extradite a citizen of the Republic of Lithuania to another state unless an international
        treaty of the Republic of Lithuania establishes otherwise. Article 14 Lithuanian shall be
        the State language. Article 15 The colours of the State flag shall be yellow, green, and
        red. The Coat-of-Arms of the State shall be a white Vytis on a red field. The State
        Coat-of-Arms, flag and their use shall be established by laws. Article 16 The anthem of the
        State shall be “Tautiška giesme” by Vincas Kudirka. Article 17 The capital of the State of
        Lithuania shall be the city of Vilnius, the long-standing historical capital of
        Lithuania.</constitution>

    <constitution place="turkmenistan">
        <url>https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Turkmenistan_2008</url> PREAMBLE We, the
        people of Turkmenistan, based on our inalienable right to determine our destiny; Proceeding
        from the responsibility for present and future of the Motherland; Expressing loyalty to the
        covenant of ancestors to live in unity, peace and harmony; With the aim of protecting the
        national values and interests, strengthening the independence, sovereignty, the status of
        permanent neutrality of Turkmenistan; Guaranteeing the rights and freedoms of each person
        and citizen, and seeking to ensure civil peace and national accord in the society, to
        substantiate the foundations of democracy and democratic, legal, secular state, we adopt the
        present Constitution - the Basic Law of Turkmenistan. SECTION I. FUNDAMENTALS OF THE
        CONSTITUTIONAL SYSTEM OF TURKMENISTAN Article 1 Turkmenistan is a democratic, legal and
        secular state in which the government takes the form of presidential republic. Turkmenistan
        exercises the complete power and complete authority on its territory, and independently
        conducts the internal and foreign policy. The state sovereignty and territory of
        Turkmenistan are homogeneous and indivisible. The State protects the independence,
        territorial integrity of Turkmenistan, and constitutional system, and provides law and
        order. Turkmenistan, by law, has the status of permanent neutrality. The United Nations
        General Assembly resolution "Permanent Neutrality of Turkmenistan" dated 12 December 1995:
        "1. Recognizes and supports the declared status of permanent neutrality of Turkmenistan; 2.
        Calls upon the member states of the United Nations to respect and support this status of
        Turkmenistan and also to respect its independence, sovereignty and territorial integrity."
        The permanent neutrality of Turkmenistan, recognized by the world community, is the basis of
        its domestic and foreign policy. Article 2 The people are the bearer of and the sole source
        of the state power in Turkmenistan. The people of Turkmenistan exercise their power directly
        or through representative bodies. No part (group) of the people, organization or
        individuals, have the right to abrogate the state power. Article 3 In Turkmenistan, the
        people are the highest value of the society and the state. The state is responsible for
        every citizen and creates conditions for free development of the individual, protects the
        life, honour, dignity and freedom, personal integrity, natural and inalienable rights of the
        citizen. Every citizen is responsible before the State for the responsibilities entrusted to
        him by the Constitution and laws. Article 4 State power is based on the principle of
        separation of powers between the legislative, executive and judicial branches, which operate
        independently, balancing each other. Article 5 The state and all of its organs and officials
        are linked by law and constitutional order. The Constitution of Turkmenistan is the Basic
        Law of the State. Rules and regulations laid down in it are unswervingly applicable. The
        laws and other legal acts that contradict the Constitution are null and void. The
        normative-legal acts of the government and administration, and the local self-government,
        are published for general information or made available through other means, except when
        they contain state or other secrets protected by law. The normative-legal Acts affecting the
        rights and freedom of the individual and citizen, if not brought to the general information
        of the public, are invalid from the time of their adoption. Article 6 Turkmenistan, being a
        full subject of the global community, has the foreign policy of permanent neutrality,
        non-interference in the internal affairs of other countries, refrains from the use of force
        and participation in military blocs and alliances, promotes peaceful, friendly and mutually
        beneficial relations with countries in the region and states of the whole world.
        Turkmenistan recognizes the priority of the universally accepted norms of international law.
        If an international treaty (contract) of Turkmenistan establishes rules other than those
        stipulated by the laws of Turkmenistan, the rules of international treaty will apply.
        Article 7 Turkmenistan has its own citizenship. The citizenship is acquired, retained and
        lost in accordance with the law. Citizenship of another state is not recognized for the
        citizens of Turkmenistan. No one can be deprived of citizenship or the right to change
        citizenship. A citizen of Turkmenistan cannot be extradited to another state or expelled
        from the limits of Turkmenistan, or restricted in the right to return to the homeland. The
        citizens of Turkmenistan are guaranteed the protection and patronage of the state in the
        territory of Turkmenistan and beyond its borders. Article 8 Foreign nationals and stateless
        persons enjoy the rights and freedoms, and bear the responsibilities, of citizens of
        Turkmenistan in accordance with law and international treaties of Turkmenistan.
        Turkmenistan, in accordance with universally recognized norms of international right and in
        the order established by the law, gives refuge to foreign citizens and stateless persons.
        Article 9 The property is inviolable. Turkmenistan approves the right to private ownership
        of the means of production, land and other material and intellectual values. They can also
        belong to the associations of citizens and the state. The law establishes objects that are
        exclusive property of the state. The state guarantees equal protection and creation of equal
        conditions for development of all forms of ownership. Confiscation of property is
        prohibited, except for the property acquired by means prohibited by law. Forced confiscation
        of property is permissible only in cases stipulated by law. Article 10 The economy of
        Turkmenistan is based on the principles of market relations. The state encourages and
        supports entrepreneurship, promotes development of small and medium enterprises. Article 11
        The state is responsible for safeguarding the national historical and cultural heritage,
        natural environment, ensuring equality between social and ethnic communities. The state
        encourages scientific and artistic creativity and distribution of its positive results,
        promotes development of international relations in the fields of science, culture, education
        and training, sports and tourism. Article 12 The state guarantees freedom of religion and
        worship, and equality before the law. Religious organizations are separate from the state,
        cannot interfere in the state affairs and carry out state functions. The public education
        system is separate from religious organizations and is secular. Each person independently
        determines his attitude toward religion, has the right to, individually or jointly with
        others, profess any religion or none, to express and disseminate beliefs related to attitude
        toward religion, to participate in religious observances, rituals, and ceremonies. Article
        13 In order to protect the state sovereignty and security, Turkmenistan has its own armed
        forces. Article 14 Turkmen is the state [official] language of Turkmenistan. The use of
        their native language is guaranteed to all citizens of Turkmenistan. Article 15 The State
        Flag, the State Emblem, and the National Anthem are the Symbols of Turkmenistan. The flag,
        national emblem and national anthem are established and protected by law. Article 16 The
        administrative-territorial structure of Turkmenistan consists of: Velayats (provinces),
        cities with right of Velayat, Etraps (districts), cities with right of district, cities
        (towns) in district, settlements, Gengeshlyk. The territory of one or more villages forms a
        Gengeshlyk. Article 17 Ashgabat is the capital of Turkmenistan. SECTION II. RIGHTS, FREEDOMS
        AND DUTIES OF THE CITIZENS OF TURKMENISTAN Article 18 The rights and freedoms of the
        individual are inviolable and inalienable. No one can be deprived of their rights and
        freedoms, or restrictions on their rights and freedoms, except in accordance with the
        Constitution and laws. The enumeration in the Constitution and laws of certain rights and
        freedoms can not be used to deny or diminish the rights and freedoms of others. Article 19
        Turkmenistan guarantees the equality of rights and freedoms of individual and citizen, and
        also the equality of the individual and citizen before the law regardless of their
        nationality, race, gender, origin, property and official status, place of residence,
        language, religion, political beliefs, party affiliation or lack of affiliation to any
        party. Article 20 Men and Women in Turkmenistan have equal civil rights. Violation of
        equality on the basis of gender is punishable by law. Article 21 The exercise of rights and
        freedoms must not violate the rights and freedoms of others, as well as the requirements of
        morality, law, public order, [or] cause damage to national security. Article 22 Each
        individual has the right to life and liberty and the exercise (of this right). No one can be
        deprived of the right to life. The right of each person to free life is protected by the
        state on the basis of law. The death penalty has been abolished in Turkmenistan. Article 23
        A person cannot be restrict in or deprived of rights, convicted or punished, except in
        strict accordance with the law. No one can be subjected to torture, cruel, inhuman or
        degrading treatment, or punishment, and without his consent to medical (medicinal or
        medical) or other experiments. A person can be arrested by the court or with the approval of
        the prosecutor only on the grounds precisely specified by the law. In urgent cases,
        precisely specified by the law, the state authorities have the right to detain the citizens
        temporarily. Article 24 Every citizen has the right to support of state in obtaining or
        acquiring a comfortable living accommodation, and construction of individual housing. The
        home is inviolable. No one has the right to enter a home or otherwise violate the sanctity
        of the home against the wishes of people living there without any legal grounds. Protecting
        the home against unlawful assault (encroachment) is the right of the individual and citizen.
        No one can be deprived of their living accommodation except on the grounds established by
        law. Article 25 Everyone has the right to protection from arbitrary interference in their
        privacy, as well as infringement of the rules of secrecy of correspondence, telephone and
        other (means of) communication, attacks on their honour and reputation. Article 26 Every
        citizen has the right to move freely and choose their place of residence in Turkmenistan.
        Restrictions on entry into separate territories, and movement in those territories, can only
        be set by law. Article 27 Men and women having reached the marriageable age have the right,
        by mutual consent, to marry and create families. Spouses have equal rights in family
        relations. Parents and substitute parents have the right and obligation to raise the
        children, care for their health, development, education, prepare them for work, and impart
        to them the culture of respect for the law, historical and national traditions. Adult
        children are obliged to take care of their parents and to extend help (support) to them.
        Article 28 Citizens of Turkmenistan have the right to freedom of opinion and expression, as
        well as to receive information if it is not a state or other secret protected by law.
        Article 29 Citizens are guaranteed freedom of assembly, rallies and demonstrations in the
        manner prescribed by law. Article 30 Citizens have the right to form political parties and
        other public associations operating within the framework of the Constitution and laws.
        Prohibited is the establishment and activity of political parties, other public,
        paramilitary associations, aimed at bringing violent change to the constitutional order,
        introducing violence in their activity, opposing the constitutional rights and freedoms of
        citizens, advocating war, racial, national or religious hatred, encroaching on the health
        and morals of the people, as well as the political parties with ethnic or religious
        attributes. Article 31 Every citizen has the right to participate in managing the affairs of
        the society and state, either directly or through freely elected representatives. Article 32
        Citizens have the right to elect and be elected to the bodies of state authority. Citizens
        of Turkmenistan, in accordance with their abilities and professional training, have equal
        right to access to public service. Article 33 Citizens have the right to work, choice of
        profession at their own discretion, sort of employment and place of work, to safe and
        healthy working conditions. Wage earners are entitled to compensation, appropriate to amount
        and quality of work. This compensation cannot be less than the subsistence minimum
        established by the state. Article 34 Citizens have the right to rest, as expressed in
        establishment of limits of work week, grant of annual paid holidays, and days of weekly
        rest. The State creates favourable conditions for recreation and use of leisure time.
        Article 35 Citizens have the right to healthcare, including free use of the network of
        public health institutions. Paid medical and non-traditional healthcare is permitted under,
        and in accordance with, the procedure established by law. Article 36 Everyone has the right
        to favourable environment. The State supervises the management of natural resources in order
        to protect and improve living conditions, as well as environmental protection and
        regeneration. Article 37 Citizens have the right to social security in old age, sickness,
        disability, loss of ability to work, loss of breadwinner, unemployment. Families with large
        number of children, orphans, veterans, people who lost their health while protecting the
        state or public interests, are provided additional support and privileges from state and
        public funds. Article 38 Every citizen has the right to education. Secondary education is
        compulsory; everyone is entitled to receive it in public schools free of charge. The state
        ensures availability of vocational education for each person according to their abilities.
        On the basis and in the manner prescribed by the legislation of Turkmenistan, governmental
        and non-governmental organizations, citizens have the right to engage in paid work activity.
        The State sets educational standards, mandatory for all educational institutions. Article 39
        Citizens of Turkmenistan have the right to freedom of artistic, scientific and technical
        creativity. All rights (copyrights) and interests of citizens in the area of scientific,
        technical, creative, artistic, literary and cultural activities are protected by law. The
        State contributes to the development of science, culture, arts, folk arts, sports and
        tourism. Article 40 The exercise of the rights and freedoms is inseparable from the
        performance by the individual and citizen their responsibilities toward the society and the
        state. Everyone, living or staying temporarily in the territory of Turkmenistan, is obliged
        to abide by the Constitution, the laws, and respect the national traditions. Article 41
        Protection of Turkmenistan is the sacred duty of every citizen. General conscription is
        compulsory for the male citizens of Turkmenistan. Article 42 Everyone is required to pay
        state taxes and other payments in the manner and extent established by law. Article 43
        Citizens are guaranteed judicial protection of honour and dignity, personal and political
        rights and freedoms of individual and citizen [as stipulated] by the Constitution and laws.
        Citizens have the right to appeal in the court against the decisions and actions of the
        state bodies, public associations and officials. Article 44 Citizens have the right to seek
        redress in courts for material and moral damage caused to them by unlawful actions of state
        bodies, other organizations and their employees, as well as private individuals. Article 45
        A person cannot be compelled to testify and give evidence against self and close relatives.
        Evidence obtained as a result of mental or physical influence, as well as through other
        illegal methods, has no legal force. Article 46 A law, aggravating the situation of
        citizens, shall not be retroactive. No one can be held responsible for actions that, at the
        time of their commission, were not recognized by law as offence. Article 47 The
        implementation of the rights and freedoms of citizens may be suspended only in a state of
        emergency or martial law in a manner and within the limits established by the Constitution
        and laws. SECTION III. THE SYSTEM OF GOVERNMENT AND ADMINISTRATION IN TURKMENISTAN Chapter
        I. General Provisions Article 48 The highest state authority and government in Turkmenistan
        is exercised by the President of Turkmenistan, the Mejlis (parliament) of Turkmenistan, the
        Cabinet of Ministers of Turkmenistan, and the Supreme Court of Turkmenistan. Article 49
        Local district representatives and executives bodies are the local authority in Velayats,
        cities with the right of Velayat, districts, and districts with rights of city, and in towns
        of Etraps, settlements, and the Gengeshlyks the local authority are
        Gengeshes.</constitution>
</constitutions>
