<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<constitution place="estonia">
    <url>https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Estonia_2015</url> PREAMBLE With unwavering
    faith and a steadfast will to strengthen and develop the state, which embodies the
    inextinguishable right of the people of Estonia to national self-determination and which was
    proclaimed on 24 February 1918, which is founded on liberty, justice and the rule of law, which
    is created to protect the peace and defend the people against aggression from the outside, and
    which forms a pledge to present and future generations for their social progress and welfare,
    which must guarantee the preservation of the Estonian people, the Estonian language and the
    Estonian culture through the ages, the people of Estonia, on the basis of Article 1 of the
    Constitution which entered into force in 1938, and in the referendum held on 28 June 1992, have
    adopted the following Constitution. CHAPTER I. GENERAL PROVISIONS Article 1 Estonia is an
    independent and sovereign democratic republic wherein the supreme power of state is vested in
    the people. The independence and sovereignty of Estonia are timeless and inalienable. Article 2
    The land, territorial waters and airspace of the Estonian state are an inseparable and
    indivisible whole. Estonia is politically a unitary state wherein administrative division shall
    be provided by law. Article 3 The state authority shall be exercised solely pursuant to the
    Constitution and laws which are in conformity therewith. Generally recognized principles and
    rules of international law are an inseparable part of the Estonian legal system. Laws shall be
    published in the prescribed manner. Only published laws have obligatory force. Article 4 The
    activities of the Riigikogu (Parliament of Estonia), the President of the Republic, the
    Government of the Republic, and the courts shall be organized on the principle of separation and
    balance of powers. Article 5 The natural wealth and resources of Estonia are national riches
    which shall be used economically. Article 6 The official language of Estonia is Estonian.
    Article 7 The national colors of Estonia are blue, black and white. The design of the national
    flag and the national coat of arms shall be provided by law. </constitution>
