<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../constitution_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<constitution country="Estonia">
    <meta>
        <source>
            <title/>
            <container/>
            <url>https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Estonia_2015</url>
        </source>
    </meta>
    <body><preamble>PREAMBLE With unwavering faith and a steadfast will to strengthen and develop
            the state, which embodies the inextinguishable right of the people of Estonia to
            national self-determination and which was proclaimed on 24 February 1918, which is
            founded on liberty, justice and the rule of law, which is created to protect the peace
            and defend the people against aggression from the outside, and which forms a pledge to
            present and future generations for their social progress and welfare, which must
            guarantee the preservation of the Estonian people, the Estonian language and the
            Estonian culture through the ages, the people of Estonia, on the basis of Article 1 of
            the Constitution which entered into force in 1938, and in the referendum held on 28 June
            1992, have adopted the following Constitution. </preamble>
        <chapter>
            <chap_title>CHAPTER I. GENERAL PROVISIONS</chap_title>
           <section> <s_text><article><a_header>Article 1 </a_header><a_text>Estonia is an independent and sovereign democratic republic wherein
                the supreme power of state is vested in the people. The independence and sovereignty
                of Estonia are timeless and inalienable. </a_text></article>
            <article><a_header>Article 2</a_header><a_text> The land, territorial waters and airspace of the Estonian state are
                an inseparable and indivisible whole. Estonia is politically a unitary state wherein
                administrative division shall be provided by law.</a_text></article>
            <article><a_header>Article 3</a_header><a_text> The state authority shall be exercised solely pursuant to the
                Constitution and laws which are in conformity therewith. Generally recognized
                principles and rules of international law are an inseparable part of the Estonian
                legal system. Laws shall be published in the prescribed manner. Only published laws
                have obligatory force. </a_text></article>
            <article><a_header>Article 4 </a_header><a_text>The activities of the Riigikogu (Parliament of Estonia), the
                President of the Republic, the Government of the Republic, and the courts shall be
                organized on the principle of separation and balance of powers.</a_text> </article>
            <article><a_header>Article 5 </a_header><a_text>The natural wealth and resources of Estonia are national riches which
                shall be used economically.</a_text></article>
            <article><a_header>Article 6</a_header><a_text> The official language of Estonia is Estonian. </a_text></article>
            <article> <a_header>Article 7</a_header> <a_text>The national colors of Estonia are blue, black and white. The design
                of the national flag and the national coat of arms shall be provided by
                law.</a_text></article></s_text></section>
        </chapter></body>
</constitution>
