<?xml-model href="../constitution_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<constitution country="Georgia">
    <meta>
        <source>
            <title>Georgia 1995 (rev. 2018)</title>
            <container>Constitute Project</container>
            <url>https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Georgia_2018</url>
        </source>
    </meta>

    <body>
        <preamble>PREAMBLE We, the citizens of Georgia - whose firm will it is to establish a
                <gov>democratic social order</gov>, economic freedom, and a legal and a social
            state; to secure <international>universally recognised human rights and
                freedoms</international>; and to enhance <sovereignty>state
                independence</sovereignty> and <peace>peaceful relations with other peoples</peace>
            - drawing on the <nationalism>centuries-old traditions of the statehood of the Georgian
                nation and the historical and legal legacy of the Constitution of Georgia of
                1921</nationalism>, proclaim this Constitution before<religion r_type="neutral"> God
            </religion>and the nation. </preamble>
        <chapter>

            <chap_title>CHAPTER ONE. GENERAL PROVISIONS</chap_title>
            <section>
                <s_text>
                    <!--regex: (Article [1-9]+).*?\n to find a_heading-->
                    <article>
                        <a_header> Article 1. State sovereignty </a_header>
                        <!--would nationalism also count as history-->
                        <a_text> Georgia is an <sovereignty>independent, unified and indivisible
                                state</sovereignty> as confirmed by the <nationalism>Referendum of
                                31 March 1991 held in the entire territory of the country, including
                                the Autonomous Soviet Socialist Republic of Abkhazia and the former
                                Autonomous Region of South Ossetia, and by the Act of Restoration of
                                State Independence of Georgia of 9 April 1991</nationalism>. The
                            territory of the state of Georgia was determined on 21 December 1991.
                            The territorial integrity of Georgia and the inviolability of the state
                            border is confirmed by the Constitution and laws of Georgia, and
                                <international>recognised by the world community of nations and by
                                international organisations</international>. The <treason>alienation
                                of the territory of the state of Georgia shall be
                                prohibited</treason>. The <international>state border may be changed
                                only by a bilateral agreement with a neighbouring
                                state</international>.</a_text>
                    </article>

                    <article>
                        <a_header> Article 2. State symbols </a_header>
                        <a_text>'Georgia' is the name of the state of Georgia.
                                <capital>Tbilisi</capital> is the capital of Georgia. <language
                                lang_type="native">The official language of Georgia shall be
                                Georgian, and, in the Autonomous Republic of Abkhazia, also
                                Abkhazian. The official language is protected by the organic
                                law</language>. The <symbols>state flag, the coat of arms, and the
                                anthem of Georgia are established by the organic law</symbols>,
                            which shall be revised in accordance with the procedure established for
                            revising the Constitution.</a_text>
                    </article>

                    <article>
                        <a_header> Article 3. Democracy </a_header>
                        <a_text> Georgia is a <gov>democratic republic</gov>. <consent>People are
                                the source of state authority</consent>. People exercise power
                            through their <parties p_type="multi">representatives, as well as
                                through referendums</parties> and other forms of <gov>direct
                                democracy</gov>. No one shall have the right to seize power. The
                            current term of a body elected in general<elections> elections shall not
                                be extended or reduced by the Constitution or law</elections>.
                                <parties p_type="multi">Political parties</parties> shall
                            participate in the formation and exercise of the political will of the
                            people. The activities of political parties shall be based on the
                            principles of freedom, equality, transparency, and <parties
                                p_type="multi">intra-party democracy</parties>. </a_text>
                    </article>

                    <article>
                        <a_header> Article 4. Legal state </a_header>
                        <a_text> Georgia is a <sovereignty>legal state</sovereignty>. The State
                            acknowledges and protects <international>universally recognised human
                                rights and freedoms as eternal and supreme human values. While
                                exercising authority, the people and the State shall be bound by
                                these rights and freedoms as directly applicable
                            law</international>. The Constitution<international> shall not deny
                                other universally recognised human rights and freedoms that are not
                                explicitly referred to herein</international>, but that inherently
                            derive from the principles of the Constitution. <separation>State
                                authority shall be exercised based on the principle of the
                                separation of powers</separation>. <consent>State authority shall be
                                exercised within the ambit of the Constitution and law</consent>.
                            The Constitution of Georgia shall be the supreme law of the State.
                            General rules for the adoption and issuance of legislative and other
                            normative acts, and their hierarchy, shall be determined by the organic
                                law.<international> The legislation of Georgia shall comply with the
                                universally recognised principles and norms of international
                                law</international>. <international>An international treaty of
                                Georgia shall take precedence over domestic normative
                            </international>acts <sovereignty>unless it comes into conflict with the
                                Constitution or the Constitutional Agreement of
                                Georgia</sovereignty>. </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header> Article 5. Social state </a_header>
                        <a_text> Georgia is a <gov>social state</gov>. <ind_rights ind_type="misc"
                                >The State shall take care of strengthening the principles of social
                                justice, social equality and social solidarity within
                                society</ind_rights>. The <ind_rights ind_type="misc">State shall
                                take care of the equitable socio-economic and demographic
                                development in the entire territory of the country</ind_rights>.
                            Special conditions for the development of high mountain regions shall be
                            determined by law.<ind_rights ind_type="misc"> The State shall take care
                                of human health care and social protection, ensuring the subsistence
                                minimum and decent housing, and protecting the welfare of the
                                family</ind_rights>. <ind_rights ind_type="misc">The State shall
                                promote the employment of citizens. Conditions for providing the
                                subsistence minimum shall be determined by law</ind_rights>.
                                <ind_rights ind_type="misc">The State shall take care of
                                environmental protection and the rational use of natural
                                resources</ind_rights>. <nationalism>The State shall take care of
                                the protection of national values, identity and cultural
                                heritage</nationalism>, and of the development of <ind_rights
                                ind_type="misc">education, science and culture</ind_rights>. The
                            State shall take care of the <ind_rights ind_type="misc">development of
                                sports, establishing a healthy lifestyle, and engaging children and
                                youth in physical education and sports</ind_rights>. The State shall
                            take care of<ind_rights ind_type="citizenship"> maintaining and
                                developing connections with the homeland for Georgian compatriots
                                residing abroad</ind_rights>.</a_text>
                    </article>

                    <article>
                        <a_header> Article 6. Economic freedom </a_header>
                        <a_text><property prop_type="private"> Economic freedom is recognised and
                                guaranteed</property>. The State shall take care of developing a
                                <economic e_type="free">free and open economy</economic>, and
                                <property prop_type="private">free enterprise and
                                competition</property>. <property prop_type="private">Abolishing the
                                universal right to private property shall be prohibited</property>.
                        </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header> Article 7. Basis of territorial arrangement </a_header>
                        <a_text> The following shall fall within <consent>the exclusive competence
                                of the supreme state authorities of Georgia</consent>: a.
                                <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">legislation on human
                                rights</ind_rights>, <ind_rights ind_type="citizenship">Georgian
                                citizenship</ind_rights>, <ind_rights ind_type="citizenship"
                                >migration>, entry into and exit from the country</ind_rights>, and
                            the <international>temporary or permanent stay of aliens and stateless
                                persons</international> in Georgia; b.<property prop_type="other">
                                criminal, penitentiary, civil, intellectual property,
                                administrative, labour and procedural legislation; legislation
                                pertaining to land, minerals, and other natural resources;
                                pharmaceutical legislation; legislation on obtaining the status of
                                educational institution, and on accreditation, and academic degrees;
                                and legislation on the National Academy of Sciences</property>; c.
                                <international>foreign policy and international relations; foreign
                                trade, customs and tariff regimes</international>; d. state defence,
                            military industry and arms trade; <peace>issues relating to war and
                                truce</peace>; determining and introducing the legal regime of a
                            state of emergency and martial law; the armed forces; courts and
                            prosecution; state security; criminal police and
                                investigation;<sovereignty> the status, regime and protection of the
                                state border; and a cordon sanitaire on the border; </sovereignty>
                                e.<currency> state finances and state loans; the printing and
                                emission of money; and legislation on banking, credit, insurance,
                                tax and trade of national significance</currency>; f. <property
                                prop_type="public">railways and motor roads of national
                                significance; the integrated energy system and regime;
                                communications</property>; <property prop_type="public">the status
                                and protection of territorial waters, airspace, the continental
                                shelf and the exclusive economic zone</property>; <property
                                prop_type="public">aviation; the merchant fleet; ensigns; harbours
                                of national significance; fishing in oceans and high seas;
                                meteorology; environmental monitoring systems; standards and models;
                                geodesy and cartography; determining the precise time; and state
                                statistics</property>. g. The <levels l_type="federalist">powers of
                                the Autonomous Republic of Abkhazia and the Autonomous Republic of
                                Ajara, and procedures for exercising such powers shall be determined
                                by the constitutional laws</levels> of Georgia that are an integral
                            part of the Constitution of Georgia. h. The <separation>state
                                territorial arrangement of Georgia shall be revised by a
                                constitutional law of Georgia on the basis of the principle of the
                                separation of powers</separation> after the complete restoration of
                            the jurisdiction of Georgia over the entire territory of the country. i.
                                <levels l_type="neutral">The citizens of Georgia shall regulate
                                affairs of local importance through local self-government in
                                accordance with the legislation of Georgia</levels>. <levels
                                l_type="federalist">The separation of the powers of state authority
                                and self-governing units is based on the principle of
                                subsidiarity</levels>. <levels l_type="federalist">The State ensures
                                that the financial resources of self-governing units correspond with
                                their powers as determined by the organic law</levels>. j.<levels
                                l_type="unitary"> An exclusive economic zone shall be established in
                                Anaklia on the basis of the organic law, where a special legal
                                regime shall apply. Other exclusive economic zones with special
                                legal regimes may also be established on the basis of the organic
                                law.</levels></a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header> Article 8. Relationship between the State and the Apostolic
                            Autocephalous Orthodox Church of Georgia </a_header>
                        <a_text>Along with <ind_rights ind_type="racial-equality">freedom of belief
                                and religion</ind_rights>, the State shall recognise the outstanding
                            role of the <nationalism>Apostolic Autocephalous Orthodox Church of
                                Georgia in the history of Georgia</nationalism>, and <religion
                                r_type="secular">its independence from the State</religion>. The
                                <religion r_type="state-religion">relationship between the state of
                                Georgia and the Apostolic Autocephalous Orthodox Church of Georgia
                                shall be determined by a constitutional agreement</religion>, which
                            shall be <international>in full compliance with the universally
                                recognised principles and norms of international law in the area of
                                human rights and freedoms</international>.</a_text>
                    </article>

                </s_text>
            </section>
        </chapter>
    </body>
</constitution>
