<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<constituiton>
PREAMBLE

We, the citizens of Georgia, whose firm will is to establish a democratic social order, economic freedom, a rule-of-law and a social state, to secure universally recognised human rights and freedoms, to enhance state independence and peaceful relations with other peoples, drawing inspiration from centuries-old traditions of statehood of the Georgian nation and the historical-legal legacy of the Constitution of Georgia of 1921, proclaim the present Constitution before God and the nation.

CHAPTER ONE. GENERAL PROVISIONS

Article 1

Georgia is an independent, unified, and indivisible state, as confirmed by the Referendum of 31 March 1991 held throughout the territory of the country, including the Autonomous Soviet Socialist Republic of Abkhazia and the Former Autonomous Region of South Ossetia, and by the Act of Restoration of State Independence of Georgia of 9 April 1991.
The political structure of the State of Georgia is a democratic republic.
‘Georgia’ is the name of the State of Georgia.
Article 2

The territory of the State of Georgia is determined as of 21 December 1991. The territorial integrity of Georgia and the inviolability of state borders is acknowledged by the Constitution and laws of Georgia, and recognised by the world community of nations and international organisations.
Alienation/transfer of the territory of Georgia shall be prohibited. The state borders may be changed only by a bilateral agreement with a neighbouring state.
Constitutional law shall determine the territorial state structure of Georgia on the basis of the principle of delimitation of powers after the complete restoration of jurisdiction of Georgia over the whole territory of the country.
The citizens of Georgia registered in a self-governing unit shall regulate the affairs of local importance through local self-government, without prejudice to the state sovereignty, according to the legislation of Georgia. State authorities shall promote the development of local self-governance.
Article 3

The following shall fall within the exclusive competence of supreme state authorities of Georgia:
legislation on Georgian citizenship, human rights and freedoms, emigration and immigration, entering and leaving the country, temporary or permanent stay of aliens and stateless persons in Georgia
status, regime, and protection of the state borders, status and protection of territorial waters, airspace, continental shelf and Exclusive Economic Zone
state defence and security, military forces, military industry, and trade in arms
issues of war and peace, determination and introduction of legal regime of state of emergency and martial law
foreign policy and international relations
foreign trade, customs and tariff regimes
state finances and state loans, money issuing, as well as banking, credit, insurance, and tax legislation
standards and models, geodesy and cartography, determination of exact time, state statistics
unified energy system and regime, communications, merchant fleet, ensigns, harbors of state significance, airports and aerodromes, control of airspace, transit and air transport, registration of air transport, meteorological service, environmental observation systems
railways and motor roads of state significance
fishing in oceans and high seas
sanitary cordon on borders
pharmaceutical legislation
legislation on accreditation of educational institutions and academic degrees
intellectual property legislation
trade, criminal, civil, administrative and labour, penitentiary and procedural legislation
criminal police and investigation
land, minerals, and natural resources legislation.
Issues falling within the joint competence shall be determined separately.
The status of the Autonomous Republic of Ajara shall be determined by the Constitutional Law of Georgia on the Status of the Autonomous Republic of Ajara.
The status of the Autonomous Republic of Abkhazia shall be determined by the Constitutional Law of Georgia on the Status of the Autonomous Republic of Abkhazia.
The status and powers of Lazika city shall be defined in an organic law of Georgia.
Article 4

After appropriate conditions have been created and local self-government bodies have been formed throughout the territory of Georgia, 2 chambers shall be set up within the Parliament of Georgia: the Council of Republic and the Senate.
The Council of Republic shall consist of members elected under the principle of proportionality.
The Senate shall consist of members elected from the Autonomous Republic of Abkhazia, the Autonomous Republic of Ajara, and other territorial units of Georgia, as well as 5 members appointed by the President of Georgia.
The composition, powers, and election procedure of the chambers shall be defined by an organic law.
Article 5

People shall be the source of state authority in Georgia. State authority shall be exercised within the ambit of the Constitution.
People shall exercise their power through a referendum, other forms of direct democracy, and their representatives.
No one shall have the right to appropriate or illegally seize power.
State authority shall be exercised under the principle of separation of powers.
Article 6

The Constitution of Georgia shall be the supreme law of the State. All other legal acts shall comply with the Constitution.
The legislation of Georgia shall comply with the universally recognised principles and rules of international law. A treaty or international agreement of Georgia, unless it comes into conflict with the Constitution or the Constitutional Agreement of Georgia, shall take precedence over domestic normative acts.
Article 7

The State shall recognise and protect universally recognised human rights and freedoms as eternal and supreme human values. While exercising authority, the people and the State shall be bound by these rights and freedoms as directly applicable law.

Article 8

The official language of Georgia shall be Georgian. The official language of the Autonomous Republic of Abkhazia shall be Georgian and Abkhazian.

Article 9

The State shall declare absolute freedom of belief and religion. At the same time, the State shall recognise the outstanding role of the Apostolic Autocephalous Orthodox Church of Georgia in the history of Georgia and its independence from the State.
Relations between the State of Georgia and the Apostolic Autocephalous Orthodox Church of Georgia shall be governed by Constitutional Agreement. Constitutional Agreement shall be in full compliance with the universally recognised principles and norms of international law, specifically in terms of human rights and fundamental freedoms.
Article 10

Tbilisi is the capital of Georgia.

Article 11

The state symbols of Georgia shall be defined by an organic law.
</constituiton>