<?xml-model href="../constitution_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<constitution country="Kazakhstan">
    <meta>
        <source>
            <title>Kazakhstan Constitution</title>
            <container/>
            <url>https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Kazakhstan_2017</url>
        </source>
    </meta>

    <body>
        <preamble>PREAMBLE We, the people of Kazakhstan, united by common historic fate, creating
            state on the indigenous Kazakh land, considering ourselves peace-loving and civil
            society, dedicated to the ideals of freedom, equality and concord, wishing to take
            worthy place in the world community, realizing our high responsibility before the
            present and future generations, proceeding from our sovereign right, accept this
            Constitution.</preamble>
        <chapter>
            <chap_title>SECTION I. GENERAL PROVISIONS</chap_title>
            <section>
                <s_text>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 1</a_header>
                        <!--Maybe a relgious tag so that religion in some constitutions can be compared against secularism in others-->
                        <a_text>The Republic of Kazakhstan proclaims itself <gov>democratic</gov>,
                                <religion r_type="neutral">secular</religion>, legal and social
                            state whose highest values are an <ind_rights ind_type="liberty"
                                >individual, his life, rights and freedoms.</ind_rights> The
                            fundamental principles of the activity of the Republic are public
                            concord and political stability; economic development for the benefit of
                            all the nation; <nationalism>Kazakhstan patriotism and resolution of the
                                most important issues of the affairs of state by democratic methods
                                including voting at an all-nation referendum or in the
                                Parliament</nationalism>.</a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 2</a_header>
                        <a_text>
                            <gov>The Republic of Kazakhstan is unitary state with presidential form
                                of government.</gov> The sovereignty of the Republic extends to its
                            entire territory. The state ensures the integrity, inviolability and
                            inalienability of its territory. <capital>The administrative-territorial
                                division of the Republic, the status of its capital shall determine
                                by law. Capital of Kazakhstan is the city of Astana.</capital> A
                            special legal regime in the financial sphere may be established within
                            the city of Astana in accordance with the constitutional law.
                                <sovereignty>The names “Republic of Kazakhstan” and “Kazakhstan”
                                have the same meaning.</sovereignty></a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 3</a_header>
                        <a_text><consent>The people shall be the only source of state
                                power.</consent>
                            <elections>The people shall exercise power directly through an
                                all-nation referendum and free elections as well as delegate the
                                execution of their power to state institutions.</elections> Nobody
                            shall have the right to appropriate power in the Republic of Kazakhstan.
                            Appropriation of power shall be persecuted by law. <consent>The right to
                                act on behalf of the people and the state shall belong to the
                                President as well as to Parliament of the Republic within the limits
                                of the constitutional powers.</consent>
                            <separation>The government and other state bodies shall act on behalf of
                                the state only within the limits of their delegated authorities. The
                                state power in the Republic of Kazakhstan is unified and executed on
                                the basis of the Constitution and laws in accordance with the
                                principle of its division into the legislative, executive and
                                judicial branches and system of checks and balances that governs
                                their interaction.</separation></a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 4</a_header>
                        <a_text>The provisions of the Constitution, the laws corresponding to it,
                            other regulatory legal acts, international treaty and other commitments
                            of the Republic as well as regulatory resolutions of Constitutional
                            Council and the Supreme Court of the Republic shall be the functioning
                            law in the Republic of Kazakhstan. The Constitution shall have the
                            highest juridical force and direct effect on the entire territory of the
                            Republic. International treaties ratified by the Republic shall have
                            priority over its laws. The procedure and conditions of the application
                            in the territory of the Republic of Kazakhstan of international treaties
                            to which Kazakhstan is a party are determined by the legislation of the
                            Republic. All laws, international treaties of which the Republic is
                            party shall be published. Official publication of regulatory legal acts
                            dealing with the rights, freedoms and responsibilities of citizens shall
                            be necessary condition for their application.></a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 5</a_header>
                        <a_text> The Republic of Kazakhstan shall recognize ideological and
                            political<!-- Interesting that they don't mention freedom of politcs and idealogy, just "diversity"-->
                            diversity. <parties p_type="0">The formation of political party
                                organizations in state bodies shall not be permitted. Public
                                associations shall be equal before the law.</parties> Illegal
                            interference of the state in the affairs of public associations and of
                            public associations in the affairs of the state, imposing the functions
                            of state institutions on public associations shall not be permitted.
                                <parties p_type="0">Formation and functioning of public associations
                                pursuing the goals or actions directed toward violent change of the
                                constitutional system, violation of the integrity of the Republic,
                                undermining the security of the state, inciting social, racial,
                                national, religious, class and tribal enmity, as well as formation
                                of unauthorized paramilitary units shall be prohibited.</parties>
                            Activities of political parties and trade unions of other states,
                            religious parties as well as financing political parties and trade
                            unions by foreign legal entities and citizens, foreign states and
                            international organizations shall not be permitted in the
                                Republic<religion r_type="state-religion">. Activities of
                                <!--Treason?--> foreign religious associations on the territory of
                                the Republic as well as appointment of heads of religious
                                associations in the Republic by foreign
                                religious<!-- Does this mean that the state has control over religous leaders?-->
                                centers shall be carried out in coordination with the respective
                                state institutions of the Republic.</religion></a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>>Article 6</a_header>
                        <a_text><property prop_type="public">The Republic of Kazakhstan shall
                                recognize and by the same token protect state and private property.
                                Property shall impose obligations, and its use must simultaneously
                                benefit the society. Subjects and objects of ownership, the scope
                                and limits of the rights of proprietors, and guarantees of their
                                protection shall be determined by law. The land and underground
                                resources, waters, flora and fauna, other natural resources shall be
                                owned by the state. The land may also be privately owned on terms,
                                conditions and within the limits established by
                                legislation.</property></a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 7</a_header>
                        <a_text><language>The state language of the Republic of Kazakhstan shall be
                                the Kazak language. In state institutions and local
                                self-administrative bodies the Russian language shall be officially
                                used on equal grounds along with the Kazak language. The state shall
                                promote conditions for the study and development of the languages of
                                the people of Kazakhstan.</language></a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 8</a_header>
                        <a_text><international>The Republic of Kazakhstan shall respect principles
                                and norms of international law, pursue the policy of cooperation and
                                good-neighborly relations between states, their equality and
                                non-interference in each other’s domestic affairs, peaceful
                                settlement of international disputes and renounce the first use of
                                the military force.</international></a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 9</a_header>
                        <a_text><symbols>The Republic of Kazakhstan shall have its state symbols -
                                the flag, emblem and anthem. Their description and order of official
                                use shall be established by the constitutional law.</symbols>
                        </a_text>
                    </article>
                </s_text>
            </section>
        </chapter>
    </body>
</constitution>
