<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<constitution place="Kyrgyzstan">
    <url>https://constitutionnet.org/sites/default/files/Kyrgyzstan%20Constitution.pdf</url> We, the
    people of Kyrgyzstan, striving to secure the national revival of the Kyrgyz, the protection and
    development of interests of all nationalities who together with the Kyrgyz form the people of
    Kyrgyzstan; guided by the ancestors’ precepts to live in unity, peace and concord; confirming
    our adherence to human rights and freedoms and the idea of national statehood; full of
    determination to develop the economy, political and legal institutions in order to secure a
    worthy living standard for all; proclaiming our adherence to common human moral principles and
    moral values of national traditions; wishing to establish ourselves among the peoples of the
    world as a free and democratic civil society, through our authorized representatives adopt this
    Constitution. First Chapter THE KYRGYZ REPUBLIC First Section GENERAL PRINCIPLES Article 1 1.
    The Kyrgyz Republic (Kyrgyzstan) is a sovereign, unitary, democratic republic created on the
    basis of a law-governed secular state. 2. Sovereignty of the Kyrgyz Republic is not limited and
    extends throughout its entire territory. 3. The people of the Kyrgyz Republic are the bearers of
    sovereignty and are the only source of the state power in the Kyrgyz Republic. 4. The people of
    the Kyrgyz Republic exercise their power directly and through the system of state organs and
    organs of local self-government on the basis of this Constitution and the laws of the Kyrgyz
    Republic. Only the Jogorku Kenesh and the President of the Kyrgyz Republic have the right to
    represent the people of Kyrgyzstan by whom they were elected. 5. Changes and amendments to the
    Constitution of the Kyrgyz Republic, laws of the Kyrgyz Republic and other important issues of
    state life may be put to a referendum (nationwide vote). The procedure for holding a referendum
    is established by a constitutional law. 6. The citizens of the Kyrgyz Republic elect the
    President of the Kyrgyz Republic, Deputies of the Jogorku Kenesh of the Kyrgyz Republic and
    their representatives to organs of local self-government. 7. Elections are free and are held on
    the basis of universal equal and direct suffrage by secret ballot. Citizens of the Kyrgyz
    Republic who have attained the age of 18 have the right to vote. Article 2 1. The state and its
    organs serve the whole society and not a particular group. 2. No group of people, no
    organization or any individual person has the right to assume power in the state. The usurpation
    of state power is a particularly severe crime. Article 3 1. The territory of the Kyrgyz Republic
    within its present boundaries is inviolable and indivisible. 2. The territory of the Kyrgyz
    Republic is divided into administrative territorial units established by law for the purposes of
    the organization of state government and local selfgovernment. 3. The cities of Bishkek and Osh
    are cities of national significance, and their status is determined by law. Article 4 1.
    Private, state, municipal and other forms of ownership are recognized and protected in the
    Kyrgyz Republic. The Kyrgyz Republic guarantees the diversity of property forms and their equal
    protection by law. 2. Land, its resources, air space, waters, forests, plant and animal life,
    and other natural resources are the property of the Kyrgyz Republic, are used as the basis of
    life and activity of the people of Kyrgyzstan and are under special protection of the state. 3.
    Land may also be in private, municipal and other forms of ownership. The limits of and
    procedures for exercising of the landowners’ rights and the guarantees of their protection are
    determined by law. 4. The Kyrgyz Republic protects the right of its citizens and juridical
    persons to own property as well as their [citizens’] property and its own [the Republic’s]
    property located on the territory of other states. Article 5 1. The state language of the Kyrgyz
    Republic is the Kyrgyz language. 2. In the Kyrgyz Republic, the Russian language is used as an
    official language. 3. The Kyrgyz Republic guarantees to representatives of all the nationalities
    that constitute the people of Kyrgyzstan the right of preservation of their native language,
    creation of conditions for learning and development [of the language]. 4. It is not permitted to
    infringe on citizens’ rights and freedoms because of their ignorance of the state or official
    language. Article 6 1. The state symbols of the Kyrgyz Republic are the state flag, emblem and
    anthem. Their description and the procedure for their official use are determined by law. 2. The
    capital of the Kyrgyz Republic is the city of Bishkek. 3. The monetary unit of the Kyrgyz
    Republic is a som. Second Section THE STRUCTURE AND FUNCTIONING OF THE STATE Article 7 1. The
    state power in the Kyrgyz Republic is based on the following principles: • Supremacy of the
    power of the people, represented and protected by the nationally elected head of the state— the
    President of the Kyrgyz Republic; • Division of state power into the legislative, executive and
    judicial branches, their concerted functioning and interaction; • Responsibility of the state
    organs before the nation and the implementation of their powers in the interest of the nation; •
    Delimitation of functions of state power and local self-government. 2.Within the limits of
    powers established by this Constitution, the state power in the Kyrgyz Republic is represented
    and executed by: • President of the Kyrgyz Republic; • Jogorku Kenesh of the Kyrgyz Republic; •
    Government of the Kyrgyz Republic and organs of executive power subordinate to it; •
    Constitutional Court of the Kyrgyz Republic, Supreme Court of the Kyrgyz Republic, local courts
    and judges of the Kyrgyz Republic. Article 8 1. Political parties, trade unions and other public
    associations may be organized in the Kyrgyz Republic on the basis of free will and common
    interests. The state guarantees the observance of rights and lawful interests of public
    associations. 2. Political parties may participate in state affairs only in the following forms:
    • Nomination of their candidates for the election to the Jogorku Kenesh of the Kyrgyz Republic,
    state posts and organs of local self-government; • Formation of factions in representative
    organs. 3. Religion and all cults are separate from the state. 4. In the Kyrgyz Republic the
    following is not permitted: • Merging of state and party institutions, as well as the
    subordination of state activity to party programs and decisions; • Formation and activity of
    party organizations in state establishments and organizations. State officials have the right to
    carry out their party activities outside their work activity; • Membership in parties and
    activity in support of any political party by the military personnel, employees of the organs of
    internal affairs, national security, justice, Procuratura and courts; • Organization of
    political parties on religious and ethnic grounds. Religious organizations must not pursue
    political aims and tasks; • Interference by members of religious organizations and cults with
    the activity of state organs; • Activity of foreign political parties, public associations,
    religious and other organizations detrimental to the constitutional system, state and national
    security. Article 9 1. The Kyrgyz Republic does not have goals of expansion, aggression and
    territorial claims to be resolved by means of military force. It rejects the militarization of
    national life, subordination of the government or its activity for the purposes of war. The
    Armed Forces of Kyrgyzstan are organized in accordance with the principles of self-defense and
    defensive sufficiency. 2. The right to conduct war is not recognized except in cases of
    aggression against Kyrgyzstan and other states bound by obligations of collective defense.
    Permission for each case of a unit of the Armed Forces crossing over the borders of the
    territory of the Kyrgyz Republic is a matter of decision of the Jogorku Kenesh of the Kyrgyz
    Republic adopted by a majority no less than two thirds of the total number of Deputies. 3. The
    use of Armed Forces for the resolution of internal political issues is prohibited. Military
    personnel may be called upon to liquidate the consequences of natural disasters and in other
    similar cases directly provided by law. 4. The Kyrgyz Republic observes generally recognized
    principles of international law, seeks universal and just peace, mutually beneficial
    cooperation, [and] resolution of global and regional problems in a peaceful way. Actions capable
    of disturbing the peaceful coexistence of the peoples, propaganda and encouragement of
    inter-ethnic or religious clashes are unconstitutional. Article 10 1. A state of exception in
    Kyrgyzstan may be imposed only in cases of natural disasters, direct threat to the
    constitutional system, mass disorder accompanied by violence and menace to human life, as well
    as under the circumstances and for limited periods indicated in a constitutional law. 2. A state
    of exception throughout the entire territory of the Kyrgyz Republic may be imposed only by the
    Jogorku Kenesh of the Kyrgyz Republic, but a state of exception may be imposed by the President
    of the Kyrgyz Republic in limited locations under circumstances requiring immediate action with
    a prompt, same day notification of that [act] to the Jogorku Kenesh of the Kyrgyz Republic,
    which must confirm the act of the President within no more than three days. In the absence of
    such a confirmation within the indicated time, the state of exception is cancelled. 3. Martial
    law in the Kyrgyz Republic may be imposed by the Jogorku Kenesh of the Kyrgyz Republic only in
    case of aggression against the Kyrgyz Republic. 4. A session recess of the Jogorku Kenesh of the
    Kyrgyz Republic is not permitted during a state of exception and martial law. In cases when the
    Jogorku Kenesh of the Kyrgyz Republic is not in session and a state of exception has been
    imposed by the President, the Jogorku Kenesh of the Kyrgyz Republic shall convene without a
    notice no later than the day following the introduction of the state of exception. 5. Referenda,
    elections, changes in the structure, functions and powers of state organs established by the
    Constitution of the Kyrgyz Republic are not allowed during a state of exception and martial law.
    Article 11 1. The state budget of the Kyrgyz Republic consists of the national budget and local
    budgets, comprising all expenditures and revenues of the state. The national budget is approved
    by the Jogorku Kenesh of the Kyrgyz Republic upon presentation by the Government of the Kyrgyz
    Republic. 2. Revenues of the national budget are generated by the total taxes established by
    law, other obligatory payments, income from state property and other receipts. 3. A single
    system of taxation functions on the territory of the Kyrgyz Republic. The right to impose taxes
    belongs to the Jogorku Kenesh of the Kyrgyz Republic. Laws establishing new taxes and worsening
    the standing of the tax payers are not retroactive. 4. In exceptional cases [and] for the
    protection the economic interests of the Kyrgyz Republic, the Government of the Kyrgyz Republic
    has the right to adopt temporary measures in the sphere of taxation by changing individual tax
    rates and other obligatory budget payments with prompt notification of the Jogorku Kenesh of the
    Kyrgyz Republic. 5. The report on the execution of the national budget is approved by the
    Jogorku Kenesh of the Kyrgyz Republic. Article 12 1. The Constitution has the supreme juridical
    force and direct effect in the Kyrgyz Republic. 2. Laws and other normative legal acts are
    adopted on the basis of the Constitution. 3. International treaties and agreements that have,
    according to a procedure established by law, come into force [and] to which the Kyrgyz Republic
    is a party as well as generally accepted principles and norms of international law are a
    component of the legislation of the Kyrgyz Republic </constitution>
