<?xml-model href="../constitution_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<constitution country="Latvia">
    <meta>
        <source>
            <title>Latvia Constitution</title>
            <container/>
            <url>https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Latvia_2016</url>
        </source>
    </meta>
    <body><preamble>PREAMBLE The people of Latvia, in freely elected Constitutional Assembly, have
            adopted the following State Constitution: The State of Latvia, proclaimed on 18 November
            1918, has been <nationalism>established by uniting historical Latvian lands and on the basis of the
            unwavering will of the Latvian nation</nationalism> to have <sovereignty>its own State and its inalienable right of
            self-determination in order to guarantee the existence and development of the Latvian
            nation</sovereignty>, <language lang_type="native">its language</language> and <nationalism>culture</nationalism> throughout the centuries, to ensure <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">freedom</ind_rights> and <peace>promote
            welfare of the people of Latvia</peace> and each individual. The people of Latvia won their 
            State in the War of Liberation. <gov>They consolidated the system of government and adopted
            the Constitution in a freely elected Constitutional Assembly</gov>. <international>The people of Latvia did
            not recognise the occupation regimes</international>, resisted them and <sovereignty>regained their freedom by
            restoring national independence on 4 May 1990 on the basis of continuity of the State</sovereignty>.
            <nationalism>They honour their freedom fighters</nationalism>, <international>commemorate victims of foreign powers, condemn the
            Communist and Nazi totalitarian regimes and their crimes</international>. Latvia as <gov>democratic, socially
            responsible and national state is based on the rule of law</gov> and on <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">respect for human
            dignity and freedom</ind_rights>; it recognises and protects <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">fundamental human rights</ind_rights> and <ind_rights ind_type="racial-equality">respects
            ethnic minorities</ind_rights>. The people of Latvia protect <sovereignty>their sovereignty, national
            independence, territory, territorial integrity</sovereignty> and <gov>democratic system of government of
            the State of Latvia.</gov> Since ancient times, <nationalism>the identity of Latvia in the European
            cultural space has been shaped by Latvian and Liv traditions, Latvian folk wisdom,</nationalism> <language lang_type="native">the
            Latvian language</language>, universal human and <religion r_type="neutral">Christian values</religion>. <nationalism>Loyalty to Latvia</nationalism>,<language lang_type="native"> the Latvian
            language as the only official language</language>, <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">freedom, equality, solidarity, justice</ind_rights>, honesty,
            work ethic and family are the foundations of a cohesive society. Each individual takes
            care of oneself, one’s relatives and the common good of society by acting responsibly
            toward other people, <nationalism>future generations</nationalism>, the environment and nature. <international>While acknowledging
            its equal status in the international community, Latvia protects its national interests
            and promotes sustainable and democratic development of a united Europe and the world</international>.
            <religion r_type="neutral">God, bless Latvia!</religion></preamble>
        <chapter>
            <chap_title>CHAPTER I. GENERAL PROVISIONS</chap_title>
            <section>
                <s_text>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 1</a_header>
                        <a_text><gov> Latvia is an independent democratic republic</gov>.</a_text>
                    </article>

                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 2</a_header>
                        <a_text> <sovereignty>The sovereign power of the State of Latvia</sovereignty><consent> is vested in the people
                            of Latvia</consent>.</a_text>
                    </article>

                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 3</a_header>
                        <a_text> The territory of the State of Latvia, <international>within the borders
                            established by international agreements,</international><sovereignty> consists of Vidzeme, Latgale,
                            Kurzeme and Zemgale</sovereignty>.</a_text>
                    </article>

                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 4</a_header>
                        <a_text><language lang_type="native"> The Latvian language is the official language in the Republic of 
                            Latvia.</language><symbols> The national flag of Latvia shall be red with a band of
                            white</symbols>.</a_text>
                    </article>
                </s_text>
            </section>
        </chapter></body>
</constitution>
