<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../constitution_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<constitution country="lithuania">
    <meta>
        <source>
            <title/>
            <container/>
            <url>https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Lithuania_2006</url>
        </source>
    </meta>
    <body><preamble>PREAMBLE THE LITHUANIAN NATION – having created the State of Lithuania many
            centuries ago, – having based its legal foundations on the Lithuanian Statutes and the
            Constitutions of the Republic of Lithuania, – having for centuries staunchly defended
            its freedom and independence, – having preserved its spirit, native language, writing,
            and customs, – embodying the innate right of the human being and the Nation to live and
            create freely in the land of their fathers and forefathers—in the independent State of
            Lithuania, – fostering national concord in the land of Lithuania, – striving for an
            open, just, and harmonious civil society and State under the rule of law, by the will of
            the citizens of the reborn State of Lithuania, adopts and proclaims this</preamble>
        <chapter>
            <chap_title>CHAPTER I. THE STATE OF LITHUANIA </chap_title>
            <section>Article 1 The State of Lithuania shall be an independent democratic
                republic.</section>
            <section> Article 2 The State of Lithuania shall be created by the Nation. Sovereignty
                shall belong to the Nation.</section>
            <section> Article 3 No one may restrict or limit the sovereignty of the Nation or make
                claims to the sovereign powers belonging to the entire Nation. The Nation and each
                citizen shall have the right to resist anyone who encroaches on the independence,
                territorial integrity, and constitutional order of the State of Lithuania by
                force.</section>
            <section>Article 4 The Nation shall execute its supreme sovereign power either directly
                or through its democratically elected representatives.</section>
            <section> Article 5 In Lithuania, State power shall be executed by the Seimas, the
                President of the Republic and the Government, and the Judiciary. The scope of power
                shall be limited by the Constitution. State institutions shall serve the people. </section>
            <section>Article 6 The Constitution shall be an integral and directly applicable act.
                Everyone may defend his rights by invoking the Constitution.</section>
            <section>Article 7 Any law or other act, which is contrary to the Constitution, shall be
                invalid. Only laws which are published shall be valid. Ignorance of the law shall
                not exempt one from liability. </section>
            <section>Article 8 Seizure of State power or of its institution by force shall be
                considered anti-constitutional actions, which are unlawful and invalid. </section>
            <section>Article 9 The most significant issues concerning the life of the State and the
                Nation shall be decided by referendum. In the cases established by law, the Seimas
                shall announce a referendum. A referendum shall also be announced if not less than
                300,000 citizens with the electoral right so request. The procedure for the
                announcement and execution of a referendum shall be established by law. </section>
            <section>Article 10 The territory of the State of Lithuania shall be integral and shall
                not be divided into any State-like formations. The State boundaries may be altered
                only by an international treaty of the Republic of Lithuania after it has been
                ratified by 4/5 [four-fifths] of all the Members of the Seimas. </section>
            <section>Article 11 The administrative units of the territory of the State of Lithuania
                and their boundaries shall be established by law. </section>
            <section>Article 12 Citizenship of the Republic of Lithuania shall be acquired by birth
                and other grounds established by law. With the exception of individual cases
                provided for by law, no one may be a citizen of both the Republic of Lithuania and
                another state at the same time. The procedure for the acquisition and loss of
                citizenship shall be established by law. </section>
            <section>Article 13 The State of Lithuania shall protect its citizens abroad. It shall
                be prohibited to extradite a citizen of the Republic of Lithuania to another state
                unless an international treaty of the Republic of Lithuania establishes otherwise. </section>
            <section>Article 14 Lithuanian shall be the State language. </section>
            <section>Article 15 The colours of the State flag shall be yellow, green, and red. The
                Coat-of-Arms of the State shall be a white Vytis on a red field. The State
                Coat-of-Arms, flag and their use shall be established by laws. </section>
            <section>Article 16 The anthem of the State shall be “Tautiška giesme” by Vincas
                Kudirka.</section>
            <section>Article 17 The capital of the State of Lithuania shall be the city of Vilnius,
                the long-standing historical capital of Lithuania.</section>
        </chapter>
    </body>
</constitution>
