<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../constitution_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<constitution country="Lithuania">
    <meta>
        <source>
            <title/>
            <container/>
            <url>https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Lithuania_2006</url>
        </source>
    </meta>
    <body><preamble>PREAMBLE THE LITHUANIAN NATION – having created the State of Lithuania
                <nationalism>many centuries ago</nationalism>, – having based its <gov>legal
                foundations on the Lithuanian Statutes and the Constitutions of the Republic of
                Lithuania</gov>, – having for centuries staunchly defended its <sovereignty>freedom
                and independence</sovereignty>, – having preserved its spirit, <language>native
                language</language>, writing, and <nationalism>customs</nationalism>, – embodying
            the <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">innate right of the human being</ind_rights> and the
                <sovereignty>Nation to live and create freely</sovereignty> in the land of their
            fathers and forefathers—in the <sovereignty>independent State of
            Lithuania</sovereignty>, – fostering <!--        "national concord" = "a national state of agreement"-->
            <consent>national concord</consent> in the land of Lithuania, – striving for an open,
            just, and <peace>harmonious</peace>
            <gov>civil society</gov> and State under the <gov>rule of law</gov>,<consent> by the
                will of the citizens</consent> of the reborn State of Lithuania, adopts and
            proclaims this</preamble>
        <chapter>
            <chap_title>CHAPTER I. THE STATE OF LITHUANIA </chap_title>
            <section>
                <s_text>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 1 </a_header>
                        <a_text>The State of Lithuania shall be an <sovereignty>independent</sovereignty> <gov>democratic</gov>
                                republic.</a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 2 </a_header>
                        <a_text>The State of Lithuania shall be created by the Nation.
                                <sovereignty>Sovereignty shall belong to the
                            Nation.</sovereignty></a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 3 </a_header>
                        <a_text><sovereignty>No one may restrict or limit the sovereignty</sovereignty> of the Nation or make
                            claims to the sovereign powers belonging to the entire Nation. <sovereignty>The
                            Nation and each citizen shall have the right to resist anyone who
                            encroaches on the independence,</sovereignty> territorial integrity, and
                            constitutional order of the State of Lithuania by force.</a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 4 </a_header>
                        <a_text>The Nation shall execute its supreme sovereign power either
                                <gov>directly</gov> or through its <gov>democratically</gov> <elections>elected
                                representatives</elections>.</a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 5 </a_header>
                        <a_text>In Lithuania, <separation>State power shall be executed by the
                                Seimas, the President of the Republic and the Government, and the
                                Judiciary. The scope of power shall be limited by the
                                Constitution.</separation><consent>State institutions shall serve
                                the people</consent>. </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 6 </a_header>
                        <a_text>The Constitution shall be an integral and directly applicable act.
                            Everyone may defend <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">his rights by invoking the Constitution</ind_rights>.</a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 7 </a_header>
                        <a_text>Any law or other act, which is contrary to the Constitution, shall
                            be invalid. Only laws which are published shall be valid. <ind_rights ind_type="legal">Ignorance of
                            the law shall not exempt one from liability</ind_rights>. </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 8 </a_header>
                        <a_text><gov>Seizure of State power or of its institution by force shall be
                                considered anti-constitutional actions,</gov> which are unlawful and
                                invalid.
                        </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 9 </a_header>
                        <a_text>The most significant issues concerning the life of the State
                                and the Nation shall be decided by <elections>referendum</elections>. In the cases
                            established by law, the Seimas shall announce a referendum. <elections>A referendum
                            shall also be announced if not less than 300,000 citizens with the
                            electoral right so request.</elections> The procedure for the announcement and
                            execution of a referendum shall be established by law. </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 10 </a_header>
                        <a_text><gov>The territory of the State of Lithuania shall be integral and
                                shall not be divided into any State-like formations.</gov> The State
                            boundaries may be altered only by an <gov>international treaty of the
                            Republic of Lithuania after it has been ratified by 4/5 [four-fifths</gov>] of
                            all the Members of the Seimas.</a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 11 </a_header>
                        <a_text><gov>The administrative units of the territory of the State of
                                Lithuania</gov> and their boundaries shall be established by law.
                        </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <!--               ie, anyone born in lithuania has the right to be a citizen-->
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 12 </a_header>
                        <a_text><ind_rights ind_type="citizenship">Citizenship of the Republic of
                                Lithuania shall be acquired by birth</ind_rights> and other grounds
                            established by law. With the exception of individual cases provided for
                            by law, <ind_rights ind_type="citizenship">no one may be a citizen of both the Republic of Lithuania and
                            another state</ind_rights> at the same time. The procedure for the acquisition and
                            loss of citizenship shall be established by law. </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 13 </a_header>
                        <a_text><ind_rights ind_type="citizenship">The State of Lithuania shall
                                protect its citizens abroad.</ind_rights> It shall be <ind_rights ind_type="citizenship">prohibited to
                            extradite a citizen</ind_rights> of the Republic of Lithuania to another state
                                <international>unless an international treaty of the Republic of
                                Lithuania establishes otherwise.</international>
                        </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 14 </a_header>
                        <a_text><language>Lithuanian shall be the State language.
                            </language></a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 15 </a_header>
                        <a_text><symbols>The colours of the State flag shall be yellow, green, and
                                red</symbols>. <symbols>The Coat-of-Arms of the State shall be a
                                white Vytis on a red field.</symbols> The State Coat-of-Arms, flag
                            and their use shall be established by laws. </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 16 </a_header>
                        <a_text><symbols>The anthem of the State shall be “Tautiška giesme” by
                                Vincas Kudirka</symbols>.</a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 17 </a_header>
                        <a_text><capital>The capital of the State of Lithuania shall be the city of
                                Vilnius, the long-standing historical capital of
                            Lithuania</capital>.</a_text>
                    </article>
                </s_text>
            </section>
        </chapter>
    </body>
</constitution>
