<?xml-model href="../constitution_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<constitution country="Russia">
    <meta>
        <source>
            <title>Russia Constitution</title>
            <container/>
            <url>https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Russia_2014</url>
        </source>
    </meta>
    <body><preamble>PREAMBLE We, the multinational people of the Russian Federation, united by a
            common fate on our land, establishing human rights and freedoms, civil peace and accord,
            preserving the historically established State unity, proceeding from universally
            acknowledged principles of equality and self-determination of peoples, revering the
            memory of ancestors who have passed on to us their love for the Fatherland and faith in
            good and justice, reviving the sovereign statehood of Russia and asserting the firmness
            of its democratic basis, striving to ensure the well-being and prosperity of Russia,
            proceeding from the responsibility for our Fatherland before present and future
            generations, recognizing ourselves to be a part of the world community, do hereby adopt
            THE CONSTITUTION OF THE RUSSIAN FEDERATION.</preamble>
        <chapter>
            <chap_title>SECTION ONE CHAPTER 1. THE BASIS OF THE CONSTITUTIONAL SYSTEM</chap_title>
            <section>Article 1 The Russian Federation - Russia is a democratic federative
                law-governed state with a republican form of government. The names Russian
                Federation and Russia are equivalent.</section>
            <section>Article 2 Man, his rights and freedoms shall be the supreme value. The
                recognition, observance and protection of human and civil rights and freedoms shall
                be an obligation of the State.</section>
            <section>Article 3 The bearer of sovereignty and the sole source of power in the Russian
                Federation shall be its multinational people. The people shall exercise its power
                directly, as well as through State government bodies and local self-government
                bodies. The supreme direct expression of the power of the people shall be referendum
                and free elections. Nobody may usurp power in the Russian Federation. The seizure of
                power or usurpation of State authority shall be prosecuted under federal
                law.</section>
            <section>Article 4 The sovereignty of the Russian Federation shall extend to the
                entirety of its territory. The Constitution of the Russian Federation and federal
                laws shall have supremacy on the entire territory of the Russian Federation. The
                Russian Federation shall ensure the integrity and inviolability of its
                territory.</section>
            <section>Article 5 The Russian Federation shall consist of republics, krays, oblasts,
                cities of federal significance, an autonomous oblast and autonomous okrugs, which
                shall have equal rights as constituent entities of the Russian Federation. A
                republic (state) shall have its own constitution and legislation. A kray, oblast,
                city of federal significance, autonomous oblast and autonomous okrug shall have its
                own charter and legislation. The federal structure of the Russian Federation shall
                be based on its State integrity, the unity of the system of State power, the
                division of matters of authority and powers between State government bodies of the
                Russian Federation and State government bodies of constituent entities of the
                Russian Federation, the equality and self-determination of peoples in the Russian
                Federation. All constituent entities of the Russian Federation shall be equal with
                one another in relations with federal State government bodies.</section>
            <section>Article 6 Citizenship of the Russian Federation shall be acquired and
                terminated in accordance with federal law, and shall be one and equal, irrespective
                of the grounds on which it is acquired. Every citizen of the Russian Federation
                shall enjoy all rights and freedoms on its territory and shall bear equal
                responsibilities as envisaged in the Constitution of the Russian Federation. A
                citizen of the Russian Federation may not be deprived of his (her) citizenship or of
                the right to change it.</section>
            <section>Article 7 The Russian Federation shall be a social state whose policy is aimed
                at creating conditions ensuring a worthy life and a free development of Man. In the
                Russian Federation the labour and health of people shall be protected, a guaranteed
                minimum wage shall be established, State support shall be provided for the family,
                maternity, fatherhood and childhood, to the disabled and to elderly citizens, the
                system of social services shall be developed and State pensions, allowances and
                other social security guarantees shall be established.</section>
            <section>Article 8 In the Russian Federation the integrity of economic space, free flow
                of goods, services and financial resources, support of competition, and the freedom
                of economic activity shall be guaranteed. In the Russian Federation private, State,
                municipal and other forms of property shall be recognized and shall be protected on
                an equal basis.</section>
            <section>Article 9 Land and other natural resources shall be utilized and protected in
                the Russian Federation as the basis of the life and activity of the peoples living
                on the territories concerned. Land and other natural resources may be subject to
                private, State, municipal and other forms of ownership.</section>
            <section>Article 10 State power in the Russian Federation shall be exercised on the
                basis of its division into legislative, executive and judicial authority. Bodies of
                legislative, executive and judicial authority shall be independent.</section>
            <section>Article 11 State power in the Russian Federation shall be exercised by the
                President of the Russian Federation, the Federal Assembly (the Council of Federation
                and the State Duma), the Government of the Russian Federation, and the courts of the
                Russian Federation. State power in constituent entities of the Russian Federation
                shall be exercised by bodies of State government formed by those constituent
                entities. The division of authorities and powers among State government bodies of
                the Russian Federation and State government bodies of constituent entities of the
                Russian Federation shall be established by this Constitution, the Federation Treaty
                and other treaties on the division of authorities and powers.</section>
            <section>Article 12 Local self-government shall be recognized and guaranteed in the
                Russian Federation. Local self-government shall be independent within the limits of
                its competence. Bodies of local self-government shall not form part of the system of
                State government bodies.</section>
            <section>Article 13 Ideological diversity shall be recognized in the Russian Federation.
                No ideology shall be proclaimed as State ideology or as obligatory. Political
                diversity and the multi-party system shall be recognized in the Russian Federation.
                Public associations shall be equal before the law. The establishment and activities
                of public associations whose goals and activities are aimed at the forcible changing
                of the basis of the constitutional order and at violating the integrity of the
                Russian Federation, at undermining its security, at creating armed units, and at
                instigating social, racial, national and religious strife shall be
                prohibited.</section>
            <section>Article 14 The Russian Federation shall be a secular state. No religion may be
                established as the State religion or as obligatory. Religious associations shall be
                separate from the State and shall be equal before the law.</section>
            <section>Article 15 The Constitution of the Russian Federation shall have supreme legal
                force, direct effect and shall be applicable on the entire territory of the Russian
                Federation. Laws and other legal acts, which are adopted in the Russian Federation,
                must not contradict the Constitution of the Russian Federation. State government
                bodies, local self-government bodies, officials, citizens and their associations
                shall be obliged to observe the Constitution of the Russian Federation and laws.
                Laws must be officially published. Unpublished laws shall not have force. Any
                normative legal acts concerning human and civil rights, freedoms and obligations
                shall not have force unless they have been officially published for the information
                of the general public. Universally recognized principles and norms of international
                law as well as international agreements of the Russian Federation should be an
                integral part of its legal system. If an international agreement of the Russian
                Federation establishes rules, which differ from those stipulated by law, then the
                rules of the international agreement shall be applied.</section>
            <section>Article 16 The provisions of this Chapter of the Constitution shall constitute
                the fundamental principles of the constitutional order of the Russian Federation and
                may not be changed except in accordance with the procedure established by this
                Constitution. No other provisions of this Constitution may conflict with the
                fundamental principles of the constitutional order of the Russian
                Federation.</section>
        </chapter></body>
</constitution>
