
<?xml-model href="../constitution_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<constitution country="Tajikistan">
    
    <meta>
        <source>
            <title> Tajikistan 1994 (rev. 2016)</title>
            <container>Constitute Project</container>
            <url>https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Tajikistan_2016</url>
        </source>
    </meta>
    <body>
   
    <preamble>PREAMBLE
        WE, THE PEOPLE OF TAJIKISTAN, As <international>an inseparable part of the world community</international>, Realizing our debt and our
        responsibility to the past, present and future generations, Understanding the<sovereignty> necessity of ensuring the sovereignty</sovereignty> and development
        of our State, Recognizing as unshakable the freedom and rights of man, Respecting the <ind_rights ind_type="racial-equality">equality of rights and friendship of all
        nations and nationalities</ind_rights>, Seeking to build a just society, ADOPT AND PROCLAIM THIS CONSTITUTION</preamble>
 
        <chapter>
            <chap_title>CHAPTER 1. FOUNDATIONS OF THE CONSTITUTIONAL SYSTEM</chap_title>
           
            <section>
                <s_text>
               
            <article>
                        <a_header>Article 1 </a_header>
                        <a_text>The Republic of Tajikistan is a <sovereignty>sovereign</sovereignty>, <gov>democratic</gov>, law-governed, <separation>secular</separation>, and <sovereignty>unitary</sovereignty> State. The form of
                            the governance of the Republic of Tajikistan is <gov>Presidential</gov>. Tajikistan is a social State the policy of which
                            is aimed at providing conditions that <ind_rights ind_type="misc">ensure dignified life and free human development</ind_rights>. "Republic of Tajikistan"
                            and "Tajikistan" are equivalent terms.</a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 2 </a_header>
                        <a_text> The <language>State language of Tajikistan is the Tajik language</language>. <language>Russian is the language of communication between
                            the nationalities</language>. All <ind_rights ind_type="racial-equality">nations and nationalities living on the territory of the Republic have the right to
                            freely use their native language</ind_rights>.</a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 3 </a_header>
                        <a_text>The State symbols of the Republic of Tajikistan are the <symbols>flag, the emblem, and the national anthem</symbols>. </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 4 </a_header>
                        <a_text>The capital of Tajikistan is the city of <capital>Dushanbe</capital>.</a_text>
                    </article>

                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 5</a_header>
                        <a_text>Human, its <ind_rights ind_type="misc">rights and freedoms are the highest value</ind_rights>. The
                            <ind_rights ind_type="misc">life, honor, dignity and other natural rights of
                            man are inviolable</ind_rights>. The <ind_rights ind_type="legal">rights and freedoms of man and citizen are recognized, observed, and protected by the
                                State</ind_rights>. </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 6 </a_header>
                        <a_text>In Tajikistan, the <nationalism>people are the bearer of sovereignty and the sole source of the State power</nationalism>, which they
                           <gov> exercise directly as well as through their representatives</gov>. The ultimate <nationalism>direct expression of the power of the
                            people is a national referendum</nationalism> and <elections>elections</elections>. The <ind_rights ind_type="racial-equality">citizens of Tajikistan, regardless of their nationalities,
                            constitute the people of Tajikistan</ind_rights>.<consent> No single social organization, political party, group of people or
                            individual has the right to usurp State power. The usurpation of power or infringement on its authorities is
                            prohibited</consent>. The <gov>right to represent the entire people of Tajikistan belongs only to the President and the Majlisi
                            Milli and the Majlisi Namoyandagon of the Majlisi Oli</gov> of the Republic of Tajikistan at their joint session.
                        </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 7 </a_header>
                        <a_text> The territory of Tajikistan is <sovereignty>indivisible and inviolable</sovereignty>. Tajikistan consists of the Gorno-Badakhshan
                            Autonomous Oblast, oblasts (areas), cities, rayons (regions), settlements, and villages. The State secures the
                         <sovereignty>   sovereignty, independence and territorial integrity</sovereignty> of the Republic. Propaganda and actions aimed to divide the
                            unity of the State are prohibited. The procedure for creating and changing administrative-territorial units is
                            regulated by a constitutional law.</a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 8 </a_header>
                        <a_text>In Tajikistan, public life shall be developed on the basis of <parties p_type="multi">political and ideological pluralism</parties>. No single
                            ideology of a party, social association, religious organization, movement, or group may be recognized as the
                            State [ideology]. <ind_rights ind_type="assembly">Social associations</ind_rights> and <parties p_type="multi">political parties</parties> are created and function within the framework of the
                            Constitution and laws. <separation>Religious unions are separate from the State and may not interfere with State affairs.</separation>
                            Creation and functioning of social associations and political parties<ind_rights ind_type="racial-equality"> propagating racism, nationalism, social
                            and religious enmity</ind_rights>, or encouraging forcible overthrow of the constitutional system and organization of armed
                            groups are prohibited. The <international>activity of political parties of other countries, establishing national and religious
                            parties, including funding of political parties by foreign countries and organizations, foreign legal entities
                            and citizens shall be prohibited</international>.</a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 9 </a_header>
                        <a_text>The State power is based on the principle of its <separation>division into legislative, executive, and
                            judicial</separation>.</a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 10 </a_header>
                        <a_text>The Constitution of Tajikistan has the supreme juridical force [and] its norms have direct effect. <consent>Laws and
                            other legal acts contradicting the Constitution have no juridical force</consent>. The State and all its organs,
                            officials, citizens and their associations are obligated to observe and implement the Constitution and laws of
                            the Republic. <international>International legal acts recognized by Tajikistan are a constituent part</international> of the legal system of
                            the Republic. In case of <consent>disparity between the laws of the Republic and the recognized international legal acts,
                                the norms of the international acts apply</consent>. <international>Laws and international legal acts recognized by Tajikistan enter
                                force after their official publication</international>.</a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 11</a_header>
                        <a_text>Tajikistan, <peace>conducting peaceful policy, respects the sovereignty and independence of other States</peace> [and]
                            determines its<international> foreign policy on the basis of international norms</international>. <peace>War propaganda is prohibited</peace>. Tajikistan,
                            guided by the supreme interests of the people, <international>may join commonwealths and other international organizations as
                            well as withdraw from them [and] establish relations with foreign countries</international>. The State <international>cooperates with
                            compatriots [living] abroad</international>. </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 12</a_header>
                        <a_text> Foundations of the economy of Tajikistan are composed of various forms of property. The State guarantees
                            the freedom of economic and entrepreneurial activity, equality of rights, and legal protection of all forms of
                            property including <property prop_type="private">private property</property>.</a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 13 </a_header>
                        <a_text>The <property prop_type="public">land, its resources, water, airspace, fauna and flora, and other natural resources are exclusively the
                            property of the State</property>, and the State guarantees their effective use in the interests of the people.</a_text>
                    </article>
                </s_text>
            </section>
        </chapter>
    </body>
</constitution>
