<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../constitution_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<constitution country="Turkmenistan">
    <meta>
        <source>
            <title/>
            <container/>
            <url>https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Turkmenistan_2008</url>
        </source>

    </meta>
    <body><preamble>PREAMBLE We, the people of Turkmenistan, based on our <sovereignty>inalienable
                right to determine our destiny;</sovereignty><nationalism> Proceeding from the
                responsibility for present and future of the Motherland;</nationalism>
            <nationalism>Expressing loyalty to the covenant of ancestors</nationalism> to
                <peace>live in unity, peace and harmony;</peace> With the aim of protecting the
            national values and interests, <sovereignty>strengthening the independence, sovereignty,
            </sovereignty>the status of permanent neutrality of Turkmenistan; <ind_rights
                ind_type="liberty">Guaranteeing the rights and freedoms of each person and
                citizen</ind_rights>, and seeking to <peace>ensure civil peace and national accord
                in the society,</peace> to substantiate the <gov>foundations of democracy and
                democratic, legal,</gov>
            <religion r_type="church-state">secular state</religion>, we adopt the present
            Constitution - the Basic Law of Turkmenistan. </preamble><chapter>
            <chap_title>SECTION I. FUNDAMENTALS OF THE CONSTITUTIONAL SYSTEM OF
                TURKMENISTAN</chap_title>
            <section>
                <s_text>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 1 </a_header>
                        <a_text><gov>Turkmenistan is a democratic, legal</gov> and <religion
                                r_type="secular">secular state</religion> in which the government
                            takes <gov>the form of presidential republic</gov>. Turkmenistan
                            exercises the <sovereignty>complete power and complete authority on its
                                territory, and independently conducts the internal and foreign
                                policy</sovereignty>. The state sovereignty and territory of
                            Turkmenistan are homogeneous and indivisible. The State
                                <sovereignty>protects the independence, territorial integrity of
                                Turkmenistan</sovereignty>, and constitutional system, and provides
                            law and order. Turkmenistan, by law, <international>has the status of
                                permanent neutrality</international>. <international>The United
                                Nations General Assembly resolution "Permanent Neutrality of
                                Turkmenistan"</international> dated 12 December 1995: "1. Recognizes
                            and supports the declared status of permanent neutrality of
                            Turkmenistan; 2. Calls upon the member states of the United Nations to
                            respect and support this status of Turkmenistan and also <sovereignty>to
                                respect its independence, sovereignty and territorial
                                integrity</sovereignty>." The permanent neutrality of Turkmenistan,
                            recognized by the world community, <international>is the basis of its
                                domestic and foreign policy</international>. </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 2 </a_header>
                        <a_text>The people are the <consent>bearer of and the sole source of the
                                state power in Turkmenistan</consent>. The people of Turkmenistan
                                <elections>exercise their power directly or through representative
                                bodies</elections>. <treason>No part (group) of the people,
                                organization or individuals, have the right to abrogate the state
                                power</treason>. </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 3 </a_header>
                        <a_text>In Turkmenistan, the people are the highest value of the society and
                            the state. <gov>The state is responsible for every citizen</gov> and
                            creates conditions for <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">free development
                                of the individual, protects the life, honour, dignity and freedom,
                                personal integrity, natural and inalienable rights of the
                                citizen</ind_rights>. Every citizen is responsible before the State
                            for the responsibilities entrusted to him by the Constitution and laws.
                        </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 4 </a_header>
                        <a_text>State power is based on the principle of <separation>separation of
                                powers between the legislative, executive and judicial branches,
                                which operate independently, balancing each other</separation>.
                        </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 5 </a_header>
                        <a_text>The state and all of its organs and officials are linked by law and
                            constitutional order. The Constitution of Turkmenistan is the Basic Law
                            of the State. Rules and regulations laid down in it are unswervingly
                            applicable. The laws and other legal acts that contradict the
                            Constitution are null and void. The normative-legal acts of the
                            government and administration, and the local self-government, are
                            published for general information or made available through other means,
                            except when they contain state or other secrets protected by law. The
                            normative-legal Acts affecting the rights and freedom of the individual
                            and citizen, if not brought to the general information of the public,
                            are invalid from the time of their adoption. </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 6 </a_header>
                        <a_text>Turkmenistan, being a full subject of the global community, has the
                                <international>foreign policy of permanent neutrality,
                                non-interference in the internal affairs of other countries,
                                refrains from the use of force and participation in military blocs
                                and alliances, promotes peaceful, friendly and mutually beneficial
                                relations with countries in the region and states of the whole
                                world</international>. Turkmenistan recognizes the priority of the
                                <international>universally accepted norms of international
                                law</international>. <international>If an international treaty
                                (contract) of Turkmenistan establishes rules other than those
                                stipulated by the laws of Turkmenistan, the rules of international
                                treaty will apply</international>. </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 7 </a_header>
                        <a_text><sovereignty>Turkmenistan has its own citizenship.</sovereignty> The
                            citizenship is acquired, retained and lost in accordance with the law. <!--                            I know this whole paragraph could be tagged together, but i opted to split it up    -->
                            <!--                            I think each seperate tag is a seperate idea on it's own-->
                            <ind_rights ind_type="citizenship">Citizenship of another state is not
                                recognized for the citizens of Turkmenistan</ind_rights>.
                                <ind_rights ind_type="citizenship">No one can be deprived of
                                citizenship or the right to change citizenship</ind_rights>. A
                            citizen of Turkmenistan <ind_rights ind_type="citizenship">cannot be
                                extradited to another state or expelled from the limits of
                                Turkmenistan, or restricted in the right to return to the
                                homeland</ind_rights>. <ind_rights ind_type="citizenship">The
                                citizens of Turkmenistan are guaranteed the protection and patronage
                                of the state in the territory of Turkmenistan and beyond its
                                borders</ind_rights>. </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 8 </a_header>
                        <a_text>Foreign nationals and stateless persons enjoy the rights and
                            freedoms, and bear the responsibilities, of citizens of Turkmenistan in
                            accordance with law <international>and international treaties of
                                Turkmenistan</international>. Turkmenistan, <international>in
                                accordance with universally recognized norms of international right
                                and in the order established by the law, gives refuge to foreign
                                citizens and stateless persons</international>. </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 9 </a_header>
                        <a_text><property prop_type="private">The property is inviolable</property>.
                                <property prop_type="private">Turkmenistan approves the right to
                                private ownership of the means of production, land and other
                                material and intellectual values</property>. <property
                                prop_type="public">They can also belong to the associations of
                                citizens and the state</property>. The law establishes <property
                                prop_type="public">objects that are exclusive property of the
                                state</property>. <property prop_type="private">The state guarantees
                                equal protection and creation of equal conditions for development of
                                all forms of ownership</property>. <property prop_type="private"
                                >Confiscation of property is prohibited</property>, except for the
                            property acquired by means prohibited by law. Forced confiscation of
                            property is permissible only in cases stipulated by law. </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 10 </a_header>
                        <a_text>The economy of Turkmenistan is based on the principles of <economic
                                e_type="free">market relations</economic>. The state encourages and
                            supports entrepreneurship, promotes development of small and medium
                            enterprises. </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 11 </a_header>
                        <a_text>The state is responsible for <nationalism>safeguarding the national
                                historical and cultural heritage</nationalism>, natural environment,
                            ensuring <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">equality between
                                social</ind_rights> and <ind_rights ind_type="racial-equality"
                                >ethnic communities</ind_rights>. The state encourages scientific
                            and artistic creativity and distribution of its positive results,
                                <international>promotes development of international
                                relations</international> in the fields of science, culture,
                            education and training, sports and tourism. </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 12 </a_header>
                        <a_text>The state guarantees <religion r_type="secular">freedom of religion
                                and worship</religion>, and equality before the law. <religion
                                r_type="secular">Religious organizations are separate from the
                                state</religion>, cannot interfere in the state affairs and carry
                            out state functions. <religion r_type="secular">The public education
                                system is separate from religious organizations and is
                                secular</religion>. Each person independently determines his
                            attitude toward religion, has the right to, individually or jointly with
                            others, profess any religion or none, to express and disseminate beliefs
                            related to attitude toward religion, to participate in religious
                            observances, rituals, and ceremonies. </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 13 </a_header>
                        <a_text>In order to <sovereignty>protect the state sovereignty and security,
                                Turkmenistan has its own armed forces</sovereignty>. </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 14 </a_header>
                        <a_text><language lang_type="native">Turkmen is the state [official]
                                language of Turkmenistan</language>. <language lang_type="native"
                                >The use of their native language is guaranteed to all citizens of
                                Turkmenistan</language>. </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 15 </a_header>
                        <a_text><symbols>The State Flag, the State Emblem, and the National Anthem
                                are the Symbols of Turkmenistan</symbols>. The flag, national emblem
                            and national anthem are established and protected by law. </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 16 </a_header>
                        <a_text><levels l_type="neutral">The administrative-territorial structure of
                                Turkmenistan consists of</levels>: Velayats (provinces), cities with
                            right of Velayat, Etraps (districts), cities with right of district,
                            cities (towns) in district, settlements, Gengeshlyk. The territory of
                            one or more villages forms a Gengeshlyk. </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 17 </a_header>
                        <a_text><capital>Ashgabat is the capital of Turkmenistan</capital>.
                        </a_text>
                    </article>
                </s_text>
            </section>
        </chapter></body>
</constitution>
