

<?xml-model href="Projects/Former-Soviet/constitution_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<constitution country="Ukraine">
    <meta>
        <source>
            <title>Ukraine 1996 (rev. 2016)</title>
            <container>Constitute Project</container>
            <url>https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Ukraine_2016</url>
        </source>
    </meta>
    
    <body>
        <preamble>PREAMBLE The Verkhovna Rada of Ukraine, on behalf of the Ukrainian people -
            <ind_rights ind_type="racial-equality">citizens of Ukraine of all
                nationalities</ind_rights>, expressing the <nationalism>sovereign will of the
                    people, based on the centuries-old history of Ukrainian state-building</nationalism>
            and on the right to self-determination realised by the Ukrainian nation, all the
            Ukrainian people, <ind_rights ind_type="misc">providing for the guarantee of human
                rights and freedoms and of the worthy conditions of human life</ind_rights>,
            <peace>caring for the strengthening of civil harmony on Ukrainian soil</peace>,
            striving to develop and strengthen a <gov> democratic, social, law-based state</gov>,
            aware of our responsibility before <religion r_type="neutral">God</religion>, our own
            conscience, past, present and future generations, guided by the Act of Declaration of
            the Independence of Ukraine of 24 August 1991, approved by the national vote of 1
            December 1991, adopts this Constitution — the Fundamental Law of Ukraine.</preamble>
        <chapter>
            <chap_title>CHAPTER I. GENERAL PRINCIPLES </chap_title>
            <section>
                <s_text>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 1</a_header>
                        
                        <a_text>Ukraine is a <sovereignty>sovereign and independent</sovereignty>
                            and, <gov>democratic, social, law-based state</gov>.</a_text>
                    </article>
                    
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 2</a_header>
                        
                        <a_text>The<sovereignty> sovereignty of Ukraine extends throughout its
                            entire territory. Ukraine is a unitary state. The territory of
                            Ukraine within its present border is indivisible and
                            inviolable</sovereignty>.</a_text>
                    </article>
                    
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 3</a_header>
                        
                        <a_text>The <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">human being, his or her life and
                            health, honour and dignity</ind_rights>, inviolability and security
                            are recognised in Ukraine as the highest social value. <ind_rights
                                ind_type="liberty">Human rights and freedoms and their guarantees
                                determine the essence and orientation of the activity of the
                                State</ind_rights>,. The State is answerable to the individual for
                            its activity. To affirm and ensure <ind_rights ind_type="misc">human
                                rights and freedoms is the main duty</ind_rights> of the
                            State.</a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 4</a_header>
                        
                        <a_text>There is <ind_rights ind_type="citizenship">single citizenship in
                            Ukraine. The grounds for the acquisition and termination of
                            Ukrainian citizenship are determined by law</ind_rights>. </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 5</a_header>
                        
                        <a_text>Ukraine is a <gov>republic</gov>. The people are the bearers of
                            sovereignty and the only source of power in Ukraine. The people<parties
                                p_type="multi"> exercise power directly and through bodies of state
                                power and bodies of local self-government</parties>. The right to
                            determine and change the constitutional order in Ukraine belongs
                            exclusively to the people and <consent>shall not be usurped by the
                                State, its bodies or officials. No one shall usurp state
                                power</consent>.</a_text>
                    </article>
                    
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 6</a_header>
                        
                        <a_text>State power in Ukraine is exercised on the principles of <gov>its
                            division into legislative, executive and judicial power</gov>.
                            <gov>Bodies of legislative, executive and judicial power exercise
                                their authority within the limits</gov> established by this
                            Constitution and in accordance with the laws of Ukraine.</a_text>
                    </article>
                    
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 7</a_header>
                        
                        <a_text>In Ukraine, <gov>local self-government is recognised and
                            guaranteed</gov>.</a_text>
                    </article>
                    
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 8</a_header>
                        
                        <a_text>In Ukraine, the principle of the rule of law is recognised and
                            effective. The<consent> Constitution of Ukraine has the highest legal
                                force</consent>. Laws and other normative legal acts are adopted on
                            the basis of the Constitution of Ukraine and shall conform to it. The
                            norms of the Constitution of Ukraine are norms of direct effect. Appeals
                            to the court in defence of the <ind_rights ind_type="misc"
                                >constitutional rights and freedoms of the individual and
                                citizen</ind_rights> directly on the grounds of the Constitution of
                            Ukraine are guaranteed.</a_text>
                        <!--not
                            sure about the tag ind_rights-->
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 9</a_header>
                        
                        <a_text><international>>International treaties that are in force, agreed to
                            be binding by the Verkhovna Rada of Ukraine, are part of the
                            national legislation</international> of Ukraine. The conclusion
                            of<international> international treaties that contravene the
                                Constitution of Ukraine is possible</international> only after
                            introducing relevant amendments to the Constitution of Ukraine.</a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 10</a_header>
                        
                        <a_text>The state language of Ukraine is the <language>Ukrainian
                            language</language>. The State ensures the comprehensive development
                            and functioning of the Ukrainian language in all spheres of social life
                            throughout the entire territory of Ukraine. In Ukraine, <language>the
                                free development, use and protection of Russian, and other languages
                                of national minorities of Ukraine, is guaranteed</language>. The
                            State promotes the learning of languages of international
                            communication.<language> The use of languages in Ukraine is
                                guaranteed by the Constitution </language>of Ukraine and is
                            determined by law.</a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 11</a_header>
                        
                        <a_text>The State promotes the consolidation and development of the
                            Ukrainian nation, of <nationalism>its historical consciousness,
                                traditions and culture</nationalism>, and also the development of
                            the <ind_rights ind_type="racial-equality">ethnic, cultural, linguistic
                                and religious identity of all indigenous peoples and national
                                minorities</ind_rights> of Ukraine. </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 12</a_header>
                        
                        <a_text>Ukraine provides for the satisfaction of <ind_rights ind_type="misc"
                            >national and cultural, and linguistic needs of
                            Ukrainians</ind_rights> residing beyond the borders of the State.
                        </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 13</a_header>
                        <a_text>
                            <property prop_type="private">The land, its mineral wealth, atmosphere,
                                water and other natural resources within the territory of Ukraine,
                                the natural resources of its continental shelf, and the exclusive
                                (maritime) economic zone, are objects of the right of property of
                                the Ukrainian people</property>. Ownership rights on behalf of the
                            Ukrainian people are <separation>exercised by bodies of state power and
                                bodies of local self-government</separation> within the limits
                            determined by this Constitution. <property prop_type="private"> Every
                                citizen has the right to utilise the natural objects of the people's
                                right of property </property>in accordance with the law. Property
                            entails responsibility. Property shall not be used to the detriment of
                            the person and society. The State ensures the protection of the rights
                            of <property prop_type="private">all subjects of the right of property
                                and economic management, and the social orientation of the
                                economy</property>. All <ind_rights ind_type="legal">subjects of the
                                    right of property are equal before the law</ind_rights>.</a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 14</a_header>
                        
                        <a_text>Land is the fundamental national wealth that is under special state
                            protection. The right of property to land is guaranteed. This right is
                            acquired and realised by citizens, legal persons and the State,
                            exclusively in accordance with the law.</a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 15</a_header>
                        
                        <a_text>Social life in Ukraine is based on the principles of <ind_rights
                            ind_type="racial-equality">political, economic and ideological
                            diversity</ind_rights>. No <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">ideology
                                shall be recognised by the State as mandatory</ind_rights>.
                            Censorship is prohibited. The <ind_rights ind_type="protest">State
                                guarantees freedom of political activity not prohibited by the
                                Constitution</ind_rights> and the
                            <!--unsure of which attribute to use for freedom of pol activoty--> laws
                            of Ukraine.</a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 16</a_header>
                        
                        <a_text>To ensure ecological safety and to maintain the ecological balance
                            on the territory of Ukraine, to overcome the consequences of the
                            Chornobyl catastrophe - a <international>catastrophe of global
                                scale</international>, and to preserve the gene pool of the
                            Ukrainian people, is the duty of the State. </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 17</a_header>
                        
                        <a_text>To protect the <sovereignty>sovereignty and territorial
                            indivisibility of Ukraine</sovereignty>, and to ensure its economic
                            and informational security are the <nationalism>most important functions
                                of the State and a matter of concern for all the Ukrainian
                                people</nationalism>. The defence of Ukraine and the protection of
                            its sovereignty, territorial indivisibility and inviolability, are
                            entrusted to the Armed Forces of Ukraine. Ensuring <sovereignty>state
                                security and protecting the state border</sovereignty> of Ukraine
                            are entrusted to the respective military formations and law enforcement
                            bodies of the State, whose organisation and operational procedure are
                            determined by law. The <ind_rights ind_type="misc">Armed Forces of
                                Ukraine and other military formations shall not be used by anyone to
                                restrict the rights and freedoms of citizens</ind_rights> or with
                            the intent to overthrow the constitutional order, subvert the bodies of
                            power or obstruct their activity. The State ensures the<ind_rights
                                ind_type="legal"> social protection of citizens of Ukraine who serve
                                in the Armed Forces of Ukraine and in other military formations as
                                well as of members of their families</ind_rights>. The <ind_rights
                                    ind_type="assembly">creation and operation of any armed formations
                                    not envisaged by law are prohibited</ind_rights> on the territory of
                            Ukraine. The <international>location of foreign military bases shall not
                                be permitted on the territory of Ukraine</international>.</a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 18</a_header>
                        
                        <a_text>The <international>foreign political activity</international> of
                            Ukraine is aimed at <sovereignty>ensuring its national interests and
                                security</sovereignty> by <peace>maintaining peaceful and mutually
                                    beneficial co-operation with members of the international
                                    community</peace>, according to generally acknowledged
                            <international>principles and norms of international
                                law</international>. </a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 19</a_header>
                        
                        <a_text>The legal order in Ukraine is based on the principles according to
                            which <ind_rights ind_type="misc"> no one shall be forced to do what is
                                not envisaged by legislation</ind_rights>. Bodies of state power and
                            bodies of local self-government and their officials are obliged to act
                            only on the grounds,<consent> within the limits of authority,</consent>
                            and in the manner envisaged by the Constitution and the laws of
                            Ukraine.</a_text>
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 20</a_header>
                        
                        <a_text>The <symbols>state symbols of Ukraine are the State Flag of Ukraine,
                            the State Coat of Arms of Ukraine and the State Anthem of Ukraine.
                            The State Flag of Ukraine is a banner of two equally-sized
                            horizontal bands of blue and yellow. The Great State Coat of Arms of
                            Ukraine shall be established with the consideration of the Small
                            State Coat of Arms of Ukraine and the Coat of Arms of the
                            Zaporozhian Host</symbols>, by the law adopted by no less than
                            two-thirds of the constitutional composition of the Verkhovna Rada of
                            Ukraine. The main element of the Great State Coat of Arms of Ukraine is
                            the <symbols>Emblem of the Royal State of Volodymyr the Great (the Small
                                State Coat of Arms of Ukraine). The State Anthem of Ukraine is the
                                national anthem set to the music of M. Verbytskyi, with words that
                                are confirmed by the law adopted by no less than two-thirds of the
                                constitutional composition of the Verkhovna Rada of
                                Ukraine</symbols>. The description of the state symbols of Ukraine
                            and the procedure for their use shall be established by the law adopted
                            by no less than two-thirds of the constitutional composition of the
                            Verkhovna Rada of Ukraine. The capital of Ukraine is the City of
                            <capital>Kyiv</capital>.</a_text>
                    </article>
                </s_text>
            </section>
        </chapter>
    </body>
</constitution>