<?xml-model href="../constitution_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<constitution>
PREAMBLE
The people of Uzbekistan,

solemnly declaring their adherence to human rights and principles of state sovereignty,

being aware of their ultimate responsibility to the present and the future generations,

relying on historical experience in the development of the Uzbek statehood,

affirming their commitment to the ideals of democracy and social justice,

recognizing priority of the generally accepted norms of the international law,

aspiring to a worthy life for the citizens of the Republic,

setting forth the task of creating a humane and democratic law-governed state,

aiming to ensure civil peace and national accord,

adopt in the person of their plenipotentiary representatives the present Constitution of the Republic of Uzbekistan.

PART ONE. FUNDAMENTAL PRINCIPLES
Chapter I. STATE SOVEREIGNTY
Article 1
Uzbekistan is a sovereign democratic republic. Both names of the state “the Republic of Uzbekistan” and “Uzbekistan” shall be equivalent.

Article 2
The state shall express the will of the people and serve their interests. State bodies and officials shall be accountable to the society and citizens.

Article 3
The Republic of Uzbekistan shall determine its national-state and administrative-territorial structure, its structure of state authority and administration, and shall pursue its home and foreign policies.

The state boundary and the territory of Uzbekistan shall be inviolable and indivisible.

Article 4
The state language of the Republic of Uzbekistan shall be Uzbek.

The Republic of Uzbekistan shall ensure a respectful attitude toward the languages, customs and traditions of all nationalities and ethnic groups living on its territory, and the creation of the conditions for their development.

Article 5
The Republic of Uzbekistan shall have its state symbols: the flag, the emblem, and the anthem sanctioned by the law.

Article 6
The capital of the Republic of Uzbekistan shall be the city of Tashkent.

Chapter II. DEMOCRACY
Article 7
The people are the sole source of state power.

State power in the Republic of Uzbekistan shall be exercised in the interests of the people and solely by the bodies empowered therefore by the Constitution of the Republic of Uzbekistan and the laws passed on its basis.

Any seizure of powers belonging to state authority, suspension or termination of activity of bodies of authority contrary to the procedure prescribed by the Constitution, as well as the formation of new or parallel bodies of authority shall be regarded as unconstitutional and punishable by law.

Article 8
All citizens of the Republic of Uzbekistan, regardless of their nationality, shall constitute the people of Uzbekistan.

Article 9
Major matters of public and state life shall be submitted for a nation-wide discussion and put to universal vote of the people (referendum). The procedure for holding a referendum shall be specified by law.

Article 10
The Oliy Majlis (the Parliament of the Republic) and President of the Republic, elected by the people, shall have the exclusive right to act on behalf of the people.

No part of the society, political party, public association, movement or individual shall have the right to act on behalf of the people of Uzbekistan.

Article 11
The principle of separation of powers into the legislative, executive and judicial shall underlie the system of state authority of the Republic of Uzbekistan.

Article 12
In the Republic of Uzbekistan, public life shall develop on the basis of a diversity of political institutions, ideologies and opinions. No ideology may be established as the state.

Article 13
Democracy in the Republic of Uzbekistan shall be based on the principles common to all mankind according to which the ultimate value is a human being, his life, freedom, honour, dignity and other inalienable rights.

Democratic rights and freedoms shall be protected by the Constitution and laws.

Article 14
The state shall function on the principles of social justice and legality in the interests of well-being of the people and society.

Chapter III. SUPREMACY OF THE CONSTITUTION AND LAW
Article 15
The Constitution and laws of the Republic of Uzbekistan shall have absolute supremacy in the Republic of Uzbekistan.

The state, its bodies, officials, public associations and citizens shall act in accordance with the Constitution and laws.

Article 16
None of the provisions of the present Constitution may be interpreted in a way detrimental to the rights and interests of the Republic of Uzbekistan.

None of laws or normative legal acts may run counter to the norms and principles of the Constitution.

Chapter IV. FOREIGN POLICY
Article 17
The Republic of Uzbekistan shall have full rights in international relations. Its foreign policy shall be based on the principles of sovereign equality of states, non-use of force or threat of its use, inviolability of frontiers, peaceful settlement of disputes, non-interference in the internal affairs of other states and other universally recognized principles and norms of the international law.

The Republic may form alliances, join unions and other interstate organizations or withdraw from proceeding from the ultimate interests of the state and the people, their well-being and security.
</constitution>