<?xml-model href="../constitution_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<constitution country="Uzbekistan">
    <meta>
        <source>
            <title>Uzbekistan Constitution</title>
            <container/>
            <url>https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Uzbekistan_2011</url>
        </source>
    </meta>
    <body><preamble>PREAMBLE <consent>The people of Uzbekistan</consent>, solemnly declaring their
            adherence to <ind_rights ind_type="liberty">human rights</ind_rights> and
                <sovereignty>principles of state sovereignty</sovereignty>, <nationalism>being aware
                of their ultimate responsibility to the present and the future generations, relying
                on historical experience in the development of the Uzbek statehood,</nationalism>
            affirming their commitment to the ideals of <gov>democracy</gov> and social justice,
                <international>recognizing priority of the generally accepted norms of the
                international law</international>, aspiring to a worthy life for the citizens of the
            Republic, <gov>setting forth the task of creating a humane and democratic law-governed
                state,</gov>
            <peace>aiming to ensure civil peace and national accord,</peace>
            <gov>adopt in the person of their plenipotentiary representatives the present
                Constitution of the Republic of Uzbekistan.</gov></preamble>
        <chapter>
            <chap_title>PART ONE. FUNDAMENTAL PRINCIPLES Chapter I. STATE SOVEREIGNTY</chap_title>
            <section>
                <s_text>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 1</a_header>
                        <a_text> Uzbekistan is a <sovereignty>sovereign</sovereignty>
                            <gov>democratic republic</gov>.<sovereignty> Both names of the state
                                “the Republic of Uzbekistan” and “Uzbekistan” shall be
                                equivalent.</sovereignty></a_text>
                    </article>

                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 2</a_header>
                        <a_text><consent> The state shall express the will of the people and serve
                                their interests. State bodies and officials shall be accountable to
                                the society and citizens.</consent></a_text>
                    </article>

                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 3</a_header>
                        <a_text>
                            <gov>The Republic of Uzbekistan shall determine its national-state and
                                administrative-territorial structure, its structure of state
                                authority and administration, and shall pursue its home</gov>
                            <international>and foreign policies</international>.<sovereignty> The
                                state boundary and the territory of Uzbekistan shall be inviolable
                                and indivisible.</sovereignty></a_text>
                    </article>

                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 4</a_header>
                        <a_text>
                            <language>The state language of the Republic of Uzbekistan shall be
                                Uzbek.</language>
                            <ind_rights ind_type="racial-equality">The Republic of Uzbekistan shall
                                ensure a respectful attitude toward the languages, customs and
                                traditions of all nationalities and ethnic groups living on its
                                territory, and the creation of the conditions for their
                                development.</ind_rights></a_text>
                        <!-- Wondering if maybe we need a tolerance right attribute; ind_type="toleration" -->
                    </article>
                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 5</a_header>
                        <a_text> T<symbols>he Republic of Uzbekistan shall have its state symbols:
                                the flag, the emblem, and the anthem sanctioned by the
                                law.</symbols></a_text>
                    </article>

                    <article>
                        <a_header>Article 6</a_header>
                        <a_text><capital> The capital of the Republic of Uzbekistan shall be the
                                city of Tashkent.</capital></a_text>
                    </article>
                </s_text>
            </section>
        </chapter>
    </body>

</constitution>
